<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Just Alfred</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>The Mind-Killer</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/the-mind-killer.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I recently listened to &lt;a href="https://www.brucelee.com/podcast-blog/2018/1/10/80-kristen-ulmer-author-of-the-art-of-fear"&gt;an excellent podcast&lt;/a&gt;
that planted a framing of fear in my mind that I’ve repeated as advice to several people over the past month.
Since it seems to be so often relevant, I repeat it once more&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be better friends with your fear than with your pride.
When we say things we don’t mean, do things that hurt others or ourselves, miss opportunities,
or generally behave in ways we later regret, so often the cause is fear.
Fear of rejection, fear of offending, fear of embarrassment, fear of failure, fear of&amp;nbsp;harm&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing our fears should be a high priority, then,
and yet we’re all supposed to get over our fears, ignore them, conquer them.
At best, maybe use them for motivation.
This inhibitory reaction to fear is fueled by pride and its immediate rewards.
It feels good to feel strong in the face of a challenge even if we pay for it later.
Instead of succumbing to pride’s blinders, we should treat fear as we treat our friends.
We should acknowledge, recognize, listen to, understand, and accept it.
We shouldn’t be embarrassed by it and send it&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can be friends with our fears,
we can be honest with ourselves and make better decisions for ourselves and those we care about.
We don&amp;#8217;t have to listen to everything our friends tell us, and likewise with fear.
But we&amp;#8217;ll miss the chance to decide if we refuse to&amp;nbsp;listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try thinking of something you wish you hadn’t said or done yesterday and probe: what was the fear behind it?
How could you have acted differently if you’d recognized your true motivations?
How might this fear affect your future interactions?
Can you recognize this fear the next time it appears?
Can you ultimately assuage this&amp;nbsp;fear?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, I fail at this over and over every day.
But such is learning. I can do better&amp;nbsp;tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2018-05-14:the-mind-killer.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>The Role and Importance of Curiosity in Data Science</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/the-role-and-importance-of-curiosity-in-data-science.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Curiosity: The urge to know more.
I gave a talk last year about the role of curiosity in the practice of data science,
and I share the bits I still like here.
Now, many of us in the field have acknowledged its importance to the point of screening for it in interviews.
It’s obvious to most that healthy curiosity will lead to
serendipitous discoveries and introduce us to new skills and knowledge.
But as per my last post on ambiguity, nothing is black and white.
How does curiosity help a data scientist? Can we be too curious? What are its&amp;nbsp;downsides?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Science&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, let’s consider how curiosity assists data&amp;nbsp;science:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The goal of science, including data science, is to create new &lt;strong&gt;knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science is driven by &lt;strong&gt;hypotheses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More hypotheses of greater variety lead to a more complete &lt;strong&gt;search&lt;/strong&gt; of the space of possible&amp;nbsp;knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creativity&lt;/strong&gt; drives the generation of new&amp;nbsp;hypotheses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Curiosity&lt;/strong&gt; drives creativity and the testing of those&amp;nbsp;hypotheses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, greater curiosity will lead to more diverse hypotheses, and we will explore them faster.
This leads to a faster accumulation of knowledge.
Without curiosity, we can only follow established procedures for generating and testing hypotheses,
and we will be limited to what we already happen to&amp;nbsp;know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiosity about the task at hand helps mainly in the form of motivation.
That is, it drives the testing of hypotheses.
But the jewels, the creative hypotheses, are found when we explore seemingly unrelated territory.
This is where our minds&amp;nbsp;expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Serendipity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the wonderful features of data science is its interdisciplinarity.
I have seen people apply such a range of disciplines to their work.
Those who come from adjacent fields such as statistics, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CS&lt;/span&gt;,
or computational physics or the like can bring their experience to their practice in a direct way.
But those coming from further afield also bring important&amp;nbsp;strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some may consider social science an adjacent field, but for some reason, we tend to associate physicists
(though not chemists, despite the significant overlap in their methods)
with data science more eagerly than social scientists.
Yet, most physicists work with the luxury of
controlled experiments, explanatory models, clean data, and simple, inviolable laws.
Social scientists have to deal with
uncertainty, messy data, greater difficulty acquiring data,
unknown sources of error, and the complexity of human experience.
This, in my mind, and spoken as a former physicist, makes them
&lt;a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2018/3/225484-computational-social-science-computer-science-social-data/fulltext"&gt;especially well-equipped&lt;/a&gt;
for the demands of most data science&amp;#8212;moreso than&amp;nbsp;physicists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More distant, take philosophy.
Ethics and epistemology have been prominent subjects of philosophical discourse for millennia,
and they are absolutely relevant to the practice.
We &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; we?
Are our beliefs in our analyses justifiable? Philosophy teaches us how to think and ask questions.
It should be no surprise that fluency here would enhance a data scientist’s approach to problem solving.
Our colleague reading Marx may have a stronger sense of the contingency of labels and categories than us,
and that may lead them to conduct more thorough exploratory data analysis (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EDA&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or take art.
Art is about expression.
It often involves arousing particular affects through word, sound, shape, or color.
Storytelling is often a major part of data science.
Experience with art can inform how one presents data via argument, user interface, or data visualization.
You may find Agnes Martin, Josef Albers, or Mark Rothko confounding,
but someone moved by them will probably use color and line especially effectively in their visual&amp;nbsp;storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jkannenberg/3538952506/in/photostream/"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2266/3538952506_0a828273ba_z_d.jpg" alt="Detail of a work by Martin showing regular, rectilinear pencil lines" width="400" height="300"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/2/20/Josef_Albers%27s_painting_%27Homage_to_the_Square%27%2C_1965.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/2/20/Josef_Albers%27s_painting_%27Homage_to_the_Square%27%2C_1965.jpg" alt="A painting by Albers with stark, nested squares of slightly different colors" width="300" height="300"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Martin, left. Alberts, right. If these intrigue you, you just might be a whiz at data viz.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would love to work with someone experienced in theater acting.
I have a feeling that someone practiced in interpreting the world
through the eyes of a fictional character would ask very different and more pertinent questions
about users or a population than I&amp;nbsp;would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever your background, hobbies, or momentary fascinations,
your history informs the way you see the world, and therefore the way you do data&amp;nbsp;science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Practice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we foster curiosity in practice?
I like to make sure people are checking assumptions, checking their reasoning,
poking for holes in their own and others’ analyses, and nurturing their interests outside work.
For my own problems, I often explain my problems to others.
We’ve all had the experience of getting not two minutes into an explanation before realizing a gaping&amp;nbsp;hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also like to lead with creativity.
Often it’s when we creatively expand a mundane problem into a field of possibilities that
people’s curiosity can perk up.
Aside from brainstorming/&lt;a href="https://www.creativityatwork.com/2011/01/10/brainwriting/"&gt;brainwriting&lt;/a&gt;,
some good prompts when research just starts or gets stuck are to ask:
“Is there an easier way to do this?”
“What would [Stakeholder] ask?&amp;#8221;”
“Are we sure we know what we’re optimizing for?”
“What’s the worst that can happen?”
“How will this help [Stakeholder]?”
You get the&amp;nbsp;picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, the simplest way to foster curiosity is to have a diverse team to begin with.
(And if all you have is “diversity of thought”, your team’s thoughts are not as diverse as you think.)
We want there to be discord and tension in a team along with the maturity not to see these as signs of dysfunction.
This tension will perk our ears to other ways of thinking, other vantages, unknown unknowns.
It’s akin to adjusting the dial away from exploitation towards exploration,
so that our teams can sway and not break under the vicissitudes of&amp;nbsp;business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Risks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I hinted, curiosity can go too far.
Especially if we forget to connect things back to our work.
It’s easy for curiosity to lead to distraction.
Even if our wanderings remain related to our task, we might find ourselves down so many rabbit holes that
we forget our actual commitments.
There is always the risk of “analysis paralysis” if
we come up with so many questions and hypotheses that we’re unable to make a decision.
Then we may miss critical windows of opportunity.
To guard against these patterns, I recommend checking in frequently with stakeholders and subject matter experts.
They can often eliminate entire categories of hypotheses based on their needs or experience.
Also, though uncomfortable, meeting more frequently than we can iterate can help
save time by forcing feedback before we go too far down a bad&amp;nbsp;path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a practical matter, curious exploration often looks like wanton scribbles.
It’s easy to end up with a huge tangle of uncommented code in a Jupyter notebook
that fails the moment we restart our kernel.
We like the output of one cell, but we can&amp;#8217;t get back to the state that generated it.
Communication and reproducibility are key to reliable science,
so we must try to keep our work traceable, even when we think we&amp;#8217;re just toying around.
The best solution will depend on a team’s culture of sharing work, code, findings, and documentation.
(A musing: I was taught since college some rules for maintaining a useful lab notebook.
Date every page.
If I write something down wrong, cross it out so I can still read it and note why and when I did so.
Start each experiment by noting what I&amp;#8217;m trying to do and expecting.
Stuff like that.
I wonder if a similar set of guidelines for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EDA&lt;/span&gt; notebooks would be worth&amp;nbsp;stating.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also is the sin of hunting for low p-values across many different statistical tests over the same data.
I argue that curiosity is valuable for generating more hypotheses, yes.
We need to test these hypotheses, yes.
We have a finite reserve of data, yes.
But if we test every hypothesis on the same data,
then by chance some tests will confess spurious patterns or hide actual ones.
The more we interrogate a data set, the less we can trust the results.
If you must do this, be very careful with the results, and consider an approach to mitigate the risks.
I refer you to your local statistician for further&amp;nbsp;guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Right&amp;nbsp;Questions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are good reasons that data science in particular thrives on curiosity.
I’ve shared some ways to prompt it when you feel you need more.
But curiosity is not an absolute virtue.
It can lead to distraction.
It can motivate sloppiness.
And without the support of powers of synthesis, empathy, some domain knowledge, and grit,
it may actually spin us in spirals away from our goals.
In the end, it comes back to the hardest skill to learn in data science: asking the right&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2018-04-02:the-role-and-importance-of-curiosity-in-data-science.html</guid><category>humans</category><category>code</category></item><item><title>The Acceptance of Ambiguity</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/the-acceptance-of-ambiguity.html</link><description>&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/17/Yin_yang.svg/240px-Yin_yang.svg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/literary-theory.html"&gt;A little while back&lt;/a&gt;, I tried to illustrate the value of accepting ambiguity via Emily Dickinson and Jacob Bronowski.
Poetry and Science.
This topic bears expansion, so now I expand.
I’ve said very little to data scientists to date, even though it’s my field.
So finally, I will address you first, then share general lessons for all of&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ambiguity&amp;nbsp;everywhere&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing profound in my saying that life is more complicated than it seems.
Yet, though a commonplace, outlining this complexity takes great effort against the culture and wisdom we receive.
For example, we like to bucket ourselves into one of two opposites, yet are these ever stable or coherent?
Female/male, gay/straight, introvert/extrovert, right/wrong, oppressor/oppressed.*
Even something as seemingly fundamental as being right- or left-handed has exceptions—some are ambidextrous, others have lost their originally dominant hand.
Most of the time, when presented with a dichotomy, the answer that feels right is
“sometimes one sometimes the other” or “somewhere in between” or “a bit of both” or “neither”.
Or my favorite: “How are those&amp;nbsp;opposites?”**&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important work of the Post-Structuralists reminded us to consider defining concepts not by what they are, but by what they are not.
They also rejected the insistence of one, correct interpretation of a text, allowing as many interpretations as readers.
They afforded value to subjective, individual experience.
This directly gave human voice to the underrepresented.
A central concept to Post-Structuralism is Derrida’s “différance”.
He characterizes it thus: “Any exposition would expose it to disappearing as a disappearance.
It would risk appearing, thus&amp;nbsp;disappearing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare to the opening lines of the Tao Te Jing***: “The way you can go / isn’t the real way.
/ The name you can say / isn’t the real name.” The “way” here is the Tao.
You can’t teach someone how to follow the Tao.
You can’t describe it.
You can only find your own way.
Beyond the Tao itself, one of the central symbols is yin and yang, represented above.
Within the side of yin is a drop of yang and vice versa.
Each pole of a dichotomy contains its opposite, thus the dichotomy is false—one must consider the&amp;nbsp;whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of my favorite examples, but you are hopefully thinking of&amp;nbsp;others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ambiguity in Data&amp;nbsp;Science&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In data scientist, we are often concerned with uncertainty metrics.
But whereas uncertainty measures the quality of our observations or models, ambiguity is deeper.
The first classifiers we typically learn to implement are binary classifiers.
Dog or cat.
Spam or legitimate.
Sales opportunity or not.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SVM&lt;/span&gt;, logistic regression, naïve Bayes, there are lots of algorithms for making a binary decision based on input data, possibly with a probability associated with the output.
But by their form, an implicit assumption is that each input record represents one or the other possible&amp;nbsp;output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To embrace ambiguity in such a classification task, one might add a “neither” option, i.e.
declare ignorance if the probability/confidence is below a threshold.
One might use the probability directly.
One might change a dog/cat classifier into two: dog/not dog and cat/not cat.
Whatever the change, one will need to establish new processes or decision flows to considerately handle the ambiguous&amp;nbsp;case(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another implicit assumption lies in the input data.
Binary features may not truly be binary (ahem, gender, ahem).
A null value might indicate the data weren’t captured or that the available options don’t apply.
Recording these distinct possibilities means losing the compactness of binary variables, but gaining more informative inputs to your models.
In some cases, it may mean recognizing the full humanity of your users.
This carries its own&amp;nbsp;weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zooming way out, even the term data science is ambiguous.
What is data science? We see endless takes on this with no final definition in sight.
And while some agreement in the community may clarify certain dialogues, this ambiguity doesn’t stop data science from working! After all, we don’t have a definitive answer to: “what is science?” As with science, data science doesn’t need its bounds to be precisely drawn in order to work or grow.
In fact, to define either too strictly would restrict their evolution and advancement.**** They need fuzzy edges in order that those edges can&amp;nbsp;adapt.*****&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love this freedom within this burgeoning field.
Every team I’ve worked on has had different goals, different standards, different personalities.
I occasionally read advice and ensuing debates about how best to place data science within a company, whether data scientists should own production code, how to keep data scientists happy, etc.
More often than not, these start with, “Data scientists like/need/want &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XYZ&lt;/span&gt;” I firmly object to these generalizations! If you start with an assumption of the personality and needs of a data scientist, you will only hire those who match those assumptions.
In reality, the field is diverse and its practitioners reflect this.
These articles are useful for seeing what other teams have tried and how well they work, but remember that your team probably has a different composition.
No good therapist applies generic techniques unthinkingly to every patient.
No good data science manager should unthinkingly apply generic&amp;nbsp;structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ambiguity in&amp;nbsp;Life&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last entreaty actually extends rather generally in life.
All the advice we find out there is great for collecting ideas.
But it will be up to each individual to decide which are useful, relevant, and helpful.
The best advice I see only provides frameworks for coming to your own decisions.
For example, reading about different communication styles opens my eyes to extra dimensions of social dynamics that I used to miss.
This helps me adapt my own communication in a more sensitive and effective&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A corollary of this is that we should be judicious in our advice to others and our expectations of them.
As we’re all impossibly different, what works for us may not work for others.
Sometimes there are good reasons others behave so seemingly irrationally.
Yes, we should keep an eye out for harmful patterns and counter them where possible.
But let’s also celebrate humanity’s resistance to&amp;nbsp;definition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we accept that others are different—they have different values, contexts, histories, needs—then we have to accept another fact.
Given the diversity of people we need to account for, no single policy can cover everyone’s needs.
In an (my) ideal society, a gamut of voices will be heard, illegitimate (“A man needs his nuggs”) and antisocial (e.g.
anti-Semitic) needs will be rejected******, and the rest will still be found contradictory.
Finally, a compromise will be made to attempt to satisfy as many needs as possible while avoiding as many and as deep of harms as possible.
However you try to eliminate the huge grey areas, the unavoidable result is that no one will ever be completely happy.
This is not to say we should accept any shade of grey—rather it’s to set our target away from the dangerous fiction of Utopia.
Let’s remember how to compromise&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;AmBIGuity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s satisfying in a primal way to be sure of the superiority of our beliefs and to subjugate the other.
(see &lt;em&gt;mansplaining&lt;/em&gt;.) But life seldom offers pure, simple either/or situations.
I challenge you to think critically about every binary choice you encounter over the next few days.
I think you’ll find lots of grey&amp;nbsp;middles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may seem a time-consuming way to live.
But perhaps not.
Maybe by accepting ambiguity, we rid ourselves of the need to force an artificial structure onto reality.
Maybe like a quantum computer, we can find new power by playing in an expanded space where many options can coexist.
We don’t have to question ourselves when we don’t fall neatly into a category.
We don’t have to have pay any mind when we observe a harmless hypocrisy.
We can accept nature in all its complexity, ambiguity, and&amp;nbsp;sublimity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* I’m inspired here by Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick’s
&lt;a href="http://evekosofskysedgwick.net/writing/epistemology-of_the_closet.html"&gt;Epistemology of the Closet&lt;/a&gt;
for her trenchant takedown of such false&amp;nbsp;binarisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;** I can’t help but think of the Fear/Love scene in Donnie&amp;nbsp;Darko.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*** I’ve chosen
&lt;a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2016/10/21/lao-tzu-tao-te-ching-ursula-k-le-guin/"&gt;the late Ursula Le Guin&amp;#8217;s rendition&lt;/a&gt;
for her preservation of the ambiguity that permeates the&amp;nbsp;original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**** See &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GOP&lt;/span&gt; efforts to restrict funding of certain categories of research or
the role of Stalin-era imposition of Dialectical Materialism to the Lysenko&amp;nbsp;Affair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;***** I am, however, of the opinion that data science needs some strict standardization and oversight.
Professional organizations, whether medical, engineering, or legal, all set explicit ethical standards.
Given the increasingly visible power of data science,
we should all take the ethics surrounding our work very seriously.
To have this dialog and debate, we need a common language.
I don’t think we’re far&amp;nbsp;off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;****** This does get slippery.
Who decides what needs are illegitimate or antisocial?
To preserve tolerance, at some point, intolerance must not be tolerated.
But what is that point? See Popper and the paradox of&amp;nbsp;tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2018-03-26:the-acceptance-of-ambiguity.html</guid><category>humans</category><category>code</category></item><item><title>My Messages for Meditators</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/my-messages-for-meditators.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Years ago, the promise of a quiet mind able to remain focused through stretches of work
got me intrigued about the power of meditation.
Not being power-hungry, I did nothing with that curiosity.
I’ve since found better reasons to learn more,
and I’ve noticed a few patterns out there that I want to address.
I am still early with meditation, but I have beliefs I would like to&amp;nbsp;share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever your goals may be for taking up meditation,
    I do not doubt their validity and worthiness.
If you have no particular goals at all, that’s perfectly fine, too.
You’ll benefit anyway,
similar to whether you exercise for the abs or just because everyone says you should.
But &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; you have specific goals,
you should check whether there is a form of meditation that actually is a good method of achieving them.
There might not&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your goal is what I once had—to develop superpowers,
essentially: the ability to churn through work efficiently and
to have unshakable confidence—I
sincerely hope you intend to use the power for good and not to further selfish&amp;nbsp;aims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your goal is to study or adopt the exotic philosophies of the Far East, more power to you.
But don’t expect admiration for this alone.
It’s one thing to acquire knowledge and have compassionate ideas.
It’s another to live those ideas in action and to establish healthy, compassionate&amp;nbsp;habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your goal is to experience transcendental states of mind, cool.
I’m all about feeling oneness with universe.
I hear psychedelics can save a lot of time and effort,
though I can’t condone the use of controlled substances.
And as before, please recognize that this manner of practice doesn’t by itself make you a better person.
Habit over&amp;nbsp;ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if your goal is to foster equanimity—if you seek to quiet negative thoughts,
manage stress or chronic pain, or relieve the effects of some trauma—then welcome.
I have much more to say to you.
This has been my more recent goal.
I recognized that the negativity I bore translated into weakness
and a burden for those who care about me.
So I’ve been trying to meditate to train these habits out of my mind.
And as inconsistent as my practice has been, the effects have been noticeable.
The rest of this post is addressed to&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m often unsure whether I’m “doing it right”.
I don’t like guided meditations because I find them distracting,
and I don’t want to rely on an external source for serenity.
I want to &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34272471-altered-traits"&gt;alter my persistent&lt;/a&gt;
traits rather than slip into altered states when the time suits me.
But observing my breath and letting my mind wander feels too passive.
How can I challenge myself?
I can’t seem to just follow a set prescription,
so I came up with my own theory of how meditation might work for me.
Your experience will be your own, but perhaps the following may seed your own&amp;nbsp;ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Buddhism, the doctrine of &lt;em&gt;anatta&lt;/em&gt;,
or &lt;em&gt;no-self&lt;/em&gt;, is a difficult concept rejecting a permanent self, soul, or essence.
I tried and failed to make sense of the particulars, so I’ve drawn from it my own notion.
My version of it is that we each change over time,
we’re all composed of constituent conscious elements,
and we’re all part of greater social organisms.
I’m &lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/i-am-not-who-i-was.html"&gt;not the same person as 12-year-old Alfred&lt;/a&gt;.
One part of me can handle strolling through a park while
a different part listens to music and another contemplates the weather.
My team, my family, my company, my city, each has a personality and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meme"&gt;memory&lt;/a&gt;,
and the dynamics of each affects and is affected by me.
Thus there is no persistent, singular, isolated self to be the subject of the whims of&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we accept this, then many (by no means all!) of our personal worries and preoccupations melt away.
Some things just aren’t important if I can expect the next moment to be different,
when I can attribute a pain to only a portion of my person,
and when I can see my place in larger wholes.
In other words, perspective enhances&amp;nbsp;equanimity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But rejecting the self is a radical departure.
Obviously I am me, right?
Aren’t I meditating in order to improve myself? My “self”?
Alas, reason alone is insufficient.
I will need the force of habit to realize the equanimity I seek, and habit comes from practice.
That’s where meditation comes&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What am I practicing?
Observing myself as a neutral third party.
The breath is the standard object of focus, but what makes it so useful?
It’s the fact that you’re always breathing, usually on autopilot,
but you can also take complete control over it, within physical limitations.
What’s really, really hard is to observe your breath without affecting it.
Not just to notice at moments now and then, but to really watch it like a movie.
Once I can do that, then it’s on to the much harder challenge of
observing the latent, inchoate thoughts and feelings swimming around,
rolling and tumbling over each other in my head—those multitudes we contain—without affecting&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I want to note also that I don’t think it really matters where or how you meditate.
You can be walking to work, sitting in traffic, taking a shower.
You can focus on your steps, hearing, chewing since
they’re also automatic actions that you can control when so inclined.
The point is just to observe yourself as if you’re not yourself.
Furthermore, the advice about sitting upright in a quiet, dark room makes things easier since
there are fewer distractions, but it’s not the one right way.
In fact, I think it’s probably advantageous to
perform some form of practice in active situations lest the effects remain compartmentalized to easy surroundings.
Mindfulness emphasizes maintaining awareness throughout the day, so it appeals to&amp;nbsp;me.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I become more familiar with this mental storm,
it becomes easier to observe it manifest in others, and to observe it with compassion.
It explains why we can all be so hypocritical and inconsistent.
I have to give up the simple, convenient stories I want to tell myself about others.
I start to see how our minds dance together through our interactions.
This compassionate practice might be overlooked if I focused solely on self-development,
but understanding our shared experience is vital perspective for the equanimity I seek.
(Equanimity for … myself? There is no self! Never mind that! Just do&amp;nbsp;it!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This practice of perceiving the chaotic, connected kinetics of human minds
changes the premises I bring to my evaluation of everything.
This fear is temporary—I can ignore it.
This unfair treatment was unintentional—I can forgive it.
This happiness is fleeting—I can revel in it while it lasts.
This good fortune is a gift—I can share it.
Practice develops a habit of perspective thus enhancing&amp;nbsp;equanimity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As worthy a goal equanimity may be, on its own, it’s selfish (cf. my messages #3 and #4).
I don’t want to be a solitary reed bending back and forth in changing winds doing nothing for my neighbors.
(“Hey man, it doesn’t affect me, so I don’t care.”)
I want to develop the strength and presence of mind to act for the sake of others.
The habit I&amp;#8217;ve so far described is a habit of mind; let&amp;#8217;s not neglect to develop habits of action.
Please, yes, use meditation for healing,
but don’t fall into the trap of being so self-absorbed that we fail our&amp;nbsp;communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the understanding I’ve reached at my early level of experience with meditation.
Your mileage will vary.
I hope these thoughts help you shape your own practice into a form that feels right for&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EDIT&lt;/span&gt; (2018-03-24)&lt;/strong&gt;: My friend pointed me to &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/leaves/comments/85u18y/some_notes_and_encouragement_on_meditation_from/?st=JF2J7D5G&amp;amp;sh=7a463fa1"&gt;this succinct, practical advice&lt;/a&gt;
on meditating. I found it a very useful reminder.&amp;nbsp;Highlight:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first suggestion is that you begin meditation with an attitude that it&amp;#8217;s something you are going to &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt;,, not something you are going to &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2018-03-14:my-messages-for-meditators.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>To Listen</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/to-listen.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Have you heard &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linguistic_relativity#Forms"&gt;the argument&lt;/a&gt;
that our thoughts are constrained by what we can verbalize?
It’s interesting when you think about it, and there are some
&lt;a href="https://www.npr.org/2018/01/29/581657754/lost-in-translation-the-power-of-language-to-shape-how-we-view-the-world"&gt;neat studies&lt;/a&gt;
to back it up.
It also adds a stimulating dimension to
&lt;a href="https://www.theparisreview.org/blog/2015/04/21/write-tight/"&gt;etymology&lt;/a&gt;,
maybe motivating us to investigate what gems of ideas
&lt;a href="http://www.thebookoflife.org/untranslatable-words/"&gt;other languages may hold&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A touching example I learned about recently is that the Chinese character for “to listen” is composed of
the characters for “ears”, “eyes”, “attention”, and “heart” (and I think, “king”, actually).
(&lt;a href="https://www.she-philosopher.com/gallery/lely_2W1.html"&gt;This link&lt;/a&gt;
is worth a glance to see what I mean.)
We see baked into the language a static reminder of what real listening involves.
How&amp;nbsp;wonderful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s also wonderful is how uniquely a glyph can portray an amalgam of concepts in a way that,
say, a German compound word cannot.
A glyph composed of many simpler glyphs may result in more strokes,
but the spoken word is still one word which usually means one syllable.
Also, in the glyph there’s no primary word with determiners,
so the connection between the composite and its components is more abstract, more poetic.
Perhaps ironically, it’s far more gestalt than the German&amp;nbsp;counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone some time ago had to have decided this character for this word would take this form.
It says something about culture of the time, doesn’t it?
It’s easy to be seduced by a sense of wisdom contained in this one character.
But before we fall prey to simplistic &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orientalism"&gt;Orientalism&lt;/a&gt;
let’s consider what little history I can&amp;nbsp;muster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said ‘this character’ at the top of the last paragraph because millenia ago,
there were certainly several competing glyphs for a given word.
Just as one finds within the Roman Empire several languages and dialects, so with China.
How interesting that this is the glyph that survived.
I would love to know what the others were like and how they came to be.
I would love to know the contexts in which
this version was first used, evolved, and saved in favor over the others.
What were the political, philosophical, and spiritual currents like
in those times that gave us such a&amp;nbsp;character?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the character under consideration is of the traditional character set.
The simplified set endorsed by the government in China replaces the character of 22 strokes (聽) with one of 7 (听).
My first instinct is to decry the affront to culture.
But, there’s a valid argument that a simpler character set expands literacy to more people.
The beauty in this character and others like it may be forgotten,
but wouldn’t the beauty in poetry and other writing reach more people?
What’s the right tradeoff?
(By the way, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debate_on_traditional_and_simplified_Chinese_characters"&gt;the debate&lt;/a&gt;
turns on far more dimensions than&amp;nbsp;these.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes, I love the notion that listening involves the heart as much as the ears,
but let’s not read too much into it.
China’s history, like every culture’s history, is&amp;nbsp;complicated.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2018-02-24:to-listen.html</guid><category>literature</category></item><item><title>Literary Theory</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/literary-theory.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am so impressed with the &lt;a href="https://thebrooklyninstitute.com/about/"&gt;Brooklyn Institute for Social Research&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BISR&lt;/span&gt; offers courses around &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYC&lt;/span&gt; and elsewhere on topics ranging from philosophy to literature to politics.
The common thread seems to be critical thought.
For me, the currency of such academic avocations is knowledge and context.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BISR&lt;/span&gt;’s return of such currency on my invested effort has been huge.
The latest course I took was &lt;a href="https://thebrooklyninstitute.com/items/courses/literary-theory-critical-introduction/"&gt;Literary Theory: A Critical Introduction&lt;/a&gt;,
led by the inimitable &lt;a href="https://thebrooklyninstitute.com/people/rebecca-ariel-porte/"&gt;Rebecca Ariel Porte&lt;/a&gt;.
If you’re like I was when I signed up, you’ve never heard of literary&amp;nbsp;theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re one of my technically inclined readers,
you’re possibly even dismissing the notion as so much ivory tower self-satisfaction.
So often through the years, people have said,
“let’s face it, it’s easier for you to pick up literature than for an English major to pick up physics.”
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BISR&lt;/span&gt; has convinced me that this opinion grossly underestimates the sophistication of the humanities.
Even the staunchest physics supremacists I encountered in grad school would get riled up over religion or politics.
This is an admission that questions revolving around the human condition are worthy ones.
No surprise, the humanities have been developing highly sophisticated perspectives for approaching these&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of Literary Theory at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BISR&lt;/span&gt;
(emphatically a cursory introduction, given only four short weeks at hand)
we read and discussed primary texts to address such questions as,
“How do our material conditions affect our being?”,
“How do we understand the structure and semiotics employed by a text?”,
“Is all knowledge mediated by language?”,
“What role should subjectivity play in interpreting the world?”,
“How much of our supposed knowledge is actually contingent on culture?”,
“To what extent are the forces and/or legacies of Western colonialism echoed in what we read today?”,
“How have depictions and understanding of gender evolved over the centuries, especially recently?”
These are all pertinent to reading text, but also pertinent to understanding the modern&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The epistemologies of physics, math, or computer science are not suited to addressing these questions.
Humans are uncountably various amongst each other and even within themselves.
There is no Standard Model of Human Physics to be found.
Humans process information entirely differently from Turing machines.
Within the humanities, however, we find several rich analytical traditions ranging from psychoanalysis to queer theory,
each with its contributions and&amp;nbsp;shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These theories and traditions do not provide elegant, concise mathematical expressions, and they&amp;#8217;re fluid, evolving continually.
That is, of course, a reflection of their aim.
It&amp;#8217;s a feature, not a failure.
Rather than attempting to conquer nature through universal understanding as with the natural sciences,
perhaps the questions of the humanities will benefit more from embracing inherent ambiguity and subjectivity.
The unit on &lt;a href="http://www.philosophybasics.com/movements_poststructuralism.html"&gt;Post-Structuralism&lt;/a&gt; made this most explicit.
These readings and discussions were the most difficult,
but also the most rewarding as they laid foundations for
Postcolonial theory, Queer theory and Feminist theory,
each of which I found so relevant to understanding present life.
In these units, the Post-Structuralist moves of
deconstruction, defining something by what it is not, and elevating subjective experiences proved their value by
giving voice to those experiences at the margins and boundaries which force us to reconsider our received&amp;nbsp;notions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to close as our class closed:
A reading of Emily Dickinson through the various literary traditions we had covered.
Copied here from the &lt;a href="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/52737/my-life-had-stood-a-loaded-gun-764"&gt;Poetry Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Life had stood - a Loaded Gun -&lt;br&gt;
In Corners - till a Day&lt;br&gt;
The Owner passed - identified -&lt;br&gt;
And carried Me away -&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now We roam in Sovreign Woods -&lt;br&gt;
And now We hunt the Doe -&lt;br&gt;
And every time I speak for Him&lt;br&gt;
The Mountains straight reply -&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And do I smile, such cordial light&lt;br&gt;
Opon the Valley glow -&lt;br&gt;
It is as a Vesuvian face&lt;br&gt;
Had let it’s pleasure through -&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when at Night - Our good Day done -&lt;br&gt;
I guard My Master’s Head -&lt;br&gt;
’Tis better than the Eider Duck’s&lt;br&gt;
Deep Pillow - to have shared -&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To foe of His - I’m deadly foe -&lt;br&gt;
None stir the second time -&lt;br&gt;
On whom I lay a Yellow Eye -&lt;br&gt;
Or an emphatic Thumb -&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I than He - may longer live&lt;br&gt;
He longer must - than I -&lt;br&gt;
For I have but the power to kill,&lt;br&gt;
Without - the power to die -&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started parsing the content.
Who’s the speaker? The gun? A woman? A man?
Is the “Loaded Gun” a potential to damage? A pregnant woman?
The Owner “carried Me away”. Do we read this literally?
“We hunt the Doe”—Perhaps in a Postcolonialist reading
the speaker is the agent of the oppressive Owner/colonizer as He slaughters the docile natives.
Perhaps in a feminist reading, the speaker is accomplice to sexual conquests.
“Yellow Eye … emphatic Thumb”—the sight and hammer of a gun? Cat’s eye, human thumb? Grotesque supernatural imagery?
“Without - the power to die -”—because a gun is a lifeless object?
Why “power”&amp;nbsp;here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We interpreted line by line together in this manner,
but then I tried &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queering"&gt;queering&lt;/a&gt; the poem to see where that might go.
How much innuendo can I inject, and how would that change the meaning?
What if I decide the gun is a sexually voracious woman?
A sexually voracious man?
The imagery can fit both—a Loaded Gun, roam, hunt, Vesuvian face, Yellow Eye, emphatic Thumb, live, the powers to kill and&amp;nbsp;die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there’s the brilliance!
This poem lends itself to such a variety of readings,
and even within the sexual reading, its gender ambiguity expands its multivalence.
A younger me would be frustrated by the absence of a correct answer,
but how human (and not algorithmic) it is to be able to study such a sententious poem,
excavating signs and symbols,
interpreting from several contexts without a need to assign a ranking of the best or most probable readings.
Indeed, accepting all readings simultaneously.
The ambiguity is precisely the source of its richness.
I hope that my technical readers can truly appreciate this.
As &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_Bronowski"&gt;Jacob Bronowski&lt;/a&gt; said,
&amp;#8220;The symbol and the metaphor are as necessary to science as to&amp;nbsp;poetry.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put as much effort into this class as for particle physics back in the day.
I didn&amp;#8217;t have to. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BISR&lt;/span&gt; understands we&amp;#8217;re working professionals.
But the rewards for my effort:
I think I know what literary theory is now.
I know that I know more about the world.
Here’s to more &lt;a href="https://thebrooklyninstitute.com/current-courses/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BISR&lt;/span&gt; classes&lt;/a&gt; in the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2018-02-19:literary-theory.html</guid><category>literature</category><category>humans</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>I Am Not Who I Was</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/i-am-not-who-i-was.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Who was I when I was twenty? I was Alfred. I’m still Alfred. Or am&amp;nbsp;I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few of the cells in my body are the same as the ones the former Alfred had.
Perhaps none of the molecules are.
It has all rotated out and&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few of the thoughts in my mind are the same as the ones the former Alfred had.
They’re colored by a richer palette now.
They reach farther beyond to more&amp;nbsp;people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a strong sense of continuity that we confer to individuals through time.
I’m not very different today than I was yesterday.
I don’t feel reborn every morning.
I have the same smile and the same frown I did as a child.
But over the span of years, I’ve worked fiercely on developing&amp;nbsp;myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we could sometimes say I’m no longer the same person I was X years&amp;nbsp;ago?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if the boy who kept embarrassing himself in class is not me in the present?
What if the youth who told racist and sexist jokes is different from me?
What if I could choose not to identify with the kid who couldn’t afford school lunches?
What if I could look at myself and be convinced that no,
the person I was is no longer wholly reflected in myself&amp;nbsp;today?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we absolve our regrets and heal our wounds by assigning past harms to a separate, past other?
Instead of guilt or shame of a problematic past,
can I extend love and compassion to the confused, scared kid once called by my&amp;nbsp;name?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would this open up for whom I could be&amp;nbsp;tomorrow?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-12-14:i-am-not-who-i-was.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>The Weak Weak Anthropic Principle</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/the-weak-weak-anthropic-principle.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Lately, in between the despair of the modern world and deciding what to eat,
my mind found for itself another source of uncertainty to obsess over.
This one’s a holdover from my physics days:
why are the laws and constants of physics such as they are?
I used to subscribe to the Weak Anthropic Principle:
if the laws of physics were different, we wouldn’t be around to ask the question, so don’t worry about it.
This is in contrast to the Strong Anthropic Principle which states that
any universe must allow for intelligent observers.
(I still hold that this is a weird leap of faith.)
As I read bits of different metaphysics, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WAP&lt;/span&gt; is becoming less and less&amp;nbsp;satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you accept the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WAP&lt;/span&gt;,
then since we have no evidence that the parameters of our universe couldn’t have been different
(unless you believe in a grand creator which renders all of this moot),
you have to accept that&amp;nbsp;either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We got really, really, extraordinarily lucky that
   the universe ended up being one that supports intelligent life as we know&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a multitude or infinity of universes with all manner of laws and/or constants of nature,
   and we are, naturally, in one that supports intelligent life as we know&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extremely improbable outcomes realistically only occur if there are extremely many rolls of the hyper-dice.
So in grad school, I rejected the first alternative, but the second was enough for me.
These days I have to wonder,
why should we believe in multiverse or big bounce theories aside from the fact they make the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WAP&lt;/span&gt; believable?
They’re only a subset of many valid models that accurately account for our best tests and observations.
So we actually can’t rely on it for supporting the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WAP&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what’s my take now?
I hold out hope (faith?) that there’s a theory of everything to be discovered
that would prove that the laws of nature are necessary – any other form would have inconsistencies.
And a corollary: the constants in those laws are necessary.
Any other values would lead to inconsistencies.
And these values are going to be constrained by the laws, not because there are arbitrary magic&amp;nbsp;values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General relativity serves as an illustrative example here as it’s a complete theory of gravity.
It’s a theory that derives from a simple proposition: the universe is geometric.
Super-obvious, right?
It’s just that curvy geometry wasn’t well-explored at the time, so Einstein had to invent new math.
And what popped out was a beautiful theory of a form that is necessary given its basic assumptions,
and this force called gravity emerges with all its nuances and surprising predictions
which are continually being validated by&amp;nbsp;experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do we have gravity, and why does it behave as it does?
Because space-time is geometric. It has to be. I love that.
I want to think a similar route from axioms to theory can exist for the basic laws of physics, i.e. reality.
In other words, instead of physics built on descriptive models,
physics starting from basic axioms and necessary laws emerging from&amp;nbsp;those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still problems, of course.
If there’s one consistent theory of everything for a set of axioms, there are probably many.
Maybe infinitely many.
So we’d still be left pondering one of them anthropic principles,
and I’d still be left annoyed.
Also, even if reality is consistent (and I really believe that it is)
is there a consistent language of mathematics complete enough to accommodate all of reality?
If no, what does that mean for math, physics, or&amp;nbsp;reality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoot, is math even the right model for expressing physics?
Plenty of derivations in physics go,
“there are two solutions to this equation,
but this one isn’t physical so we’ll ignore it.”
Math is definitely useful for producing predictions, but maybe reality is more&amp;nbsp;subtle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, finding this theory of everything wouldn’t actually be terribly useful.
The world we play in is complex enough that
we’re still going to rely on statistical and approximate models to do anything practical.
Plus the interesting stuff is usually the emergent behavior that doesn’t derive directly from the basic&amp;nbsp;laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why does this question matter?
Well, it just seems so remarkable that we live in a universe with such a wealth of phenomena as we have.
How beautiful would it be to show that reality is as it uniquely must be?
I would find deep comfort if for all the contradictions inherent in being human,
at least the universe is consistent and&amp;nbsp;whole.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-12-02:the-weak-weak-anthropic-principle.html</guid><category>science</category></item><item><title>Discoveries (I)</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/discoveries-i.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Regular readers may recall my pivot from searching for truth to searching for beauty.
Philosophy has been wonderful for teaching me how to pose questions
and how others have framed their explorations of them.
But philosophy works best in the spaces where answers are most uncertain.
Once we start finding answers,
we tend to stop thinking of those questions as philosophical
and place them in the domain of whatever new science came up with answers.
I’m taking a view that the answers to my questions can only be ones I devise for myself
and that it will be the pursuit of beauty that leads me to&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How’s that search going? Some&amp;nbsp;highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned the &lt;a href="http://www.smb.museum/en/museums-institutions/museum-fuer-islamische-kunst/collection-research/research-cooperation/multaka.html"&gt;Multaka project&lt;/a&gt;
in &lt;a href="http://blog.justalfred.com/empathy-in-its-place.html"&gt;my last post&lt;/a&gt;.
I love this example of community-level, considered, intentional empathy.
When we open ourselves to those who are different from us, we can learn greater human truths in&amp;nbsp;return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over coffee with a friend of five years,
we shared what we’d been grappling with, learning, and thinking about lately.
And I thought back to when we first met.
We talk differently.
We’ve had our trials and lessons.
They say your childhood friendships are the strongest because those were your formative years.
But adult years are formative as well.
May we never stop&amp;nbsp;growing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a lot of time this summer exploring the nature on offer around me.
This included hikes among woods, stone trails, grand waterfalls, gardens, arboretums, and lakes.
Each experience with its own mood, each with its own colors, each with its own sound and silence.
But the message I took was consistent.
There is life and change everywhere.
None will ever know us. Most will never notice. We’re only small parts of a whole.
The response is humility and the release of much&amp;nbsp;burden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/falls.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/falls.jpg" width="504"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Imagine this in an aeon&amp;#8230;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to see a lot of art.
Some of it banal, some of it difficult, some of it pleasant, some of it wondrous.
My reactions told me about myself.
I bring my history to the art I see. I take the art I’ve seen to the life I experience.
I took a wonderful class on &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12749.Swann_s_Way"&gt;Swann’s Way&lt;/a&gt;,
the first book in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_Search_of_Lost_Time"&gt;Proust’s magnus opus&lt;/a&gt;.
The importance of art is one of several major themes.
&lt;a href="https://quamproxime.com/2017/03/04/artifice-as-realism/"&gt;Artifice can often distill truth more clearly than realism or reality&lt;/a&gt;.
An abstract form can conjure a mood, a reaction, a memory—are these not as real as a face or a landscape?
There are personal truths in art waiting for your engagement to be unleashed.
For example, from the below figure in the ground:
Proximate, purposeful emptiness is more imposing on a person than a parallel, positive-space presence.
There’s a resonance here with Buddhism’s second noble&amp;nbsp;truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/michael_heizer.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/michael_heizer.jpg" width="504"&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.diaart.org/collection/collection/heizer-michael-north-east-south-west-19672002-2003-174-1-4"&gt;&lt;i&gt;North, East, South, West&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Michael Heizer&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Proust.
There’s so much beauty to unpack there.
I have to reserve it for another&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-10-29:discoveries-i.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Empathy in its Place</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/empathy-in-its-place.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I wish more of the world were more empathic.
When marketing tells us we&amp;#8217;re special beyond anyone else,
it&amp;#8217;s easy to lose the ability to relate to the people around us.
Pity carries judgment (“you poor thing”),
and sympathy isn’t always welcome (“I’m sorry you did that to yourself”).
But empathy, the exercise of sharing another person’s state of mind and emotions,
requires recognizing that the other person is experiencing something unique and personal.
It raises the object of your empathy from an autonomous, ambiguous other to a sentient,
whole person whom you are trying to understand and share an experience with.
It’s not an easy task, but it’s available to everyone, even&amp;nbsp;psychopaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy isn’t only relevant in interpersonal relations—it’s vital even at the societal level.
One of the most beautiful examples I’ve heard recently was at a wonderful lecture titled,
“The Humanities in the World” given by Mariët Westermann of the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.
As an example of the humanities addressing a very pertinent, politically relevant problem,
she pointed to the &lt;a href="http://www.smb.museum/en/museums-institutions/museum-fuer-islamische-kunst/collection-research/research-cooperation/multaka.html"&gt;Multaka project in Berlin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Germany welcomed a huge number of Syrian and Iraqi refugees into its borders in recent
years—as well as the attendant cultural bewilderment.
The Berlin state museums realized that as they held many Syrian and Iraqi artifacts,
they represented a direct connection for the refugees to their homes.
This was especially meaningful given the rampant destruction of historical artifacts and&amp;nbsp;sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the museums trained a pilot group of refugees as docents who gave tours in both Arabic and German.
This had multiple aims and effects.
The docents could extend the connection of the museums more widely with their communities,
they could provide more personal accounts of the artifacts than anyone else could,
they actively improved their German,
and the project started important and informative dialogues with the museum&amp;nbsp;staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different refugee visitors reacted differently.
Many were grateful for this connection to the homes they left.
Others appreciated the care and reverence with which these artifacts were held.
Yet others found the extraction of these artifacts into Germany problematic.
But having this space to have these conversations openly is a great benefit for all.
Multaka is Arabic for meeting point and is intended as such.
The project has expanded and continues to&amp;nbsp;evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final wonderful outcome involved many refugees’ curiosity
about the history of this western country that took them in.
The images of the years during and after &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WWII&lt;/span&gt; were especially salient.
To see how Germany went from post-war devastation
to the world-leading powerhouse that it is today gave hope for the future of their home&amp;nbsp;countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love this story because it’s one of facilitating empathy—experiencing
each others’ existence—between communities in such a direct, meaningful way,
and it’s happening in a place we think of as indulgent, stolid, and insulated from modern life.
The effects go beyond those immediately involved.
It humanizes new neighbors.
What better than the humanities to ease this very human&amp;nbsp;situation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, empathy isn’t absolutely good.
&lt;a href="http://bostonreview.net/forum/paul-bloom-against-empathy"&gt;Read Paul Bloom&lt;/a&gt;
for more, but consider what empathy affords the manipulative.
Also, empathy is a demanding exercise.
One could argue that empathy matters most between those who are most different,
and in those cases it is not a spontaneous reflection,
but an active effort to understand and imagine.
This means we naturally empathize most with those who are most familiar or attractive to us.
It also means empathy can be exhausting and lead to burn-out,
especially if you’re syncing with a very painful&amp;nbsp;experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What may be more useful is non-empathetic compassion.
That is, wishing better for someone else without taking on their burden.
&lt;a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/the-clarity/201703/compassion-is-better-empathy"&gt;There’s research&lt;/a&gt;
indicating that this mindset leads to
positivity, kindness, and eagerness to help in contrast with
the burden and discomfort assumed with empathy.
And when the direction of our compassion is guided by moral reasoning,
then we can overcome our cognitive biases to do more&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So then why do I wish more of the world were more empathic?
Because of the acute reminder of the humanity of people not like ourselves.
Because of the love that’s demonstrated by choosing to suffer along with someone else.
Because sometimes what we need most is merely to be&amp;nbsp;understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So tell me your story, friends, share with me your pains. I will&amp;nbsp;listen.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-10-14:empathy-in-its-place.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Truth and Beauty</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/truth-and-beauty.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am one of those people who has always believed himself to be incomplete.
I&amp;#8217;m often asking, &amp;#8220;What am I doing wrong?&amp;#8221; I&amp;#8217;m never good enough. I&amp;#8217;m unloveable.
My work is never up to my standards. I&amp;#8217;m usually afraid to&amp;nbsp;try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been reading a lot on resilience and philosophy lately. It&amp;#8217;s been undoubtedly
helpful. It&amp;#8217;s clear that many of my questions and judgments are not well-formed.
As my good, respected friend framed it, you can always have worked harder or faster.
You can always have done something just a little bit better.
So those sorts of judgments have no value.
I recognize I&amp;#8217;ve been far kinder to others than to myself.
But old habits are hard to&amp;nbsp;break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, I&amp;#8217;ve granted myself a slightly extended amount of time off to find balance.
To figure out a frame of mind from which I can be a better person sustainably.
But this, too, starts from the wrong premise.
This still assumes that there is some concrete, better model of myself that I can identify and
move confidently towards.
This still involves a search for a truth that will always escape&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href="http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24113.G_del_Escher_Bach"&gt;Gödel, Escher, Bach&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#8217;s extremely elegant.
But one reminder for me is that even number theory, the study of the properties
of numbers, the study of the theorems of arithmetic—even this is incomplete.
There is no way to systematically arrive at all true statements.
There is also no way to evaluate the truth value of a given statement.
What could be more cut and dry than arithmetic?
And yet our knowledge here is bounded.
Arithmetic is &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/goedel-incompleteness/"&gt;necessarily incomplete&lt;/a&gt;.
What hope do any of us have of completeness&amp;nbsp;ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn&amp;#8217;t call for a renunciation of truth or hope, but I think I&amp;#8217;ll try something different.
I think I&amp;#8217;ll try searching for beauty instead.
Kant connected moral reasoning with our purely rational faculties via beauty and aesthetics.
Maybe engaging with the beautiful is what I&amp;#8217;ve been missing as I seek kinder truths.
Nature, art, ideas, animals, people.
I&amp;#8217;ll try connecting.
There&amp;#8217;s no real program here.
I&amp;#8217;m following it on purely on&amp;nbsp;faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#8217;s in this context that I find myself in my host family&amp;#8217;s spare home
overlooking the lake with cool weather, colors starting to decorate the sky.
Sitting down with a serving of Scotch, reading material in hand,
and a Bach 6-part fugue referenced in the aforementioned book
(the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6QA212M70hM"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ricercar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
from his &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Musical_Offering"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Musical Offering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
to be exact) on my headphones.
Exceptional audiophile headphones that were gifted from my last company.
The sound is glorious. The music is brilliant. It&amp;#8217;s stirring. It&amp;#8217;s&amp;#8230; beautiful.
And I stop, and I appreciate, and I sip my Scotch. And I remember.
This Scotch was collectively gifted to me by my coworkers when I left my job.
There&amp;#8217;s love in these drops.
Beauty has reminded me of a beautiful&amp;nbsp;truth.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-07-09:truth-and-beauty.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Present</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/present.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I entered the next room in the contemporary art room at the Corning Museum of Glass and was drawn immediately to the pure forms.
A figure represented in printed, offset &lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/plates.jpg"&gt;glass plates&lt;/a&gt;;
a large, slightly bulging &lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/black_cube.jpg"&gt;cube of black glass&lt;/a&gt;.
Then I found Nicole Chesney&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.cmog.org/collection/rakow-commission/nicole-chesney"&gt;Present&lt;/a&gt;.
A nacreous, abstract atmosphere painted and wiped across a glass canvas.
And I started to&amp;nbsp;think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty. Why? Do others find it pretty? Would I have found it pretty ten years ago?
Will I find it pretty in ten years? What am I supposed to see? Why does it matter?
What do other people think about when they take the time to experience this piece? Is that what matters?
Are we connected somehow? I don&amp;#8217;t see a story or an object or a scene. Just a feeling.
It feels delicate. It exhibits &lt;em&gt;wabi-sabi&lt;/em&gt;. I want to protect this.
It&amp;#8217;s not Japanese, and yet it feels Zen all the same.
I see a faint, clouded reflection of myself. I feel like I&amp;#8217;m here, but I&amp;#8217;m not.
Approaching &lt;em&gt;muga&lt;/em&gt;. I start to detach. I want others to see this and experience&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with these thoughts in mind, I made my own&amp;nbsp;art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self Portrait: Relinquishing My&amp;nbsp;Self&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/self-portrait1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/self-portrait1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-01-10:present.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Excerpts of 2016</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/excerpts-of-2016.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I write far more personally than publicly. Here are some excerpts from entries throughout 2016.
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resolutions&amp;#8230;Plan.&amp;nbsp;Learn&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;Who am I?&amp;#8230;Thank you&amp;#8230;I don&amp;#8217;t have&amp;nbsp;answers&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;Lovely breakfast&amp;#8230;I actually do like who I am for the most part these&amp;nbsp;days&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;I&amp;#8217;ve been naïve&amp;#8230;Philosophy&amp;#8230;Let&amp;#8217;s apply&amp;nbsp;this&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leadership. New challenge&amp;#8230;What&amp;#8217;s the point of&amp;nbsp;dating/relationships?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;I will only gain this by pushing myself into discomfort&amp;#8230;I could smile again the next day&amp;#8230;I want&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I&amp;#8217;m not&amp;#8230;People love&amp;nbsp;me&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;I know it&amp;#8217;s not true. But the words still sting&amp;#8230;It&amp;#8217;s inspiring to observe&amp;#8230;Lovely visit&amp;#8230;The friend I want to be: reliable, trustworthy, helpful, attentive,&amp;nbsp;respectable&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&amp;#8217;m&amp;nbsp;tired&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;She&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;She&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;They were all supportive&amp;#8230;Heck yeah&amp;#8230;I feel like I have a great new&amp;nbsp;friend&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commentary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I have learned, forgotten, grown, regressed, smiled, and suffered.
I&amp;#8217;m still grasping for control and searching for meaning, but with less judgment.
I&amp;#8217;m better able to help the people around me, and it turns out there&amp;#8217;s nothing more fulfilling to me.
I&amp;#8217;ve retracted into my shell somewhat, but it&amp;#8217;s richer inside than before.
This year, I want to share more of it with the people who would see.
Thank you, my&amp;nbsp;friends.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-01-01:excerpts-of-2016.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>PyGotham 2016</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/pygotham-2016.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I wish I could make all this prettier, but I gave a talk at
&lt;a href="https://2016.pygotham.org/"&gt;PyGotham&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#8217;s not my best work since I&amp;#8217;m not actually terribly experienced with the
subject matter. But it does represent packaged knowledge that I wish I had
when I was getting started with&amp;nbsp;Spark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few people asked for slides, so this is my attempt to post them. I&amp;#8217;m not
bothering with making reveal.js work, so it&amp;#8217;s all one long html doc. Sorry
it&amp;#8217;s not prettier. I know what pretty looks like; I don&amp;#8217;t know how to make
pretty&amp;nbsp;things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, for what it&amp;#8217;s worth, I present to you
&lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/html/PyGotham2016.html"&gt;the slides&lt;/a&gt;
to &amp;#8220;Spark Dataframes for the Pandas&amp;nbsp;Pro&amp;#8221;. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-07-20:pygotham-2016.html</guid><category>Code</category></item><item><title>You are an Antichrist</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/you-are-an-antichrist.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Correlation is not Causation. Any student of statistics has heard this repeated
time and again. But the world is complex and dynamic, and our mental capacity
has to fit in the 20-Watt, 3 pound organic mass inside our skulls. We&amp;#8217;re wired
to see patterns and when we notice B happen right after A enough times, we&amp;#8217;re
liable to think &amp;#8220;A caused B&amp;#8221;. This is good for the survival of the primitive
human. But we are not primitive. Are we? Perhaps to prove we are not, there
were those philosophers as Leibniz who went so far as to deny that
causation even really existed.
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But any reasonable person would accept that we can justifiably say that
&amp;#8220;A causes B&amp;#8221; provided a governing model and evidence to support said model.
Fire causes burns. This is useful and, moreover, reliable. It&amp;#8217;s not a far
stretch from there to allow statements of the form &amp;#8220;A prevents B&amp;#8221;. From there,
&amp;#8220;The absence of A causes B&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;The absence of A prevents&amp;nbsp;B&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, given an acceptance of causation, through action and inaction
we have effects on the world. Note that these aren&amp;#8217;t usually easy or possible
to trace (see chaos theory or the butterfly effect).
Given that every event could have generated a multitude of outcomes (even
the staunch determinist has to allow for the probabilistic nature of
quantum mechanics) there are an infinity of possible worlds that never come
to&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a subset of these possible worlds, our inactions or actions permit or
create a person who brings as much concurrent peace, harmony, and joy to
humanity as is possible. A&amp;nbsp;savior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we have acted or not acted, and thus this person does not exist. Our
actions have prevented this person, or the absence of our actions have
prevented this person. This person could have existed in an infinity of
forms, and some of these (an infinity of these) have been rendered impossible
by&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could all have effected a different chain of events, but we did not.
We could all have brought into being a savior to the world or become one
ourselves, but we did not. Our awareness of this effect is irrelevant. A
murderous machine is defective and requires termination regardless of its
awareness of its nature.
Therefore we are all guilty of causing harm to humanity. We are all&amp;nbsp;sinners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this same line of reasoning can also bring us to its opposite
conclusion. Logic is&amp;nbsp;fun!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-04-16:you-are-an-antichrist.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Renaissance Role Models</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/renaissance-role-models.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Who are your role models? Who are the people you try to emulate in some
aspect or other of life? Maybe parents? Maybe celebrities? Maybe fictional
characters? What are they like as&amp;nbsp;people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who are your celebrity crushes? Who are the people you like to look at
or watch? Maybe film stars? Maybe athletes or models? What are they like
as&amp;nbsp;people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did anyone come up in both&amp;nbsp;lists?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess that most people would answer no. I guess also that for most people,
the second list is longer. Probably a lot longer. And that&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;unfortunate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read an interesting piece recently about &lt;a href="http://www.thebookoflife.org/on-using-sex-to-sell/"&gt;advertising in the age of the
Renaissance&lt;/a&gt;.
I haven&amp;#8217;t been able to verify all the details, but the central ideas were
familiar to an art historian friend of mine. Here&amp;#8217;s the&amp;nbsp;gist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ficino/"&gt;Marcilio Ficino&lt;/a&gt;, an Italian
Renaissance Philosopher under the employ of the Medici family, wanted art to
educate. Art triggers contemplation if it engenders a desire to understand. We
desire to understand when we feel the engagement of love. And the quickest path
to love is to appeal at a sexual&amp;nbsp;level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, sexy advertising is a quick means to capturing attention which we
can then steer towards high&amp;nbsp;aims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closest direct quote of Ficino&amp;#8217;s I&amp;#8217;ve found refers to beauty rather than
sex appeal, but the idea still merits&amp;nbsp;conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas Renaissance art would depict idealized human forms,
often nude, to convey grace, harmony, and compassion, these days the idealized
human forms portrayed convey little more than material and physical notions.
That&amp;#8217;s a lost opportunity. We have sex appeal down to a science. What if we
could harness that power to improve&amp;nbsp;society?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a smaller scale, I think we might do our communities a service by
attempting to perform as sexy/beautiful role models ourselves.
We could collectively decide to be the best people
we can be, and through charisma and style inspire others to emulate us. I
definitely don&amp;#8217;t mean all others. I&amp;#8217;m certainly one who can only ever hope
to appeal to a small subslice of the general population. But for the people
who find something attractive about the way I carry myself, I want them to
discover other virtues as they learn more about me. Those who have more charm
and good looks can hope to positively influence more&amp;nbsp;people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us already try to be good people, and most of us also already try
to present well. What&amp;#8217;s novel in this mindset is in the motivation of
the latter. You might style your hair, dress of a fashion, or apply your
makeup with the aim of being respectable to colleagues, comfortable for
a setting, or simply to feel attractive. Seldom do we do so with the aim
of inspiring others. With this mindset, an otherwise
vain concern gains a measure of&amp;nbsp;nobility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like this idea so far, but I see two major pitfalls to consider. I&amp;#8217;d love
to hear of&amp;nbsp;others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, this is a wholly different proposition for men and women.
The standards of beauty/sexiness are vastly unequal. This argument can
easily be interpreted as an elaborate way of telling women to &amp;#8216;smile&amp;#8217;, a
detestably common occurrence resulting from many men&amp;#8217;s misguided belief
that women are supposed to make them feel good. I am not encouraging anyone
to diminish herself or&amp;nbsp;himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sexy in whatever way you wish to be (sexy doesn&amp;#8217;t have to be sexual) and
beautiful in the ways that you know you are.
Embody the virtues you wish for the world to celebrate. Let these two efforts
support and motivate each other. I want us to celebrate the
best of ourselves. Not to objectify or dehumanize&amp;nbsp;ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, to the last point, serving as a role model can be interpreted as only
communicating the happy, positive, strong, successful sides of ourselves.
I think this is a damaging pattern, and I think we should be allowed to share
our darker, weaker selves. Let&amp;#8217;s not pretend to be perfect. Everyone faces
some degree of adversity. Let&amp;#8217;s demonstrate ways to face it with poise,
compassion, and&amp;nbsp;humility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One&amp;#8217;s quality as a human being and one&amp;#8217;s fitness as a role model should have
nothing to do with your attractiveness, but human nature isn&amp;#8217;t so egalitarian.
Instead of lamenting this flaw in our wiring, let&amp;#8217;s exploit it to better&amp;nbsp;society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(footnote: there are psychological studies that support many of the claims
and observations here, but as an outsider to the domain, I don&amp;#8217;t know which
are well established and which have yet to be replicated. So I decided not
to reference literature whose quality I don&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;understand.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;postscript 2016-05-28: After a couple months letting this stew, I think the
call to action here shouldn&amp;#8217;t be to pretty ourselves up. Not everyone wants to
be the object of attention. We &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; try to embody the virtues we admire
anyway. I don&amp;#8217;t have a problem with that part. So the real call to action is
just to notice those who choose to combine physical appeal with other virtues
and not see it as distracting from those virtues. It&amp;#8217;s ok for a professor
to be hot in more ways than&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-03-26:renaissance-role-models.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Caseo-exploration</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/caseo_exploration.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Day after day, month after month, I would aimlessly poke through the company
kitchen looking for snacks I knew weren&amp;#8217;t there. I knew what was behind all the cupboard
doors, I knew what was in the fridge, I knew I wouldn&amp;#8217;t want anything there.
But I&amp;#8217;d look anyway, because humans make no&amp;nbsp;sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cupboards had the same nuts, chips, popcorn, and cookies. The fridge had the same yogurt,
hummus, and cheeses. Including those gross, little Babybel cheeses. The ones with the laughing
cow. My mother told me they&amp;#8217;re referred to as &amp;#8220;cow head cheese&amp;#8221; in Korea. Which means something
else here&amp;#8230;. I learned that there&amp;#8217;s a whole collection of images online of figures and sculptures
molded from the red wax coating. In my mind, that coating makes each unit of cheese a miniature cheese
wheel. Individual, miniature, hermetically sealed cheese wheels. So you ought to be able to age
Babybel cheese the way you do a cheddar or a gouda. Day after day, month after month, I looked
at those Babybel cheeses and wondered what an 18-month Babybel cheese would look and taste like.
Finally, I decided there was only one way to find&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/cheese_experiment.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/cheese_experiment.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week marked the 18-month anniversary of the oldest in my collection. I didn&amp;#8217;t collect
the cheeses with rigorous regularity, but I was satisfied in the end having a somewhat even
spectrum of ages. It was time to examine. Opening the freshest of the four samples presented
no surprises. The 5-monther was noticeably moist. The 11-monther was wet and felt firmer
and denser. It was also noticeably more yellow than its younger brethren. The 18-month
sample expressed considerable moisture, felt even more firm,
and had a lovely (actually, a nauseous) grey, mottled patina. None was terribly aromatic,
except for maybe a scent of decay from the oldest&amp;nbsp;sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After regaining our confidence lost from seeing the drippy, grey sample, we started our vertical
tasting with the best of the bunch. Best, as in it hadn&amp;#8217;t outlived its &amp;#8216;best by&amp;#8217; date.
Most people are probably familiar with the salty, sour taste and the soft texture
that kind of sticks to your teeth. I guess a lot of people enjoy it. I&amp;#8217;m not&amp;nbsp;judging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 5-month sample tasted quite different. It tasted pungent and had a different texture. We
wondered whether the recipe had changed along with the&amp;nbsp;packaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 11-month sample was more noteworthy. The flavor was mellowed and slightly nutty.
The texture had relaxed into something like a custard or a firm panna cotta.
Smooth, dense, but yielding and not at all sticky. My friend detected formaldehyde.
I&amp;#8217;m not familiar with that particular vapor, but yes, there was a trace of something of
an origin that perhaps shouldn&amp;#8217;t be cheese. Some soft cheeses produce ammonia as they age,
so maybe it was&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was only brave enough to cut into the core of the oldest sample, which presented
small volume to evaluate. But further complexity was present. There was also a cheddar-like
sharpness that was absent from the other samples. The texture was similar to the 11-month
sample. Aside from the frightful exterior, this was the most cheese-like of&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn&amp;#8217;t get sick. I got to enjoy a nice Spanish-themed dinner
with my good friends. And I enjoyed months of happy anticipation for the unveiling.
Any regrets? That I didn&amp;#8217;t start this sooner. And I wish I took better notes of my impressions.
But in the end, I consider my hypothesis proven correct with caveats.
Yes, Babybel cheese will age and gain character. But it will gain unfriendlies that you
don&amp;#8217;t want to eat. Pros and&amp;nbsp;cons.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-02-13:caseo_exploration.html</guid></item><item><title>Der Tod und Der Atheist</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/der-tod-und-der-atheist.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Tod_und_das_M%C3%A4dchen"&gt;Schubert&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vKh4JsWvsPw"&gt;lied&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Atheist (me, hopefully not any time&amp;nbsp;soon):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not just yet! Oh, not just yet! &lt;br /&gt;
There is so much left to learn! &lt;br /&gt;
I have obligations to fulfill! &lt;br /&gt;
Let me do more good. &lt;br /&gt;
Let me do more good. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Death (also&amp;nbsp;me):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give me your hand, you fragile, defeatist soul! &lt;br /&gt;
I am a friend, and come not to judge. &lt;br /&gt;
Your debts are paid! You&amp;#8217;ve earned friends&amp;#8217; love, &lt;br /&gt;
Surrender your sensations to serenity! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-01-30:der-tod-und-der-atheist.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Proust in the Park</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/proust-in-the-park.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I can easily spend an entire day in front of a computer reading articles and writing emails, and by the end of the day I won&amp;#8217;t be able to recall half of what crossed my eyes.
It may feel industrious to spend so much time ingesting information and ostensibly learning, but the human brain has its limits.
With the mind zipping back and forth between the task at hand, the next task to come, the needs of your peers, the way to phrase a request, the bills that you can&amp;#8217;t forget to pay, your posture, are your zippers and buttons closed, the errand you need to run on the way home, the messages you need to pass along, the last thing you said to the person you&amp;#8217;re trying to impress whose validation you need, the emails you owe people, the wording of your next clever tweet, the next thought comes and goes before the last has had time to settle comfortably in your accessible&amp;nbsp;memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m trying to simplify my routine and cut out the extraneous.
If I only allow myself half a mind&amp;#8217;s worth of attention and a minimum of time on a task like reading, then it&amp;#8217;s worth no time at all; I won&amp;#8217;t remember the details anyway, I won&amp;#8217;t experience the gist, and it takes time away from being fully engaged in something else, something more meaningful.
It means acknowledging that I will miss out on interesting research, funny stories, insightful commentary, but half-engaged, I would be effectively missing out anyway.
So I&amp;#8217;m aiming to spend time more fully engaged in fewer activities.
It requires training, though; the mind does not easily focus on one thing for&amp;nbsp;long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And why should it?
If early humans fell frequently and naturally into states of singular focus, they would have been ill-suited to deflect the myriad dangers present in open nature.
This is the evolutionary psychological justification for the capriciousness of our consciousness.
To reject this default requires training; mindfulness meditation of the secular Buddhist variety is one form of training that particularly interests me, partly because so many of its central teachings are consistent with modern psychology.
Yet, I haven&amp;#8217;t progressed much with mindfulness practice, so I&amp;#8217;m trying alternative means to the same end as easier first&amp;nbsp;steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent some time with my host family after leaving my last job; more sympathetic and less judgmental than my real family, I have nothing but positive associations with their home and their company.
In conversation, they mentioned the &lt;em&gt;Duane Moore&lt;/em&gt; series by Larry McMurtry.
I gathered that these were sort of a Proustian telling of a life lived in Texas.
In fact, in the book &lt;em&gt;Duane&amp;#8217;s Depressed&lt;/em&gt;, the eponymous character is assigned by his therapist to read the first book of Proust&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;Remembrance of Things Past&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;more recently translated as &lt;em&gt;In Search of Lost Time&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;and is given one year to do so.
Fiction as therapy.
&lt;em&gt;In Search of Lost Time&lt;/em&gt; is a 4,000-page series of seven books that is infamous for its serpentine prose and extended phrasing.
But many point to Proust&amp;#8217;s uniquely intricate and evocative manner of capturing the thoughts, experiences, and observations of a life lived from boyhood through old age.
He reminds us of the details in the everyday that makes life so fascinating and ennobles us to find deeper meaning in our own existences.
In my unemployment and goal of further self-discovery, I decided to follow Duane&amp;#8217;s lead and read &lt;em&gt;Swann&amp;#8217;s Way&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proust&amp;#8217;s style does indeed test one&amp;#8217;s limits of concentration.
By the time you&amp;#8217;re out of the third nested appositive, you&amp;#8217;ve usually forgotten the start of the sentence.
A month later, I&amp;#8217;m 80 pages in, but I&amp;#8217;m motivated to keep at it.
After some warm-up, I can sometimes get into a flow where I can read a few pages before my mind wanders and I have to go back and re-read a bit.
With some training, I hope to get into this flow more easily&amp;#8212;an alternative to meditation.
I&amp;#8217;ve taken to heading to the park to read; it&amp;#8217;s away from the distractions of home&amp;#8212;music, endless tidying up, emails&amp;#8212;and unlike a coffee shop, I can take as much time as I like without feeling bad for taking up space.
It&amp;#8217;s a lovely park that&amp;#8217;s always full of crowds in the summer except at its quiet, shaded peripheries, and just a quick stroll from home.
I didn&amp;#8217;t discover it until several months after moving into the neighborhood; it was in the opposite direction as work.
The way we explore a new city is funny; familiar routes feel shorter, rectilinear streets are more welcoming, and the journey home is always faster.
Once my brain accepted this park, it was easy for me to immediately treat as ordinary the great central fountain and the immense, gleaming, white arch at its side.
We notice, we accept, and we move&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other day, I made it a point to take a leisurely stroll around the park to take in the environs as if for the first time before settling into a quiet, shady spot to dig into my book.
I noticed.
A conversation in Russian, a couple in the grass whose posture in dalliance must have taxed the young man&amp;#8217;s strength, a leisurely group of police officers, several tables of chess players including one with a young, clean-cut boy trying to impress an older, disheveled man, a kind-looking, attractive young woman walks my way&amp;#8212;but I shouldn&amp;#8217;t make eye contact unless I were intent on engaging, and how would you do that mid-stride in a park, anyway?&amp;#8212;and walks by followed by an older woman with a small dog who smiles at me, I forgot that there are public restrooms in this park, a squirrel takes a glance at me then decides to keep digging for whatever it thought it smelled, some flowers catch my eye; I wonder how much maintenance they require, a group of college students pass by, all smiles and banter, ice cream sandwiches for $4, I wonder if that price is strategic since many would drop a five and leave the change, a man with a mask hovers over a boy on the ground while a woman films from above, student film, probably.
And then I found my spot.
It was shady, and from my guess of where the shadows would travel, would remain shady.
A peek upwards noticed no avian nuisances to drop an interruption to my reading.
Sitting down, I took a moment to take in the cool breeze&amp;#8212;most welcome when so much of the summer has been sticky and oppressive.
When I see others wrapped in light cardigans and sweaters, I know I&amp;#8217;ll be a little more comfortable in my single layer.
And thus I&amp;nbsp;began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrator recounting his boyhood described the apparent reality of the fictional worlds contained in the books he read&amp;#8212;even more viscerally real than the landscape beyond the book in front of his eyes.
And then passed the old woman with the dog again&amp;#8212;I wonder why she smiles at me.
Back to fiction.
No, the thoughts that exist only in my mind are all fiction.
Unless I asked, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t know whether that woman was actually smiling at me or to herself.
Even then, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t know for sure, so I&amp;#8217;m free to make up whatever accounting pleases me most.
We all do this all the time; our thoughts and beliefs aren&amp;#8217;t reality&amp;#8212;only a personal fiction that, hopefully, does not depart too much from the personal fictions of others.
So, specifically, back to my reading.
After a bit, the narrator&amp;#8212;or more accurately, Proust&amp;#8212;went on to describe the advantage of&amp;nbsp;fiction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novelist&amp;#8217;s happy discovery was to think of substituting for those opaque sections [of another person], impenetrable by the human spirit, their equivalent in immaterial sections, things, that is, which the spirit can assimilate to itself.
After which it matters not that the&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I was distracted by excited shouts; not angry, more celebratory, as you would hear at a parade or around a talented street performer.
A double decker tour bus seemed to be stuck in an intersection not far ahead of me, and a second followed close&amp;nbsp;behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After which it matters not that the actions, the feelings of this new order of creatures appear to us in the guise of truth, since&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More shouts, and above the rhythms and the jazz from the local buskers, I heard the strain of a soprano singing what might have been opera.
I tried to place the direction, but soon lost the voice&amp;nbsp;entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230; the feelings of this new order of creatures appear to us in the guise of truth, since we have made them our own, since it is&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two buses decided to park just in front of me, and a picture-taking crowd gathered.
Signs informed that it&amp;#8217;s Body Painting Day, and the upper deck of both buses were filled with topless, painted people.
That explains the revelry.
But no, they weren&amp;#8217;t merely topless, they were all completely nude and painted head to toe.
The city provides some odd experiences, to be sure, and I was tempted to snap a picture as others were doing (&amp;#8220;pics or it didn&amp;#8217;t happen&amp;#8221;), but decency in my mind prevailed and I decided to afford the liberated crowd a bit of privacy.
I quickly realized how silly that was.
Obviously these people were perfectly happy, proud even, to be in public essentially nude and attracting a lot of attention, so why would they be ashamed to be in a photograph?
That reasoning was confirmed when they got off the buses for a photo op in the park.
I decided I respected the confidence many of these people&amp;#8212;whom popular fashion would tell to be ashamed of their bodies&amp;#8212;must have to expose themselves so publicly in so celebratory a fashion.
That confidence must be rooted in a firm, unyielding self-love; something I&amp;#8217;ve only recently realized I&amp;#8217;m missing and I need.
But the happy shouts and gathering crowd were interrupting my reading, so I got up and found another&amp;nbsp;spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novelist&amp;#8217;s happy discovery was to think of substituting for those opaque sections [of another person], impenetrable by the human spirit, their equivalent in immaterial sections, things, that is, which the spirit can assimilate to itself.
After which it matters not that the actions, the feelings of this new order of creatures appear to us in the guise of truth, since we have made them our own, since it is in ourselves that they are happening, that they are holding in thrall, while we turn over, feverishly, the pages of the book, our quickened breath and staring eyes.
And once the novelist has brought us to that state, in which, as in all purely mental states, every emotion is multiplied ten-fold, into which his book comes to disturb us as might a dream, but a dream more lucid, and of a more lasting impression than those which come to us in sleep; why, then, for the space of an hour he sets free within us all the joys and sorrows in the world, a few of which, only, we should have to spend years of our actual life in getting to know, and the keenest, the most intense of which would never have been revealed to us because the slow course of their development stops our perception of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This passage struck me as one of those keen expositions of a fact most of us take for granted for which we continue, a hundred years on, to read, admire, and gain wisdom from Proust.
From fiction, we may receive a distillation of the human condition that expands the range of emotional experiences to include ones we may never otherwise know.
It may be this fact that explains the societal impact of &lt;em&gt;Uncle Tom&amp;#8217;s Cabin&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Jungle&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;One Flew Over the Cuckoo&amp;#8217;s Nest&lt;/em&gt;.
The disturbance or joy we feel from novels like &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Pride and Prejudice&lt;/em&gt; owes itself to the same.
Have you ever fallen in love with a fictional character&amp;#8212;not a real, attached sort of love, but from the descriptions of another character&amp;#8217;s love, a parallel, vicarious one?
I know a few people who only read non-fiction claiming the rest is a frivolous waste of time; they either lack Proust&amp;#8217;s insight, or they don&amp;#8217;t value emotional enrichment.
Life as a human consists of competing emotional currents, and the better we understand them, the better we understand ourselves and others.
Emotional enrichment is not only beneficial, but essential to a mature and responsible world-view.
And as Proust eloquently explains, the novel is a particularly powerful vehicle of that&amp;nbsp;enrichment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The passage also provides a motivational seed&amp;#8212;two percent of the way through this magnus opus&amp;#8212;a metaphorical carrot on a stick, tempting the reader to make the effort to continue through the rest.
This is, after all, a novel.
It is a demanding one, but it has already provided such vivid tableaux with the sympathetic expression of an intense emotion which, indeed, I have never known&amp;#8212;or perhaps that I forgot ever having.
A friend who has read &lt;em&gt;Swann&amp;#8217;s Way&lt;/em&gt; remarked that it had some really beautiful moments.
Maybe I do want to be more ambitious and read the entire work.
Maybe my life really will be richer for&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only got a couple pages further before I decided to walk home.
I had enough to think about, and before getting lost in Proust&amp;#8217;s world, before receiving another flood of ideas, before losing my train of thought completely, I wanted to&amp;nbsp;share.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2015-07-20:proust-in-the-park.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Stories</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/stories.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of my goals with this blog is to motivate others to share their experiences.
I think there is value to this, especially if you think no one would care about your story.
The fact is, there are people out there who will care.
And it can mean the world to know that they are not alone in their experiences.
So I&amp;#8217;d better set an example and share my&amp;nbsp;own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently left my job at Paperless Post as a Data Scientist/Data Engineer.
Paperless Post boasts a gender-diverse workforce and a refreshingly cooperative culture.
Smart people work there who encourage your ambitions and generously share their knowledge.
The company tries hard to make its employees feel like first-class citizens without implicitly enforcing a particular culture.
I had friends across the company with whom I could chat about anything from tea to opera to history.
I absolutely loved the team we hired.
My teammates were very intelligent, kind, curious people with diverse backgrounds, skills, and interests.
(Also, only one of the four was a man. I was proud of this. I didn&amp;#8217;t make the final hiring decisions, but my input carried some weight.)
I was working on important projects and made our team visible throughout the&amp;nbsp;company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did I&amp;nbsp;leave?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t know the true answer to&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the two months since I gave my notice, my answer to why I left has continually changed, though it was always&amp;nbsp;honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I felt that I had accumulated too much exhaustion and with it negativity, and I was blocking progress more than I was helping.
So I had to remove myself to allow the team to move forward without me as a moody&amp;nbsp;bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I felt that actually, I was doing more than anyone to help my team, but I wasn&amp;#8217;t being allowed the authority I needed to be as effective as I could be.
So I had to remove myself to find a situation where I could realize my full&amp;nbsp;potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I felt that management was honestly trying to fill the gaps and inefficiencies I pointed out, but I was too impatient to see their efforts through.
I was too insecure and weak-willed to express what I and the team needed with sufficient assertiveness.
So I had to remove myself to save myself from frustrations of my own&amp;nbsp;creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I felt that even if I could choose the projects I would spend my time on, the needs of the company were out of step with my interests.
So I had to remove myself so as not to waste the company&amp;#8217;s resources with my&amp;nbsp;disinterest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I felt that everything could have been fine, but I was such an emotional wreck (as evidenced by my rapid weight loss) that I needed more than a vacation to regain my sensibilities.
So I had to remove myself to save my team from absorbing my pessimism and to save myself from falling into deeper&amp;nbsp;depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I feel now?
I think when I gave my notice, all I knew was that I wasn&amp;#8217;t happy and I wasn&amp;#8217;t going to get much happier.
And I wasn&amp;#8217;t even sure of that much.
I think all of the reasons I gave people had truth, and yet none was really true.
There is some research that indicates intuition can actually outperform thoughtful analysis for sufficiently complex problems, particularly when there isn&amp;#8217;t much experience to rely on.
I think my situation was a case of this.
My gut had been telling me to quit for a long time.
It took me a while to&amp;nbsp;listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, that&amp;#8217;s how I remember things.
Memories are funny that way.
They keep &lt;a href="http://discovermagazine.com/2009/jul-aug/03-how-much-of-your-memory-is-true"&gt;rewriting themselves&lt;/a&gt;.
My retelling is honest, but is it true?
Like Nabokov&amp;#8217;s humming Humbert recounting a fictional fiction, how much can I trust my loose, wet&amp;nbsp;memory?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all I can give is a story.
And that story will change again in due time as I imagine myself gaining some hitherto unrealized&amp;nbsp;clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I have no regrets.
A month ago, I was physically weak, anhedonic, and two steps from tears at any moment.
Now I am healthier, visibly happier, and I have a clearer sense of what I need out of life and a career than I have ever had.
I can see where I am, where I want to be, and how I&amp;#8217;ll get there.
I&amp;#8217;m past much, though not all, of the fear that I held before.
I knew before that I would be ok.
Now I believe that I will be&amp;nbsp;ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not bad for a month&amp;#8217;s worth of&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2015-07-09:stories.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Re-Introduction</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/re-introduction.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As with so many projects, blogs in particular, mine suffered inattention after the initial excitement of setting it up wore off and the demands of life took over.
So here&amp;#8217;s take two on the revival of this outlet.
I have a couple guides in the works detailing starting a blog in Pelican and installing Arch linux, but I intend to share smaller posts more often.
Topics will range from data science to computer science to physical science, music to math to madness.
Keep an eye out for posts coming soon.
I hope you&amp;nbsp;enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2015-06-29:re-introduction.html</guid><category>info</category></item><item><title>Introduction</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/introduction.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Back when I was in grad school, I started a blog to satisfy an itch to write.
I used Blogger at the time because it was free and easy to set up.
Now it seems the reputation of that platform has gone the way of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOL&lt;/span&gt;.
Also, now that I work in the software industry, I have new blogging needs.
So I&amp;#8217;ve decided to restart my blog in this new format.
I hope it&amp;#8217;s one that will be easy to migrate in the future should the need&amp;nbsp;arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a lot of work left to do.
I&amp;#8217;m in the process of migrating my old posts over here.
I&amp;#8217;ll also post my process for starting this.
I haven&amp;#8217;t decided whether or not to allow&amp;nbsp;comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the intent of this blog is to help me clarify my thinking around topics that are important to me.
Either personally or professionally.
I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to learning a lot in this&amp;nbsp;process.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2015-01-02:introduction.html</guid><category>info</category></item><item><title>Hypotheses Part 3</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/hypotheses-part-3.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/12/hypotheses-part-3.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/12/hypotheses-part-3.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The professional desk jockeys among my readers have probably all
considered the toll that lifestyle takes on their bodies. Standing desks
are growing as a solution to the slouching and inactivity. This often
works great, but does introduce fatiguing stress to one&amp;#8217;s joints. Others
take to sitting on exercise balls.
&lt;a href="http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/04/12/ask-well-ball-chairs/"&gt;Studies&lt;/a&gt; indicate
that these ball chairs don&amp;#8217;t actually improve posture or provide extra
exercise. My personal experience corroborates this. I think I&amp;#8217;ve hit on
a good compromise, and it&amp;#8217;s a pretty old idea.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just balance something on your head! Find a comfortable position (don&amp;#8217;t
forget to arch your lower back slightly) then stick something on your
head. Now you&amp;#8217;re locked in. Turn your head at your own&amp;nbsp;risk.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can start with something easy like a stuffed animal or a banana.
Then maybe a book. Try balancing a bottle of Scotch while wearing a bike
helmet. Pretty soon, you&amp;#8217;ll be spinning plates on sticks and be straight
as a stick,&amp;nbsp;too.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re worried about looking silly, well, you can go back to sitting
on a&amp;nbsp;ball.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hypothesis is that this idea actually works. I welcome&amp;nbsp;data.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you tend to work on a laptop, consider where your hands
function comfortably and where your natural line of sight is. You&amp;#8217;ll
find the two are rather&amp;nbsp;distant.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2013 03:39:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-12-16:hypotheses-part-3.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category></item><item><title>Guido</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/guido.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/11/guido.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/11/guido.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you about a great guy named Guido. He invented a language
that greatly lowered the barrier for new students to enter into his art.
It was very difficult to learn a script in the old languages either
because the syntax was so arcane or because you really needed someone to
fill in missing details every time. Guido&amp;#8217;s language was intuitive and
readable, and it made it possible to reproduce results with minimal
training. And now, around a millennium later, it&amp;#8217;s hard to imagine music
without the ubiquitous staff that Guido d&amp;#8217;Arezzo first&amp;nbsp;invented.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_of_Arezzo"&gt;Guido&lt;/a&gt;
was really interested in teaching. Prior to his staff notation, there
wasn&amp;#8217;t a great way to indicate the pitch of a note. There were notations
to indicate whether to go up or down by a lot or a little, but it wasn&amp;#8217;t
particularly precise. He also invented mnemonics to help students learn.
There&amp;#8217;s something called the Guidonian hand by which a student could use
his knuckles to help remember his system. And of course, there&amp;#8217;s
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solf%C3%A8ge"&gt;solfège&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do&lt;/em&gt;. A deer&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221; That whole &lt;em&gt;do-re-mi&lt;/em&gt; business is solfège. It makes my
head hurt. &lt;em&gt;Do&lt;/em&gt; isn&amp;#8217;t a C or an A or any specific note. It&amp;#8217;s the base
note of whatever key the song is in. A step up from there is &lt;em&gt;re&lt;/em&gt;, a
step up from there is &lt;em&gt;mi&lt;/em&gt;, a half-step up from there is &lt;em&gt;fa&lt;/em&gt;, and so
on. If the key is C-major, &lt;em&gt;do-re-mi-fa&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CDEF&lt;/span&gt;. If it&amp;#8217;s D-major, it&amp;#8217;s
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEF&lt;/span&gt;#G.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets worse. In a minor scale, &lt;em&gt;do-re-mi-fa-sol-la-ti-do&lt;/em&gt; becomes
&lt;em&gt;do-re-&lt;strong&gt;me&lt;/strong&gt;-fa-sol-&lt;strong&gt;le&lt;/strong&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;te&lt;/strong&gt;-do&lt;/em&gt;. In order to read a line and get
the solfège right, one has to keep track of the particular key and mode.
These often change in the middle of a piece. People who can sing solfège
in real time freak me&amp;nbsp;out.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been asking professional musicians when I get the chance what
importance solfège had in their musical training. I&amp;#8217;m still struggling
to understand since no one seems to actually use it. My current
suspicion is that it&amp;#8217;s a useful framework for illuminating music theory
and the relations between notes. After all, a c-sharp and d-flat are not
the same note, despite what a piano or guitar would have you believe.
Solfège lays this fact bare along with other concepts. (I would love to
chat with someone who teaches this stuff. hint&amp;nbsp;hint)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we can thank Guido for the names, &lt;em&gt;do-re-mi-fa&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8230;. Actually, he
called it &lt;em&gt;ut-re-mi&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8230;, but it all started with him. He took the names
from the hymn, &lt;em&gt;Ut queant laxis&lt;/em&gt;, because each of the first six
half-lines started with a different note. The starting syllables were
assigned to those notes. Convenient. Thanks,&amp;nbsp;Guido.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_van_Rossum"&gt;Guido van Rossum&lt;/a&gt;
(inventor of the python programming language) is pretty cool,&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2013 20:12:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-11-16:guido.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Does Not Compute</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/does-not-compute.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/10/does-not-compute.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/10/does-not-compute.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s talk about language. How amazing is it that using sounds or
symbols, we can implant in another person&amp;#8217;s mind an entirely new state?
We can describe a place that person has never seen, we can construct a
belief that person has never considered, we can convey an emotion that
person has never&amp;nbsp;felt.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not without errors in transmission. Remember the game, &amp;#8220;telephone&amp;#8221;?
Why can&amp;#8217;t language be more precise? Let me try to explain this in an
unconventional way and see what it means for programming languages.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a language in which the intent of the communicator is completely
unambiguous to a qualified listener. I&amp;#8217;ll use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CD&lt;/span&gt; audio recordings as an
illustration. With good enough equipment, a listener can hear a
soundscape that is indistinguishable from the&amp;nbsp;original.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most people don&amp;#8217;t listen to CDs anymore. They listen to streaming or
downloaded music. The major difference is that these recordings are
compressed. Those parts of the audio signal that people can&amp;#8217;t hear well
are removed. This leads to degradation of the signal, but much, much
less information is required while most people never notice. So it&amp;#8217;s a
worthwhile tradeoff. In fact, there&amp;#8217;s a whole class of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Probabilistic_data_structures"&gt;probabilistic
data
structures&lt;/a&gt; in
computer science that sacrifice accuracy for performance and&amp;nbsp;size.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, human languages have each been reduced to use only a subset of
all possible
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Phonetic_Alphabet"&gt;sounds&lt;/a&gt;
and symbols. Take the word, &amp;#8220;hot&amp;#8221;. Here&amp;#8217;s a list of things that can be
described as hot: fire, chile pepper, horseradish, supermodel,
basketball player, a fashion trend, the color of a room. In English, we
use this single, overloaded word to represent this array of meanings.
Yet we&amp;#8217;re rarely confused due to our evolved talents for lexical
ambiguity resolution (as so wonderfully explained by my new colleague
&lt;a href="http://jennazeigen.com/lexical.jpg"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, when a word can take multiple meanings, we&amp;#8217;re
terrifically adept at taking context into account to disambiguate the
intended meaning. This permits us to compress our language into a
manageable size. More importantly, it permits us to be sloppy. The
sentence, &amp;#8220;I ain&amp;#8217;t git no donuts, but I gotta coke,&amp;#8221; is completely
understandable despite all the&amp;nbsp;errors.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers aren&amp;#8217;t like us. Computers are purely logical units that
mindlessly apply instructions to data because they have no governing
mind. At the processor level, they have no innate capacity to correct
erroneous instructions or to resolve ambiguities. This is what makes
coding hard. A sentence like &amp;#8220;Come to the kitchen&amp;#8221; is perfectly
understandable to us since we can guess there is supposed to be a period
at the end to indicate the sentence has ended. A computer would say the
sentence never finished so the instruction cannot be
processed. (Interestingly, there are companies that hire adults with
autism or Asperger&amp;#8217;s since they are often exceptional at handling and
debugging&amp;nbsp;code.)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the beginning programmer, I think this is an obvious, but useful
insight. Sort of like realizing the center squares of a Rubik&amp;#8217;s cube
don&amp;#8217;t move: those center squares cease to be puzzle pieces and become
stationary references to guide your manipulations. The stupid silicon
insight sets an exacting reference from which one can evaluate one&amp;#8217;s own
code. Instead of wondering why the dumb computer didn&amp;#8217;t get what he was
(not) clearly telling it to do, the novice can expend that brainpower on
avoiding the typos and syntax errors whose importance he now&amp;nbsp;understands.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-10-04:does-not-compute.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Code</category></item><item><title>Nobels</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/nobels.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/09/nobels.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/09/nobels.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what&amp;#8217;s cooler than winning a Nobel Prize? Winning two Nobel
Prizes. How many people have done this since the first award in 1901?
Four. Would you believe that the first was a&amp;nbsp;woman?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Madame Marie Skłodowska-Curie. Born in Poland, died in France. A
pioneering woman in science, her list of achievements is humbling to
even the greatest of geniuses. Her first Nobel was the Physics Prize,
awarded in 1903 alongside Henri Becquerel and her husband, Pierre Curie,
for the discovery of spontaneous radioactivity. (Quick, what&amp;#8217;s the
difference between radiation and radioactivity?) Her second was the
Chemistry Prize in 1911 for the discovery of radium and polonium and the
isolation of the&amp;nbsp;former.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To date, she is the only individual to have won the Nobel Prize in two
different sciences. She was also one of the most generous with the award
money. Her discoveries (and her gender) forced the reconsideration of
well-established beliefs. Her legacy continues in the Curie Institutes
in Paris and Warsaw. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marie_Curie"&gt;And on and on and
on&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8230;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logic, innovation, and temerity are not exclusive to men. As much as we
marvel at modern science and technology, we&amp;#8217;d be much further along if
our culture were not tainted with a latent sexism (and racism, for that
matter). I mention this for two reasons. First, we have wonderful role
models in science to inspire young women. They are shamefully largely
forgotten. Second, if men do not as a whole learn to respect women as
their intellectual equals, then everyone pays a&amp;nbsp;cost.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is not fair, but we can choose to treat others&amp;nbsp;fairly.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2013 14:06:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-09-08:nobels.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category><category>Humans</category></item><item><title>Hypotheses Part 2</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/hypotheses-part-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/08/hypotheses-part-2.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/08/hypotheses-part-2.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fancy bars these days like to serve their cocktails with a single big
chunk of ice. Less surface area means slower cooling means less dilution
of your expensive elixir over time. I don&amp;#8217;t buy&amp;nbsp;it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s my reasoning. Ice serves two purposes in
cocktails. First is to chill liquids, second is to keep those liquids
cold. Let&amp;#8217;s consider these in&amp;nbsp;turn.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At what temperature is ice? Zero degrees Celsius, right? Sometimes. Your
freezer is actually quite a bit colder, so fresh ice from the freezer is
just as cold. Pick up an ice cube with a damp hand, and it will freeze
the water on your fingers and stick. It&amp;#8217;s not very pleasant. But do it
anyway. For science. Ice sitting in a bucket for a while will be pretty
close to zero. You&amp;#8217;ll know it if the ice is&amp;nbsp;wet.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s ignore melting for a moment. We can talk about whiskey stones if
you prefer. Once you drop a cold stone in a room-temperature liquid, the
two will equilibrate in temperature. The liquid chills, and the stone
warms. But the stone doesn&amp;#8217;t warm uniformly. The outside warms up first
and passes this heat inwards. This means the inside of a whiskey stone
or block of ice can be substantially colder than the outside. Every bit
of cooling of the liquid has to come from the stone/ice, so with a
single large chunk, it takes longer to get to the cooling power of the
center, meaning it takes longer to cool the&amp;nbsp;liquid.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s talk about wet ice, so that the whole chunk is at zero or so. Now
all cooling of the liquid results in melting of the ice. Heat from the
liquid causes the ice to transition into a liquid state until the two
reach thermal equilibrium. But for a given volume and initial
temperature of liquid that you&amp;#8217;re chilling, the exact same amount of ice
will melt regardless of its shape. So again, less surface area means the
liquid takes longer to&amp;nbsp;chill.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put these two effects together, and using one large chunk of ice will
leave more cooling power locked in the center of the ice, and more of
the chilling will have to come from melting rather than simple heat
exchange. Result: bigger ice cube = slightly more&amp;nbsp;dilution.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about keeping a drink cold? Now the liquid is presumably at the same
temperature as your ice already. Also presumably, you&amp;#8217;re a distinguished
imbiber and sip your drink slowly. We can ignore simple heat exchange
between ice and liquid here since that will occur quickly compared to
the lifetime of your drink. Now, let&amp;#8217;s compare a glass filled with
crushed ice vs. one big chunk. As the heat enters your glass, it
eventually makes its way to your ice and melts it. Equal amounts of heat
means equal amounts of melting. However, with one big chunk, your drink
can get a little warmer in regions further from the ice. Since the
volume of liquid that needs cooling becomes effectively smaller, less
ice has to melt.&amp;nbsp;Score.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if most of your ice is sitting above the surface of
your drink it&amp;#8217;s chilling not only the liquid, but also the air. Most of
your scotch&amp;#8217;s lifetime will be in this state. Yes, even if the ice were
not sticking shamelessly out, the liquid would be chilling the air, and
end up melting the ice anyway. But it would also have less surface area
and sit lower in the glass resulting in more insulation from warmer&amp;nbsp;air.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are two small, competing effects, and it&amp;#8217;s not clear without
experiment which wins. My guess is that a big, but not huge ice cube is
better here. In part because most people won&amp;#8217;t care much about the
difference between a drink at 0C and&amp;nbsp;3C.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My recommendation: always chill drinks with small ice cubes fresh from
the freezer if possible. For serving, ice cubes from a standard ice cube
tray are probably big enough. Bigger than that, and you&amp;#8217;re just showing
off. If you really hate dilution, get whiskey stones and/or
double-walled glasses. If your glass has a stem, use it so you&amp;#8217;re not
pumping heat from your hands into your drink. If I&amp;#8217;ve left something out
of my analysis, please let me&amp;nbsp;know!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 14:08:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-08-21:hypotheses-part-2.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category></item><item><title>Hypotheses Part 1</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/hypotheses-part-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/07/hypotheses-part-1.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/07/hypotheses-part-1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m going to try again to focus on short-form publishing here. I&amp;#8217;m
starting yet another series of posts called &amp;#8220;Hypotheses&amp;#8221;. I am well
known as having random ideas float through my head. Some of these are
ideas about how some part of existence works. I&amp;#8217;ll share some with you
in this series.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Have you ever marveled at dogs&amp;#8217; olfactory acumen?
Give a bloodhound a sock, and he&amp;#8217;ll find a lost person. Or so the movies
say. Have you also ever marveled at how smelly we can get by the end of
a&amp;nbsp;day?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall that daily showering is a very late phenomenon in the course of
human evolution. We don&amp;#8217;t read perpetual complaints of people stinking
in historical accounts, which means the stench we acquire used to be
easily tolerable. But now we diligently wash away our natural odors
daily, and frequently apply more redolent replacements. Still, how many
of you have learned your partner&amp;#8217;s smell? Not the fragrance worn, but
the natural musk? I am willing to bet most of you. Here&amp;#8217;s my&amp;nbsp;hypothesis:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you grew up in a dark cave your entire life. Having evolved
these exquisitely sensitive light sensors we call eyes, and having never
strained them, stepping into sunlight for the first time would be
overwhelming or excruciating. Maybe it&amp;#8217;s the same with the smell of&amp;nbsp;people.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noses are appreciated as keen chemical sensors, but I posit that we are
evolved to be particularly sensitive to the range of human smells. Our
deprivation of that stimulus leads what used to be a normal and varied
experience to be singularly and intolerably&amp;nbsp;malodorous.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can&amp;#8217;t be too hard to validate or falsify. Try getting stinky with
your most loved one, and tell me how it goes. Trying this with a house
full of roommates would be even better. Some desensitization is
necessary to overcome the initial shock, but maybe by the third or
fourth day, you&amp;#8217;ll start to like it. I bet you&amp;#8217;ll be able to tell
different people apart. You may even be able to tell their moods. But
please do shower if you decide to report to me in&amp;nbsp;person.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2013 18:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-07-27:hypotheses-part-1.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category></item><item><title>Preconceptions Part 2</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/preconceptions-part-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/05/preconceptions-part-2.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/05/preconceptions-part-2.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s over. Four trips to Lincoln Center over the space of a week, and
more hours of serious drama and music than I can count with my fingers
and toes. (My toes aren&amp;#8217;t very nimble, so for the purposes of counting,
I effectively have four toes.) The live experience is definitely more
rewarding than even the &lt;a href="http://www.metoperafamily.org/metopera/liveinhd/liveinhd.aspx"&gt;Live in
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; shows
where the connection is asymmetric. In the opera house, the performers
give me their best, and I return my undivided attention and gratitude
(in the form of applause). They certainly earned it these four evenings.
After viewing it in person, I can say that this is a wonderful
production. It is not perfect. No production of Wagner is ever close to
perfect. But the embattled Lepage is actually the least of the
production&amp;#8217;s problems.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/IMG_20130426_181022.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/IMG_20130426_181022.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in the &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/04/preconceptions-part-1.html"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;,
the production has been criticized for its reliance on a large,
mechanical set. It has been deprecated by most critics who found it an
unnecessary distraction that resulted in a shallow&amp;nbsp;interpretation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes his machine creaks, but it&amp;#8217;s no louder than other props or the
audience members&amp;#8217; coughs. Mostly it just sits there, and after warming
up, the creakiness seemed to&amp;nbsp;diminish.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, images that sometimes move are projected onto the machine which
sometimes moves. The critics call this distracting, but how is it
different from allowing anything else on the stage to move? &amp;#8220;For shame,
they lowered a backdrop in the middle of the act, which caused me to
completely lose track of the music,&amp;#8221; said no one after any opera. Never
mind that Wagner explicitly calls for some drastic scene changes as one
blogger
&lt;a href="http://thewagnerblog.com/2012/05/the-met-ring-and-critical-incompetence/"&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;.
If moving images are so distracting, how are these critics able to
comment on movie scores? My take: there are images on the set that move
with the set and in response to the singers on the set!&amp;nbsp;Awesome!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if we&amp;#8217;re going to call the imagery in this production shallow, then
we&amp;#8217;d better start addressing the upholstery choices of other operas. A
bland or traditional design is a missed opportunity for the director to
force his personal, narrow, anachronistic wrapper around the production.
Wagner was actually quite specific in his stage directions. Do the
critics demand that every new production include a deep layer of
obfuscation unintended by the composer? Do they want high-concept
settings in every scene that somehow don&amp;#8217;t also usurp your attention
away from the&amp;nbsp;music?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some images were admittedly a little strange. The palantir-esque eye
during Wotan&amp;#8217;s monologue in Die Walküre was probably not a Wagner
invention. The transitional purple-pink, amorphous patterns in the final
opera defied any explanation. But these were neither distasteful nor
jarring. A few slightly odd visuals do not deem the entire production
&amp;#8220;catastrophic&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;disastrous&amp;#8221; as many critics have proudly&amp;nbsp;hyperbolized.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of a particularly effective use of the set was the opening
to Act &lt;span class="caps"&gt;III&lt;/span&gt; of Die Walküre: Ride of the Valkyries. Here, the eight
Valkyrie sisters ride through the sky selecting the bravest of fallen
warriors to bring back to Valhalla. They enter with a (tremendously
difficult, especially as an opener) battle cry of &amp;#8220;Hojotoho!&amp;#8221; In other
productions, the curtain rises, the music starts, the goddesses enter
onto the stage, they sing, they call to their implied horses offstage,
and it is a rousing show. In the Lepage production the music starts with
the sisters spaced between the 24 moving planks. 16 of these are
stationary and show the mountains and clouds passing below while the
eight that they sit atop are fashioned as the heads of their horses.
These horse heads tilt up and down suggesting their riding motion.
Rather than entering the stage one-by-one, there they are riding fast,
high in the sky. When it&amp;#8217;s one Valkyrie&amp;#8217;s time to enter, she slides down
her plank onto the front of the stage, effectively dismounting. This is
possibly the first presentation of this scene that fully expresses the
dynamism and vivacity of these warrior goddesses. It was thrilling and
the audience definitely&amp;nbsp;responded.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/xeRwBiu4wfQ" frameborder="1" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another was Donner&amp;#8217;s clearing of the sky which opens the way to
Valhalla. For this short scene, Donner stands alone on the set which
serves as a misty, tilted surface representing the sky. As the music
rises and he prepares for his strike, he strides in circles about the
center of the set which pushes the mist into a sort of whirlpool (as I
mentioned, the images are responsive). Finally, at the music&amp;#8217;s climax,
he strikes the ground (which is the sky, remember) with his huge hammer,
bolts of lightning flash from the point of contact, and the mist clears.
(I was going to link a video from the original season&amp;#8217;s performance, but
it was different enough to lack the vitality of the version I&amp;nbsp;saw.)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems I detected with the production were three-fold. First,
there were a few curious decisions in the direction. But being ignorant
of Wagner&amp;#8217;s stage directions, I&amp;#8217;ll leave those alone. Second, while
there were definitely more than a few fantastic voices (Stefan Margita,
Stephanie Blythe, Eric Owens, Hans-Peter König, Jay Hunter Morris), a
few important characters received weaker talent. Wotan, in particular.
Mark Delavan is a clumsy actor with a voice too thin to conjure the full
authority of the character. But these roles are all so incredibly
demanding, the fact they had voices left at all by the end deserves
great respect. (Bryn Terfel plays Wotan in the recordings that are
&lt;a href="http://www.metoperashop.org/shop/der-ring-des-nibelungen-met-opera-includes-wagners-dream-9608"&gt;available for
purchase&lt;/a&gt; on
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DVD&lt;/span&gt; or Blu-ray, and his portrayal ranges from tender to terrifying.
Sometimes tired,&amp;nbsp;though.)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the conductor, Fabio Luisi, managed to let me down too often.
There were times in Das Rheingold where the Met orchestra stated bold
themes less than boldly, and others when they rose too loud and
completely drowned out the singers. In Götterdämmerung, the orchestra
was frustratingly inconsistent. Especially in the brass. I don&amp;#8217;t know if
it was just one or several horn players having a bad night, but it was
highly uncharacteristic of this normally superior&amp;nbsp;ensemble.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, these are mere quibbles. Ring productions are always big,
expensive, exhausting, enormously challenging projects. To accept and
surmount the considerable technical and technological challenges that
Lepage&amp;#8217;s production entails honors Wagner&amp;#8217;s ambitions. Do the myriad
leitmotifs not derive from a few fundamental bases? Then isn&amp;#8217;t it
fitting to have the sets derive from variations on a common foundation,
i.e. the machine? The public seems more appreciative than the critics.
There were people outside with signs begging for tickets each night. The
always generous applause at the end of acts usually came well before the
last note sounded. And walking around listening to conversations, the
only negative comment I heard was from some poor young man complaining
over his phone about how he couldn&amp;#8217;t understand the plot or the singing
and couldn&amp;#8217;t leave and shouldn&amp;#8217;t have eaten Chipotle earlier in the&amp;nbsp;day.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Ring experts find the production too vanilla for their tastes, fine.
If you&amp;#8217;ve seen a dozen Ring cycles and are well familiar with Wagner&amp;#8217;s
intent, I understand that you want a new perspective. But most people
have not, and the machine together with the cast and orchestra make for
a brilliant introduction. In the end, I accuse the critics of deciding
the production a failure first, then inventing reasons to justify this
later. Perhaps blogger David Kim &lt;a href="http://www.bachtrack.com/appraisal-wagner-ring-cycle-robert-lepage-metropolitan-opera"&gt;sums it
up&lt;/a&gt;
best: &amp;#8220;The most virulent criticism I’ve seen of Lepage’s work comes from
music critics of many years standing who have particular interests in
twentieth and twenty-first century music. The most effusive praise comes
from websites dedicated to Wagner. That probably tells you most of what
you need to&amp;nbsp;know.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2013 01:19:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-05-10:preconceptions-part-2.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Preconceptions Part 1</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/preconceptions-part-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/04/preconceptions-part-1.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/04/preconceptions-part-1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight begins my first &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen"&gt;Ring
cycle&lt;/a&gt; at the
opera house. I&amp;#8217;ve seen the &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/9sgVjgraXsc?t=50s"&gt;Otto Schenk
production&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DVD&lt;/span&gt;, and the Live in
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HD&lt;/span&gt; performances of the &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/sHa3NO219lc"&gt;Robert Lepage
production&lt;/a&gt; in the theaters. I thought them
both fantastic productions. The former was much beloved by New York&amp;#8217;s
operavores. The latter has been
&lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2012/05/the-met-ring-cycle-critics.html"&gt;universally&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/topics/reference/timestopics/people/l/robert_lepage/index.html"&gt;panned&lt;/a&gt;.
It is that latter production that I will be seeing&amp;nbsp;live.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Criticisms mostly center around the set, dubbed &amp;#8220;the machine&amp;#8221;. Robert
Lepage is responsible for the Cirque du Soleil show,
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/xT9CXr2o5ME"&gt;Kà&lt;/a&gt;, in Las Vegas, and he brings his
high-tech artistry here. The machine is a dynamic backdrop consisting of
24 independently rotatable planks that can turn from a simple flat
screen to stair steps to the trees of the forest and more. The machine
has been called loud, distracting, alienating, shallow. My impressions
from the theaters were rather opposite. I found the use of the machine
highly creative and visually stunning. I thought it in keeping with
Wagner&amp;#8217;s ideal of the unified&amp;nbsp;gesamtkunstwerk.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I am well aware that the experience at the hall can differ
significantly, so I won&amp;#8217;t yet criticize the critics. For now, my
opinions are as&amp;nbsp;follows:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Otto Schenk production is about as traditional a staging as you&amp;#8217;ll
find. This is not a bad thing. Compare to productions out of
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/boa7zcaVOSo"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/PMhL011V7J4"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/osoKrvetnpU"&gt;Valencia&lt;/a&gt;, or the Mecca for ring-heads:
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/TJk4rb7za54"&gt;Bayreuth&lt;/a&gt; (pronounced bye-royt). There are
so many subtexts that one could project onto the Ring that many argue
the most enduring productions are the ones that do not confine the
interpretation in any way. A post-industrial American setting is novel,
but it restricts the message. By keeping the setting in an ambiguous
time and allowing the gods godliness, the opera is free to communicate
in whatever ways the viewer/listener is receptive. Schenk&amp;#8217;s sets and
costumes are stirring, the music and singing superb. I love this
production as well as anyone&amp;nbsp;else.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My viewing of the Gelb production seemed just as traditional. We are
still talking about gods and heroes. In some ways I gather that it is
even truer to the text. Some of Wagner&amp;#8217;s stage directions have been
ignored for technical reasons, but Gelb manages to adhere (sometimes to
ironic complaints of adding unnecessary details). The costumes and
singing are just as breathtaking. For my non-opera-going friends, the
Lepage production is the one I would introduce&amp;nbsp;first.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am being intentionally vague since I&amp;#8217;m trying to keep an open mind.
The rest of my impressions will have to come later. For now, my feelings
toward the new production are very positive. I will let you know in a
couple weeks whether the criticisms deserve merit or are merely&amp;nbsp;meretricious.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 04:18:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-04-25:preconceptions-part-1.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Amazing Engineering - Episode 1</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/amazing-engineering-episode-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/03/amazing-engineering-episode-1.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/03/amazing-engineering-episode-1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an experimental physicist, I spent more time engineering than doing
science. As a result, I&amp;#8217;ve come to greatly appreciate sophisticated or
clever works of engineering. Sometimes you read about accomplishments
that don&amp;#8217;t seem possible. I&amp;#8217;m starting a series on these sorts of
feats.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For the first episode, I&amp;#8217;d like to start with something I first learned
about as an undergrad. See if you can guess what this&amp;nbsp;is:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://d1jqu7g1y74ds1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/sunspot.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://d1jqu7g1y74ds1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/sunspot.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you guessed &amp;#8220;sea creature&amp;#8217;s eye&amp;#8221;, you would be wrong. If you guessed
anything biological, you would be wrong. It&amp;#8217;s actually an extremely
high-resolution image of a sunspot. (By the way, the image was taken
from
&lt;a href="http://www.universetoday.com/71971/amazing-sunspot-image-from-new-solar-telescope/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
article) Here&amp;#8217;s what&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;unique:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astronomical observations almost always involve focusing light of some
sort onto a sensor. But after traveling all the way here in a
more-or-less straight line through mostly nothing, light from the stars
has to pass through our atmosphere. X-rays get scattered like light in a
dusty room, while visible and infrared light get jumbled up from
atmospheric turbulence. Look above a hot car in the summer to see a
strong example of&amp;nbsp;this.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to make up for that is to stick your telescope in space, à la&amp;nbsp;Hubble.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other, more radical way is to correct for the jumbling. That&amp;#8217;s
right. Make a shape-shifting mirror that changes fast and accurately
enough to compensate for the atmosphere&amp;#8217;s messiness, and do it with
enough resolution to matter. It&amp;#8217;s the optical equivalent of
noise-canceling headphones. And it&amp;#8217;s significantly harder. Also, much
more precise. It&amp;#8217;s called Adaptive Optics. And, remarkably, it&amp;#8217;s been in
use since the late&amp;nbsp;90s.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technique involves using a point source in the sky, like a star, as
a reference. The active mirror element continuously changes so as to get
as tight an image of this reference as possible. This improves the
angular resolution of a telescope by a factor of about twenty or so.
Which means what used to be one blob can be resolved into a few hundred
smaller blobs, if they were ever arranged like&amp;nbsp;that.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is no star that&amp;#8217;s bright enough to use, then you can make one.
Lasers are used to illuminate a spot higher up in the atmosphere to use
for reference. Artificial&amp;nbsp;stars!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to look at the sun, though, things are harder for three
reasons. First, heating of the air at ground level worsens the jumbling.
Second, visible light is more susceptible to atmospheric turbulence than
the infrared light that&amp;#8217;s often more interesting for night-time
observations. Third, there&amp;#8217;s no point-like reference star to use, and
it&amp;#8217;s too bright out to make&amp;nbsp;one.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that image above captures quite a lot of engineering magic. It seems
like a given that we&amp;#8217;d have clear images of our closest star, but it
takes something as crazy as adaptive optics to actually achieve it. Oh,
and by the way, this technology has led directly to medical applications
(like improved laser eye surgery), so it&amp;#8217;s another case of pure science
leading to unexpected benefits elsewhere in&amp;nbsp;society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 20:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-03-31:amazing-engineering-episode-1.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category></item><item><title>A Little Night-Food Music</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/a-little-night-food-music.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/03/a-little-night-food-music.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/03/a-little-night-food-music.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the unaware, the title is a reference to Mozart&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eine_kleine_Nachtmusik"&gt;Eine Kleine
Nachtmusik&lt;/a&gt;.
Everyone knows the tune. Also for the unaware, &amp;#8220;night-food&amp;#8221; refers to
the food you eat at dinner. So you see, the title is clever and not at
all contrived because this post is about music to go along with dinner.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently hosted a dinner party and made some Korean food for the
occasion. The menu included ddukbokki as an appetizer which I dubbed,
&amp;#8220;evil rice sticks&amp;#8221;. They can be a challenge in their spiciness. The main
course included oxtail soup. I had fruit and sweet potatoes ready for
dessert, though my guests graciously brought more decadent&amp;nbsp;treats.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picking music for the appetizer was no problem. I chose a bit of
Paganini, Tartini&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Devil&amp;#8217;s Trill Sonata&amp;#8221;, and Liszt&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Mephisto
Waltz&amp;#8221;. Choosing music to match the soup was a bit more challenging. I
thought of Bydlo from Mussorgsky&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Pictures at an Exhibition&amp;#8221;, but that
fills less than 4 minutes. I considered adding some Soviet music
signifying the proud march of the working ox, but felt that could be a
bit heavy. I decided to play the entire suite and put on lighter fare
for after-dinner conversation. (It turns out my taste in music leans
dark, so my choices may not have been all that&amp;nbsp;light.)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized later that I neglected the tune once synonymous with the
consumption of hot, bovine flesh.
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LsReWx9XdNs"&gt;Hoedown&lt;/a&gt; from Copland&amp;#8217;s
Rodeo. Predictably, my palm darted towards my forehead at moderate
velocity upon that&amp;nbsp;realization.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not bother to try coming up with matches for fruit and sweet
potatoes, though I suppose I could have. &amp;#8220;Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy&amp;#8221;
would almost be appropriate, except for the unfortunate sentience of
that character. Perhaps there is a harvest song I could have&amp;nbsp;played.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would have gone on your playlist? Am I missing other songs about
cows or oxen? Are there any classical tunes about sweet potatoes?
Working the other direction, are there songs that you feel make a
natural fit for a particular meal? e.g. Schubert&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Trout&amp;#8221; quintet. Or
maybe Swan Lake if anyone ate&amp;nbsp;swan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 01:23:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-03-12:a-little-night-food-music.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Concert Etiquette</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/concert-etiquette.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/02/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/02/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concert hall is a unique place. I can think of no other place in
which the attention of so many people is so singularly focused. Be it
the opera, ballet, symphony, or chamber recital, the attention points to
the stage. And because the rests, the silence, in music is as important
as the notes (just ask &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4%E2%80%B233%E2%80%B3"&gt;John
Cage&lt;/a&gt;), that
attention remains unbroken through the performance. This leads to what
may seem a stifling atmosphere to many &amp;#8212; full of obscure and antiquated
rules and traditions. In actuality, there is only one rule, and it
exists for good reason. That rule is: do not disturb.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is a familiar rule. It is the reason we turn off our cell phones
and keep our feet down at the movies. It only seems so uptight in the
concert hall because nothing is amplified. Popcorn chomps are easily
obscured in a theater with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THX&lt;/span&gt;-certified surround sound. Any sort of
noise, be it shuffling your feet or un-sticking your sweaty hand from
your program, distracts fellow patrons from that which they paid and
came to&amp;nbsp;experience.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed that raw, unfiltered connection to the stage is partly what makes
it so exciting. In this hyper-connected, perpetually moving, modern age,
how rare and precious it is to join hundreds or thousands of others in
sharing an experience of human expression! Is it not for this reason we
attend sports games and attend concerts of other genres? Yet, as with so
many treasures, this one is fragile. Any small sound could obscure a
delicate touch of phrasing that separates the pleasant from the&amp;nbsp;sublime.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sudden distractions are like scratches on your favorite cd. And as
with cds, they are unfortunately unavoidable. I am very forgiving with
drops, coughs, and gasps (when elicited by an occurrence on the stage)
because these are involuntary. After all, most of the audience tends to
be elderly, no? It is the shuffling, cell phone glare, and whispering
that is so very distracting. I have heard announcements on more than one
occasion suggesting, &amp;#8220;if you would like to enjoy a candy or cough drop
during the performance, please open it now.&amp;#8221; We are serious about the&amp;nbsp;music.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one rule that I will confess is unnecessary. During
multi-movement works such as concertos and symphonies, we are to hold
our applause until after the final movement. I honor this, but I do not
begrudge those who do not. In my opinion, if the audience&amp;#8217;s
concentration really must not be broken between two movements, then it
is up to the conductor to maintain engagement. That is accomplished as
easily as by not dropping his hands. As for the performers&amp;#8217;
concentration, they are&amp;nbsp;professionals.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the end, that is all. Do not make noises, do not move excessively,
do not check your phone, do not wear strong fragrances, do not wear an
enormous hat. Do not whisper until the lights come up. This one is hard
for people, for some reason. But really, just do your best not to
disturb your neighbors, and enjoy what unfolds on the&amp;nbsp;stage.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final note, I have started my exploration into the data set
mentioned in the last post. It may take me some time to execute my plans
as I am still a novice programmer, but here is a peek without
explanation at what I have found so far. I have accepted the assistance
of a good friend with a doctorate in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CS&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;) so I hope that we will have
something fun for you&amp;nbsp;soon!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/tritone.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://blog.justalfred.com/images/tritone.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2013 03:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-02-19:concert-etiquette.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Renaissance</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/renaissance.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/02/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/02/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think I have to remind my readers what &lt;em&gt;renaissance&lt;/em&gt; means, but
that is what is going on&amp;nbsp;here.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;It has been well over a year since my last post, and
much has changed. For one, I can hardly call myself a physicist anymore.
Now I live and breathe data of the machine-readable form. My tools have
changed from solder and liquid nitrogen to python and hadoop. I have
also attended almost as many concerts since my last post as I had in my
entire life up to that point. I still do not have the ear or history of
a professional critic or musicologist, but I can certainly appreciate
much more than I could before. I am approaching three months in a grand
new city with wonderful opportunities to explore the arts. I intend to
take&amp;nbsp;advantage.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given these changes, I plan to extend the content of this blog.
Classical music will be a recurring theme as before, but I will start to
mix in some musings on technology, data, and other arts including food
and visual arts. Where these intersect with music, I will be sure to
post my thoughts. And I hope to share some creative work of my own in
time. In the past, I have concentrated on the quality of my writing, but
in the interest of sharing more content and ideas, you may notice a few
more typos and poor grammar here and&amp;nbsp;there.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of the type of content I would like to share, I leave you
today with this interesting tool: http://www.peachnote.com/ It appears
to have stopped returning results at the time of publishing, but when it
works, it allows you to search for melodies (minus the temporal
component). The term n-gram comes from natural language processing. The
keyboard on your smart phone probably does a fair job of predicting the
next word you intend to type. One way to do it is to go through a large
corpus of text (preferably one generated by people on their phones as
opposed to something less germane, like legal text) and count up how
many times words follow other words. We may find that &amp;#8216;whites&amp;#8217; is highly
likely to follow &amp;#8216;egg&amp;#8217;. So if a user inputs &amp;#8216;egg&amp;#8217;, we should recommend
&amp;#8216;whites&amp;#8217; for the next word. But we can do better by looking at
&lt;em&gt;bigrams&lt;/em&gt;. If a user types &amp;#8216;Easter egg&amp;#8217;, then the next word will very
seldom be &amp;#8216;whites&amp;#8217;. Something like &amp;#8216;hunt&amp;#8217; is more likely. Increasing the
pattern length to trigrams or up to arbitrary n-grams greatly increases
the quality of results, but quickly gets more expensive (in terms of
computing time) to train and&amp;nbsp;compute.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, the linked tool gives the frequency of melodies across a
time span rather than saying anything about what follows. But the data
are rich for experimentation and discovery with respect to how western
musical tastes have evolved over the past few centuries. Melodies of up
to 15 intervals (15-grams) are searchable here! Music is a
multidimensional stream and therefore difficult to represent in
machine-readable bits. This is a wonderful first step at extracting one
dimension in order to enable some discovery. I will be taking a crack at
it when I find the&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 01:57:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-02-11:renaissance.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category><category>info</category></item><item><title>The People’s House</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/the-peoples-house.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/10/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/10/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering that one&amp;#8217;s social graph is not uniformly distributed among
the general population, but rather concentrated around a small number of
highly-connected nodes, I think it is fairly safe to say that 100% of my
readers fall in the lower 99%. 
&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2011/10/12/141272600/is-opera-stuff-only-rich-people-like"&gt;Recent&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2011/10/13/141319827/opera-is-for-the-99-heres-what-you-told-us"&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt;
on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NPR&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s Deceptive Cadence blog discuss the widespread perception of
opera as exclusive to the 1%, the super-rich.  And yet here you&amp;#8217;ve come,
my commoners, to where I like to share my thoughts on that very topic. 
Responses to the posts ranged from accusations of opera being outdated
and out of touch to those blaming Hollywood for the false stereotypes. 
Many people pointed to their personally penurious positions and
penchants for opera as evidence against the stereotype.  I&amp;#8217;ll take the
argument a step further.  You will find few institutions more
egalitarian than the opera house.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Granted, at the major halls, there are seats that sell for several
hundred dollars each, and season subscriptions run easily into the
thousands.  I recall seeing back in 2010 that by donating about
$20,000, I think, to The Metropolitan Opera, one could reserve an early
spot in line to buy tickets to attend the new complete Ring Cycle in
2012.  Tickets for the cycle could themselves exceed&amp;nbsp;$3,000.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, an upcoming rap concert (not exactly an elitist
pastime) in the area offers tickets in the range of $72-$272. 
Meanwhile, rush tickets at even the most esteemed opera houses are
typically $20 or less while regular seats are usually available in the
neighborhood of $30.  Seats under $100 are sometimes more readily
available than those above.  Smaller companies can offer rush or regular
tickets for as low as $5.  Now opera seems the more economical&amp;nbsp;option.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cheap seats are not necessarily bad seats, either.  Seats on the
floor in front of the orchestra are some of the most expensive, but
suffer visual and auditory interference from obstacles between the seats
and the stage.  These patrons do, however, get to see and be seen, and
among the social elite, this is worth the premium.  Meanwhile, sitting
in the sloped balconies, you get a clear line of sight to the stage,
resulting in a purer experience.  The cheapest seats are normally in the
upper balconies.  This sets you farther from the stage, but in good
acoustic shape at most opera halls.  San Francisco occasionally even
employs &amp;#8220;OperaVision&amp;#8221; at select performances which hangs a projection
screen high enough to be unobtrusive that shows the stage action and
subtitles to further equalize the&amp;nbsp;experience.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cheapest seats may cost less than one tenth of the price of the most
expensive, but certainly do not deliver one tenth the&amp;nbsp;enjoyment.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it is common for opera companies to engage with their
public through outdoor showings, public broadcasts, or other kinds of
outreach.  They bring culture to more than just their cities&amp;#8217;&amp;nbsp;elite.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here we have an organization in which the rich subsidize the
involvement of the rest of us, and no one is forcing them.  They do it
willingly and eagerly at a rate that their beloved free market
dictates.  It gets better.  Ticket receipts don&amp;#8217;t begin to cover the
costs of each performance, but further contributions from businesses and
wealthy individuals fill the gap.  There are no cries of class warfare,
no calls for the impoverished to pay their &amp;#8220;fair&amp;#8221; share.  With this art,
everyone&amp;nbsp;wins.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost.  Unfortunately and ironically, many of the performers who bring
us this art suffer the most loss.  Professional opera singers have
trained for no less than eight to ten years, invested hundreds of
thousands of dollars, face intense competition, are at the mercy of
their physical health, and most are even fluent in Italian, French,
and/or German on top of their native English.  Opera performances are
scheduled a few days apart to preserve the singers&amp;#8217; voices.  If a
baseball pitcher tears a ligament, surgery will fix that in time.  If a
singer overexerts and damages her voice, the options are far more
limited.  And for all this risk, work, and sacrifice, compensation
remains paltry to the point that some cannot afford to attend their own
performances (if that were physically&amp;nbsp;possible).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the next time you go to the opera with your $20 rush ticket,
remember that some super rich suckers paid for their crummy $300 seats
so that you can witness a miracle of human achievement and cooperation
unfold before you at a cost that&amp;#8217;s a fraction of the value you get from
it.  No bouncer at the door sends you away for wearing a shirt of the
wrong color.  No talentless actor is making millions for standing coolly
in front of explosions on a screen.  No one gets into brawls because of
the winners or losers because no one wins or loses.  You can appreciate
that the opera house is a house of the people.  And for just an evening,
life feels&amp;nbsp;fair.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2011 17:39:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-10-19:the-peoples-house.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>ToreAmix</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/toreamix.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/09/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/09/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write a blog post on remixes, and in less than a week I discover a
perfect example of a high-concept remix album being released by Tori
Amos.  I confess I am not familiar with her discography, but I gather
that her latest album, &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/2011/09/11/140261371/first-listen-tori-amos-night-of-hunters"&gt;Night of
Hunters&lt;/a&gt;,
is an exceptional one.  You can listen to it in its entirety for free at
the link, presumably until the release date of September 20.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This album is released on the esteemed German classical label, Deutsche
Grammophon.  It&amp;#8217;s a modern day &lt;em&gt;song cycle&lt;/em&gt;.  These
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winterreise"&gt;collections&lt;/a&gt; of
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/An_die_ferne_Geliebte"&gt;songs&lt;/a&gt; centered
around a common &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwanengesang"&gt;theme&lt;/a&gt;
were popular in the late Classical and Romantic eras and are worthy of a
post of their own.  In this case, a continuous narrative spans the
entirety of the cycle.  Each song is essentially a remix of pieces
spanning 400 years.  Amos&amp;#8217;s vocals and piano work are accompanied by,
among others, the principal clarinetist of the Berlin Philharmonic, an
award-winning string quartet, and her daughter and&amp;nbsp;niece.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lyrics (libretto?) follow one half of a &amp;#8220;shattering&amp;#8221; couple on a
spiritual journey through space and time with a childlike shape-shifter
as guide.  Many of the individuals met along the way are represented by
various instruments.  The story resolves in acceptance of individual
misfortune and appreciation of the vaster calamities in the world.
(&lt;a href="http://www.echodust.com/2011/08/track-by-track-introduction-to-tori.html#more"&gt;Amos explains her album
here.&lt;/a&gt;) 
Why such a mythical narrative for this moral?  In Amos&amp;#8217;s
&lt;a href="http://www.out.com/detail.asp?page=1&amp;amp;id=31598"&gt;words&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;#8220;I decided to
take it to a place that I understood and a place that has mythology,
because good song cycles &amp;#8212; there&amp;#8217;s a level of otherworldliness &amp;#8212;
that&amp;#8217;s why it works. To me, if it doesn&amp;#8217;t have a poetic subtext going
on, and the characters don&amp;#8217;t come in that take us on some kind of
spiritual quest, then I don&amp;#8217;t think it will last for 50 years or 100
years. It has to transcend time in a way &amp;#8212; and yet reflect the time
you&amp;#8217;re in.&amp;#8221;  Wagner would wholeheartedly
&lt;a href="http://www.wnyc.org/articles/music/2004/mar/02/the-ring-and-i-the-passion-the-myth-the-mania/"&gt;agree&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I invite you to listen to the album even if you don&amp;#8217;t have time to
analyze the lyrics.  I haven&amp;#8217;t had the chance to sit for that long
myself.  But it&amp;#8217;s wonderful music.  I leave you with the track listing
with links to the sources for each song.&amp;nbsp;Enjoy!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/VO80Ras4dXE"&gt;Shattering&amp;nbsp;Sea&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/kZhaceWRKoE"&gt;SnowBlind&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/lgDPl6J3lIY"&gt;Battle of&amp;nbsp;Trees&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/se3oZOphUDU"&gt;Fearlessness&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/myRTkyWejfo"&gt;Cactus&amp;nbsp;Practice&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/Il6-lZYDpqY"&gt;Star&amp;nbsp;Whisperer&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Job&amp;#8217;s Coffin (Inspired by Nautical Twilight.  Not sure I get&amp;nbsp;that.)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/Re-eu9q_yUU"&gt;Nautical&amp;nbsp;Twilight&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/c8FUZ-saANQ"&gt;Your&amp;nbsp;Ghost&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/zWKl704J-8U"&gt;Edge of the&amp;nbsp;Moon&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/0LX3TRnAojw"&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Chase&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/YV3Avalm5KM"&gt;Night&lt;/a&gt; of
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/d5p_U8J0iRQ"&gt;Hunters&lt;/a&gt; (The second melody is hard to
place, but it&amp;#8217;s there.  Start at 0:39 in the chant, 3:23 in the&amp;nbsp;song.)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/oXfFMlxV53M"&gt;Seven&amp;nbsp;Sisters&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/KDv97T9ocLg"&gt;Carry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2011 05:53:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-09-17:toreamix.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Remix</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/remix.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/09/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/09/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my readers:  Apologies for the extended hiatus.  As it turns out,
finishing and defending a dissertation drains one&amp;#8217;s energy for
composition more than I anticipated.  After my momentum was lost, it was
hard to pick up the pencil, as it were, through travels, moves, job
searching and so on.  But I can only go so long without exercising my
creative muscle, and so I am back.  And today my topic is the remix.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Or is the term &amp;#8220;covers&amp;#8221;?  &amp;#8220;Edits&amp;#8221;?  &amp;#8220;Reworks&amp;#8221;?  I won&amp;#8217;t attempt to
differentiate.  What I am calling a remix is any piece of music that
draws heavily from an existing piece.  I think we are all familiar with
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/_jOfH-Qa0Dc"&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; in
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X5JALwwaASg"&gt;popular&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://ocremix.org/remix/OCR01182/"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;.  Some of these can be
earnest tributes to the original music; others are just lazy thefts of
creativity.  But they are not symptoms of the decline in the industry of
modern&amp;nbsp;man.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earliest example of which I am aware is the
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/mNMQu5LXaeI"&gt;organum&lt;/a&gt; of medieval music.  In this
style, the church took liturgical &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/2HEKhr002Ts"&gt;Gregorian
plainchant&lt;/a&gt; and added a harmonic vocal
line.  This evolved into the &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/FLD7FiHaTqE"&gt;motet&lt;/a&gt; where
vocal lines of different, often secular text were overlaid on, again,
Gregorian chant.  Since then, there has been a rich tradition of
composers writing &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/hqoamga8744"&gt;variations&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/OK7I284Xf3k"&gt;admired
works&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pictures_at_an_Exhibition#Orchestral_arrangements"&gt;other
composers&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in the linked examples of Mussorgsky, it can be quite interesting to
see what different arrangements can bring to a familiar melody.  Ravel&amp;#8217;s
orchestration has been criticized as too French, i.e. too soft and
mellifluous compared to the more discordant and percussive tone of the
original.  And yet the textural range accessible to an orchestra far
surpasses a single piano, so for many, Ravel&amp;#8217;s is the only version they
have&amp;nbsp;heard.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my very first post, I mentioned Schubert&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2OHJ0QwmzFs"&gt;Der
Erlkönig&lt;/a&gt; and the
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UWNCbpwC-PQ"&gt;transcription&lt;/a&gt; by Heinrich
Wilhelm Ernst.  It is one of the most popular lieder, and for good
reason.  The original combines drama, narrative, poetry, and &lt;em&gt;word
painting&lt;/em&gt; for a profoundly moving four minutes.  Compare the baritone&amp;#8217;s
performance to that of a &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/Iz5TV8LWbro"&gt;soprano&lt;/a&gt;.  Very
different performances, yes, but does the drama persist when sung by a
woman?  After all, three of the four characters are explicitly&amp;nbsp;male.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now focus for a moment on the triplet ostinato on the right hand of the
accompaniment.  (Try emulating that on your desk to get a feel for how
difficult it is.)  This motive evokes the urgent galloping of the horse
on which the father is riding with the son.  Berlioz
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/sTYqFzps0i4"&gt;orchestrated&lt;/a&gt; the accompaniment, but is
this an improvement?  Maybe the percussive timbre of a piano better
evokes the horse&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;hoofs.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going the other way, listen now to Liszt&amp;#8217;s
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/PFPSun30TBE"&gt;transcription&lt;/a&gt; for solo piano and Ernst&amp;#8217;s
transcription for violin linked earlier.  Once your head stops spinning,
consider whether anything is lost by condensing the lied into the
limitations of one instrument.  Does the melodic line get too broken
because of the need to maintain the triplet motive?  Does the loss of
explicit words lose much of the drama, even if you know what words are
supposed to be there?  Perhaps for you the exhilaration of seeing such
virtuosity offsets the lost elegance from the original composition? 
(&lt;a href="http://imslp.org/wiki/Erlk%C3%B6nig,_D.328_%28Op.1%29_%28Schubert,_Franz%29"&gt;For the
brave&amp;#8230;.&lt;/a&gt;)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more fun is when a substantial &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/MD6xMyuZls0"&gt;remix&lt;/a&gt;
of a &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/ra-mRawdH3o"&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; is itself substantially
&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/l6P54YocHLo"&gt;remixed&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the remix is nothing new in music.  They serve the same purposes and
are as contentious now as back then.  Some final thoughts to ponder: 
What are these purposes and who may benefit from them?  Are we prone to
favoring our first exposures to a piece?  Which version of &amp;#8216;Pictures&amp;#8217;
did you first hear, and is it the one you prefer?  What are some of your
favorite remixes?  They needn&amp;#8217;t lean towards virtuosic.  Or towards
trance, for that matter.  Let&amp;#8217;s have a&amp;nbsp;discussion!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2011 01:50:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-09-17:remix.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Quicklink 4</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/quicklink-4.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/03/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/03/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a single link for you today.  Life has been incredibly busy since
my last post.  It will continue to be very busy for the next month.  But
I can at least squeeze in posts like this one.  I came across &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2011/03/01/134160882/classical-music-shred-fest-which-pieces-get-you-pumped-up?ft=1&amp;amp;f=129702125"&gt;this fun
piece&lt;/a&gt;
in the blog I&amp;#8217;ve mentioned before.  I don&amp;#8217;t really agree with a couple
of his examples as being &amp;#8220;metal,&amp;#8221; but certainly you can imagine a heavy
metal cover of any of these pieces.  In fact, you can imagine heavy
metal covers to a lot of classical pieces.  Compare the opening to
Rachmaninoff&amp;#8217;s Piano Concerto no. 2 and Muse&amp;#8217;s Space Dementia, and
you&amp;#8217;ll hear clear similarities.  Or check out Epica&amp;#8217;s album, &amp;#8220;The
Classical Conspiracy&amp;#8221; for several cool rocked out versions of classical
music.  What classical pieces would you like to hear remixed into heavy
metal or sound metal to you in their own&amp;nbsp;right?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2011 05:35:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-03-21:quicklink-4.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Grad School Allegory</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/grad-school-allegory.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/02/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/02/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some friends of mine and I recently watched a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DVD&lt;/span&gt; of a production of the
opera, &amp;#8220;Dialogues of the Carmelites&amp;#8221; (1957) by Francis Poulenc based on
the &lt;a href="http://www.catholicapologetics.info/library/onlinelibrary/martyrs.htm"&gt;Martyrs of
Compiègne&lt;/a&gt;. 
It&amp;#8217;s somewhat modernist, being almost completely in recitative with
occasional ensembles.  Unfortunately, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DVD&lt;/span&gt; forewent subtitles since
the production used the English libretto, but can anyone ever understand
a soprano in any language?  I understand the libretto is deep and
thoughtful (&amp;#8220;Dialogues&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;), so I&amp;#8217;m sorry we missed out on that.  Still,
it ends with a most heartbreaking scene.  I could not stop thinking
about it, so I looked up a few different productions of that scene on
YouTube and decided I liked &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GcUXp-fpiD0"&gt;this
one&lt;/a&gt;.  Watch it once and
tell me it doesn&amp;#8217;t move you.  Yes, that is the sound of a guillotine
that repeats 16 times for these 16 nuns.  Listen to the texture of the
music thin down from chorus to quartet, trio, duet, solo.  It&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;tragic!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I realized it works as an allegory for our sad lives as PhD
students.  Read on for my translation.  And excuse the sacrilege.  It&amp;#8217;s
just satire.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scene opens with a group of shabbily-dressed women being rounded up
by soldiers.  The women are PhD students.  The soldiers are the
government.  See how they&amp;#8217;re forcefully rounding up the students instead
of letting them volunteer out of their own interest?  That&amp;#8217;s like how
the persistently insufficient funding for education and research forces
us grad students to be exploited as cheap labor under false pretenses of
a sure career in academia instead of letting us choose to enter grad
school based on realistic considerations of the value of that
education.&amp;nbsp;Yep.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, an angry mob gathers.  They&amp;#8217;re the ignorant public.  You might see
some tea-party folk in there.  They think magnets make you healthy, but
cell phones make you sick.  They don&amp;#8217;t like seeing their tax dollars
&amp;#8220;wasted&amp;#8221; on things like research or arts education.  That&amp;#8217;s why they&amp;#8217;re
so arm-wavingly mad.  You can see that government can keep them in
check, but it&amp;#8217;s also acquiescing to their demands to stop funding the
grad students.  Go figure.  You can see that some of the students are
confused and don&amp;#8217;t know how to deal with the unwarranted&amp;nbsp;vilification.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Government opens up a path.  Kinda looks like an ivory tower, right?  By
following that path, the students are giving up their lives.  They all
kinda realize it, but they&amp;#8217;ve come this far, so why stop&amp;nbsp;now?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see they&amp;#8217;re not happy about it, though.  Everyone but the black
woman is on her knees.  One student collapses, but she&amp;#8217;s helped by
remembering that at least she doesn&amp;#8217;t have it as bad as the black
student who somehow manages to stay strong.  The black student is also
reminding everyone of the dream by making their hands into
representations of that ivory&amp;nbsp;tower.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, so now the black student is the first to defend her thesis so she
can take on the world.  In other words, she&amp;#8217;s the first to get put
down.  Of course.  She touches her head (gotta be smart), heart (gotta
be calm), and shoulders (gotta be able to resist the abuses of the
examining committee).  They all start singing, &amp;#8220;Salve Regina,&amp;#8221; which you
might translate as, &amp;#8220;Hail the Queen.&amp;#8221;  Think of it as a pep rally. 
They&amp;#8217;re encouraging each other.  That shaggy dude in the crowd who makes
the sign is an old drop-out who knows what&amp;#8217;s in store for&amp;nbsp;everyone.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a sad procession of students defending their theses only
to have their lives taken away and their dreams crushed.  About halfway
through, you see one student despair.  Another comforts her.  &amp;#8220;Be
strong.  We can do this.  We&amp;#8217;ll reach that ivory tower!  You go first.&amp;#8221; 
And a little later, who&amp;#8217;s that lurking in the shadows?&amp;nbsp;hmm&amp;#8230;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two left.  And then one.  In a moment of clarity she realizes the
futility and starts to run back to normal life.  But who should pop out
of the shadows?  It&amp;#8217;s her old classmate returned as an adjunct!  (or
postdoc, if you wish)  You can tell because even though her clothes are
still shabby, at least her face isn&amp;#8217;t dirty.  Seeing this illusion of
success revives the notion that there&amp;#8217;s hope in academia and she goes
back up the path cheering herself&amp;nbsp;on.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally the adjunct/postdoc makes the climb, though she sings a
different tune.  The music is more despondent, tired, fatalist.  You
hear her end.  Then echoes of the procession.  Finally everyone leaves
to bite the next hand that fed them forgetting anything these students
ever&amp;nbsp;did.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s just like real life!  But in all seriousness, these victims of
Robespierre&amp;#8217;s Reign of Terror find worthy remembrance in Poulenc&amp;#8217;s
beautifully haunting music.  Whether Catholic or not, one must be moved
by their grace in martyrdom.  I still get shivers listening to this&amp;nbsp;tableau.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2011 17:59:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-02-19:grad-school-allegory.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Quicklink 3</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/quicklink-3.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/02/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/02/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is somewhat old news now.  Anthony Tommasini, classical music
critic for the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYT&lt;/span&gt;, started the year posing the question, &amp;#8220;Who are the
10 greatest composers in history?&amp;#8221;  The subsequent
&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/09/arts/music/09composers.html"&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2011/01/07/arts/music/20110107-top-ten-composers.html"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt;
are thoughtful and present something of a quick tour through music
history.  The rest of the articles are listed
&lt;a href="http://artsbeat.blogs.nytimes.com/tag/top-10-composers/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; in
reverse chronological order.  The final list is announced
&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/23/arts/music/23composers.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
It&amp;#8217;s just for&amp;nbsp;fun.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/nation/la-na-white-house-pianist-20110125,0,52927.story"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s
a story that demonstrates why one must be thoughtful if one is to
command an international audience without inadvertently insulting&amp;nbsp;people.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2011 00:10:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-02-13:quicklink-3.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Virtuosity</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/virtuosity.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/02/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/02/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A belated&amp;nbsp;post&amp;#8230;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I will explore the notion of virtuosity and what it means to me. 
Let&amp;#8217;s start with the Oxford Dictionary Online&amp;#8217;s
(&lt;a href="http://oxforddictionaries.com/?attempted=true"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ODO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) definition of a
virtuoso: &amp;#8220;a person highly skilled in music or another artistic
pursuit.&amp;#8221;  Seems simple enough, but when talking about new words or
ideas, I find it instructive to consider the edges.  No one would argue
against applying the appellation to &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k8K53QCdS20"&gt;Yehudi
Menuhin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dxzpy1b1_BY"&gt;Arthur
Rubinstein&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L5C99JyP2ns"&gt;Jacqueline
du Pré&lt;span style="font-family: inherit; font-size: small;"&gt;&lt;span
class="Apple-style-span"
style="border-collapse: separate; color: black; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; white-space: normal;"&gt;&lt;span
class="Apple-style-span"
style="line-height: 15px;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
so heaping more praise on them does little to clarify anything.  But
what about soloists less celebrated?  Do they deserve the designation? 
Is skill all that matters or does depth of expression make a
difference?  What about dancers, authors, or painters?  Why are we more
likely to proclaim a poet a genius than a virtuoso?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What is the difference between a genius and a virtuoso, anyway?  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ODO&lt;/span&gt;
says a genius is &amp;#8220;a person who is exceptionally intelligent or creative,
either generally or in some particular respect.&amp;#8221;  In common usage, we do
usually associate geniuses with exceptional intellect (e.g. Hawking,
Wittgenstein, Ken Jennings), creativity (e.g. Shakespeare, Mozart,
Kandinsky), or both (e.g. da Vinci,
&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/01/science/01butterfly.html"&gt;Nabokov&lt;/a&gt;,
Edison).  Virtuosi are associated with exceptional skill in performance,
especially live performance.  Sometimes they display genius in this
regard (e.g. Hilary Hahn&amp;#8217;s thoughtful interpretation of the fiendish
Schoenberg Violin Concerto), sometimes not (e.g. Lang Lang&amp;#8217;s
over-dramatic interpretations of, well,&amp;nbsp;everything).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;#8217;s a start towards our target.  Although the poet is highly
skilled in an artistic pursuit, it is his creativity that we cherish,
and so he is dubbed a genius.  Likewise with a composer of music.  But
the prima ballerina or the marimbist (as in my last post) is cherished
for her skill in execution.  There is creativity involved, to be sure. 
But I can come up with a creative interpretation of the Moonlight
sonata.  That does not mean it will be skillfully-executed unless maybe
I record a dozen takes and splice together the best moments.  In front
of an audience, there is only one chance to get it right.  It is the
singular nature of this experience and the acknowledgment of the
requisite talent and dedication that compels us to bestow upon our
virtuosi a title greater than&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;performer&amp;#8221;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how good do you have to be?  Do we call every solo musician who
tours internationally a virtuoso?  What about those musicians who play
full-time with orchestras?  There is a different emphasis in their
performance, but it is still performance.  Unfortunately, I think this
is where arguments are unavoidable.  I, personally, think the world&amp;#8217;s
major orchestras boast some of our greatest virtuosi, and some do manage
to do some solo touring.  If you consider that the solo bassoon or
French horn repertoire is only so large, effectively precluding a
full-time solo career for many instruments, then one understands why
this is so.  But the question changes for violinists or cellists.  Where
do the sets of virtuosi, solo violinists, and orchestra violinists
intersect?  This boundary to the definition, I am afraid, must remain a
subjective&amp;nbsp;matter.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about popular musicians, like &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-5VwPfyEq3w"&gt;John
Petrucci&lt;/a&gt; of Dream Theater,
Mariah Carey, or &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ItZyaOlrb7E"&gt;this
drummer&lt;/a&gt;?  Martial
&lt;u&gt;artists&lt;/u&gt; like &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=18t7H7i7VIw"&gt;Bruce
Lee&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1igTGE1_kTs"&gt;Jet
Li&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfA0TzmYRww"&gt;this
guy&lt;/a&gt;?  Or sports greats
like, well, ok, I don&amp;#8217;t know sports.  Take your pick.  They are all
celebrated for the skill which they demonstrate in live, unedited
performance.  The musicians certainly ought to be eligible though it
simply isn&amp;#8217;t customary to call them virtuosi.  Yet it doesn&amp;#8217;t seem right
to call Michael Jordan a basketball virtuoso.  True, sports are not
typically considered an artistic endeavor.  But what difference is there
between watching a tennis match and a judo match?  Not a whole lot.  But
there is a big difference between watching a judo match and a wushu
form, like in the linked young Jet Li video.  Insofar as the
demonstration of a martial art or other athletic activity is an
expression of the practitioner, I think the term, virtuoso, can be
applied.  If it is simply one athlete reacting to the actions of the
other athlete(s), I think there is no art.  But perhaps this gets into
an argument over the nature of&amp;nbsp;art.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So these are my opinions.  To summarize, the virtuoso is one who
demonstrates considerable skill (not necessarily depth or sensitivity)
in live performance of an artistic (i.e. expressive) nature.  I am sure
there will be those who disagree with me, and I would love to hear your
arguments.  Please, indulge me.  I leave you with two last thoughts.  Is
it fair for our criteria to be different for performers from different
times or backgrounds?  When do we stop calling a child a prodigy and
start calling her a&amp;nbsp;virtuoso?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2011 22:11:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-02-12:virtuosity.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Quicklink 2</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/quicklink-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/01/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/01/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#8217;t given you a real post since before Christmas, and all I have
to offer today is a couple of fun links.  My apologies.  I&amp;#8217;m working on
a couple of posts, but they&amp;#8217;re taking more research to complete than I
expected.  I haven&amp;#8217;t been feeling particularly inspired to write about
simpler topics.  See, I have this other writing project that has to take
priority for some&amp;nbsp;reason&amp;#8230;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So today,
&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2011/01/14/132930151/the-classical-interrogation-room?ft=1&amp;amp;f=129702125"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
is a cartoon that proves I&amp;#8217;m not alone in a sentiment to which I&amp;#8217;ve
twice referred&amp;nbsp;before.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second is a lovely &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6k705AhOzKc"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;
of the winner of an online competition for young musicians.  She&amp;#8217;ll get
to perform in Carnegie Hall and feature in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NPR&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;From The Top&amp;#8221; program
which features pre-collegiate musicians from around the country.  I
share this in part because of a joke I recently heard: What do you call
a person who hangs around musicians?  A percussionist.  That&amp;#8217;s what&amp;#8217;s so
great about this.  How often does anyone, let alone a kid, get to
demonstrate this level of proficiency in a percussion instrument?  How
many professional female percussionists do you ever see in orchestras or
as soloists?  (I can only think of Evelyn Glennie who also happens to be
deaf.)  And how often does anyone look at a percussionist alongside a
slew of violinists, pianists, cellists, etc. and decide that the
percussionist is more talented?&amp;nbsp;Brava!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep this young lady in mind as we&amp;#8217;ll be considering her in my next
post.  I&amp;#8217;ll try to get it up in the next week or two.  But really, I
need to be making better progress on my other&amp;nbsp;endeavor&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 04:18:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-01-17:quicklink-2.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Happy New Year</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/happy-new-year.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/01/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2011/01/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year, folks.  Something something auld lang syne.  This blog
is still young and impressionable, so maybe this is a good time to tweak
its direction.  Anything you&amp;#8217;d like to see more or less of?  Do I link
too many YouTube videos?  Do you even watch them?  I aim to please.  You
know what would please me?  If you come up with illustrations, examples,
or counter-examples of the things I mention here, especially from music
that&amp;#8217;s not classical, share them with me!  I would love more&amp;nbsp;dialogue.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In parting, here&amp;#8217;s a tune to bid farewell to the old year: &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gRCzEQTP_Ks"&gt;Chopin Piano
Sonata No.&amp;nbsp;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2011 05:42:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2011-01-03:happy-new-year.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Christmas post</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/christmas-post.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s Christmas, I&amp;#8217;m on vacation, so here&amp;#8217;s a short post for you to&amp;nbsp;enjoy.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;First, I want to point out a couple articles that
tickled my fancy.  The first is a story about a flash-mob &lt;a href="http://www.mercurynews.com/top-stories/ci_16912758?nclick_check=1"&gt;gone
wrong&lt;/a&gt;. 
In Sacramento, a flash mob was arranged to sing Handel&amp;#8217;s Halleluiah
Chorus (&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZCFCeJTEzNU"&gt;best rendition
ever&lt;/a&gt;).  The organizing
group made arrangements with the mall and made sheet music available
online for people to study.  But so many people showed up that the floor
started to shake.  Some likened it to an earthquake.  They had to
evacuate the mall.  Handel would be&amp;nbsp;proud.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is an article from the somewhat new classical music blog on
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NPR&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/"&gt;Deceptive Cadence&lt;/a&gt;.  I
get a lot of inspiration and material for this blog from here.  &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2010/12/14/132035046/least-favorite-christmas-song?ft=1&amp;amp;f=129702125"&gt;This
article&lt;/a&gt;
is a fun little conversation about least favorite Christmas songs.  I
have to agree with Tom.  I never could stand &lt;em&gt;Little Drummer Boy&lt;/em&gt; and
I&amp;#8217;ve already mentioned how much I hate Ravel&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;Bolero&lt;/em&gt;.  I love how he
compares the two.  What are your least favorite/most hated Christmas
songs?  I&amp;#8217;ve always wondered if music majors get irritated with how
&lt;em&gt;Deck the Halls&lt;/em&gt; butchers the &lt;em&gt;solfege&lt;/em&gt; (fa la la la la la la la la
should be re mi fa re mi re do ti do, right?)  And while it&amp;#8217;s true I
don&amp;#8217;t ever want to see &lt;em&gt;The Nutcracker&lt;/em&gt; ballet, I do enjoy the music. 
There&amp;#8217;s just something grotesque to me about the costumes and the
dancing and the phantasmagoria&amp;#8230;.  Leave me alone, it creeps me out. 
But share what songs you hate this season.  Or at least what songs
you&amp;#8217;re happy you won&amp;#8217;t have to hear for another year after&amp;nbsp;today.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a good year, overall.  Thanks, my friends, for reading and
taking an interest in my interest.  Have a Merry Christmas and happy New
Year!  Or if you don&amp;#8217;t celebrate Christmas, at least enjoy the fact that
you&amp;#8217;re getting at least a day or two off of&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2010 14:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2010-12-25:christmas-post.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>SATB</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/satb.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That stands for &lt;em&gt;soprano&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;alto&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;tenor&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;bass&lt;/em&gt;. That&amp;#8217;s just a
scoring for choral works common enough to get an abbreviation. You may
have noticed if there are choirs in your church that there are the high
and lowish female sections and highish and low male sections of the
choir.  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SATB&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that&amp;#8217;s easy enough. But I also wondered, what&amp;#8217;s a &lt;em&gt;baritone&lt;/em&gt;?
Doesn&amp;#8217;t &lt;em&gt;treble&lt;/em&gt; mean something? The three tenors don&amp;#8217;t sound that high.
I never heard them singing &lt;em&gt;falsetto&lt;/em&gt;. (That&amp;#8217;s the higher register of
your voice associated with yodeling which, by the way, is really hard
whether you enjoy it or not.  Try it.) If you&amp;#8217;ve wondered these things,
too, then read on.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I took my music history class (instead of something useful, like
the physics of oxides) we were taught that female voices are classified
as &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FMPv8mADpA4"&gt;soprano&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OV-ZfCWM3qo"&gt;mezzo-soprano&lt;/a&gt; (mezzo for
short), and &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0ddOhDxbWgU"&gt;contralto&lt;/a&gt;
where soprano is the highest.  Male voices are classified as
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RdTBml4oOZ8"&gt;tenor&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IO62fj__ehA"&gt;baritone&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JStPRk62QdI"&gt;bass&lt;/a&gt; where tenor is the
highest.  This was simple, and this made sense.  But then I recalled
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bmYRQWYlDbM"&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; which I&amp;#8217;d
encountered some time prior.  In case this sounds like screeching to
you, I direct your attention to Dessay&amp;#8217;s precise &lt;em&gt;intonation&lt;/em&gt; even as
she makes the leaps across the &lt;em&gt;disjunct&lt;/em&gt; melody (wide pitch &lt;em&gt;intervals&lt;/em&gt;
between notes).  Also, notice her easy, wide, consistent &lt;em&gt;vibrato&lt;/em&gt; (are
those wide enough to be trills sometimes?), her ease singing softly and
loudly, and the extra, little flourishes that she executes that just
amplify the difficulty of the song.  This, in my opinion, is an
excellent demonstration of &lt;em&gt;virtuosity&lt;/em&gt;.  It&amp;#8217;s technically solid without
being&amp;nbsp;ostentatious.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How is this relevant?  Well, looking through the comments, I saw her
described as a &lt;em&gt;coloratura soprano&lt;/em&gt;.  Eh?  So there are different kinds
of sopranos?  Well, it just so happens that beyond the six vocal ranges
I just mentioned, there are also classifications into voice types. 
According to the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voice_type"&gt;wikipedia
article&lt;/a&gt;, sopranos can be
further classified into coloratura sopranos, lyric sopranos, dramatic
sopranos, soubrettes, and spintos.  The difference between these voice
types depends on such things as vocal color, agility, range of the
various registers, where the voice is most comfortable regardless of
overall range, etc.  But it gets a little worse.  Coloratura sopranos,
for instance, can be further classified as lyric or dramatic
coloraturas, or as sfogato sopranos.  Compare the differences
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coloratura_soprano#Listen_and_Compare"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;#8217;t just opera arcana akin to the amateur sommelier&amp;#8217;s spouting of
nonsense aromas he purports to detect in a Virginian chardonnay that he
thinks is French.  It&amp;#8217;s actually really important for these singers to
be classified correctly.  One mezzo &lt;a href="http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2010/11/15/DDJK1GBHJ9.DTL"&gt;recently
learned&lt;/a&gt;
that she&amp;#8217;s actually a soprano, an experience that she compared to
undergoing a sex change.  Had she not discovered this sooner, there
would have been serious risks to her voice and career.  Maria Callas
&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=123612228"&gt;famously&lt;/a&gt;
astounded critics early on by triumphantly filling roles written for the
coloratura soprano to the dramatic soprano and even into mezzo
territory, but soon wore out her voice.  You wouldn&amp;#8217;t ask a person built
as a line-backer to play as a quarterback (did I get that football
analogy right?) without expecting problems.  Likewise for singers.  You
can work to extend your range, and certainly many singers can fill roles
spanning a small range of classification.  But pushing boundaries too
far can be&amp;nbsp;dangerous.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we haven&amp;#8217;t covered all of the ranges yet, have we?  Turns out treble
refers to prepubescent boys or girls with a soprano range.  What about
the male falsetto?  Some of you may recall the &lt;em&gt;castrati&lt;/em&gt; popular in the
Baroque era.  Through a surgical manipulation prior to puberty, the
church maintained in these men child-sized vocal cords with
superman-sized rib-cages to back them up.  This produced ideal qualities
for &amp;#8220;angelic&amp;#8221; singing, but at a great cost.  Fortunately, the practice
is no longer condoned.  But who&amp;#8217;s to sing the many phenomenal parts
written for these poor men?  The closest modern equivalent is the
&lt;em&gt;counter-tenor&lt;/em&gt;.  I just learned this a couple days ago.  It&amp;#8217;s basically
a guy who &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WX83BSR0mug"&gt;sings well&lt;/a&gt; in
the falsetto register.  And, of course, there are subclassifications. 
Some of you might find the sound disorienting, interesting, beautiful,
or possibly even hot.  They don&amp;#8217;t have the huge voices and stamina of
castrati, but at least they have their manhood.  And this really isn&amp;#8217;t
very uncommon in popular music, is it?  Think of Prince, Matthew
Bellamy, Thom Yorke, and&amp;nbsp;others.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, I have to wonder, by probability alone, shouldn&amp;#8217;t there be some
accidental castrato sitting around in India or China that we don&amp;#8217;t know
about?  Kids hurt themselves in weird ways all the time.  Wouldn&amp;#8217;t it be
interesting to hear?  I&amp;#8217;m just&amp;nbsp;saying.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you have it.  Following the world&amp;#8217;s singers is as complicated
and interesting as following baseball players.  They all have their
roles, fortes, styles, career development, injuries, and so on.  It&amp;#8217;s as
exciting when a seasoned singer joins a new production as when a
seasoned player joins a team.  And it&amp;#8217;s as confounding to my mind trying
to keep track of it&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2010 22:04:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2010-12-19:satb.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Quicklink 1</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/quicklink-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heard about this from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NPR&lt;/span&gt; today:
&lt;a href="http://howtolistentomusic.tumblr.com/"&gt;http://howtolistentomusic.tumblr.com/&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or for the YouTube channel directly:
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/howtolistentomusic"&gt;http://www.youtube.com/user/howtolistentomusic&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This music critic goes through popular songs and rates each section
(identified in the upper right) on the instrumental, lyrical, and vocal
aspects with notes when appropriate. (It&amp;#8217;s a little awkward when he
can&amp;#8217;t get permission to play the actual song&amp;#8230;) It&amp;#8217;s rather subjective,
of course. But it&amp;#8217;s still an interesting look at how one critic makes
his judgments. What I found most useful is seeing the sections
identified (i.e. the form of the piece). You may notice a frequent
formula emerge from the more banal songwriters.&amp;nbsp;Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2010 19:44:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2010-12-15:quicklink-1.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Austin-auto</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/austin-auto.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A kind friend forgave my ignorance of popular and indie music since I
know a fair deal about classical music. This, she deemed, was an
elevated sort of knowledge. The compliment was appreciated, but I can&amp;#8217;t
logically justify it to myself. Knowledge of classical music is just as
useless in everyday life as baseball stats or celebrity gossip. Perhaps
more useless since people rarely ever know what I&amp;#8217;m talking about. Also,
I can&amp;#8217;t say that my focus is any more intense during a performance than
a football fan&amp;#8217;s is during a game, though perhaps my memory is more
actively engaged. I can&amp;#8217;t see how naming members of any of the world&amp;#8217;s
orchestras (which I can&amp;#8217;t do) is any more valuable than naming players
on sports teams. My performance abilities are no more keen for my
interest than the Guitar Hero addict or the guy who plays pickup
basketball on weekends. You&amp;#8217;re probably just as able to pick out a song
appropriate to a mood or situation from popular music as I am from&amp;nbsp;classical.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As another example, I complain that so many popular songs are little
more than looped tracks with maybe some key changes and vocals on top.
Well, guess what? That&amp;#8217;s existed in classical music for centuries. A
phrase that&amp;#8217;s repeated over and over like that is called a &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;ground bass&lt;/span&gt; or an &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;ostinato&lt;/span&gt;. You know &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6wpPk8qk3uQ"&gt;Pachelbel&amp;#8217;s
canon&lt;/a&gt;, right? A lot of
string players &lt;span style="font-size: 78%;"&gt;(pretend they)&lt;/span&gt; hate
playing it because it&amp;#8217;s the &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JdxkVQy7QLM"&gt;same &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GD&lt;/span&gt;
thing&lt;/a&gt; over and over again.
Ravel&amp;#8217;s Bolero is another example that uses an ostinato which I won&amp;#8217;t
link because I hate it that much. The use of ostinati went out of
fashion for a century and a half but came back for different purposes.
And while not technically an ostinato, listen to the different repeated
figurations in the left hand of this &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qnz91LnGSD4"&gt;Mozart
sonata&lt;/a&gt;. (Who can name what
the low-high-middle-high bass pattern that starts the piece is called?)
Or in the right hand of this &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O6txOvK-mAk"&gt;Beethoven
sonata&lt;/a&gt;. So I can&amp;#8217;t say I&amp;#8217;m
above repetitive music&amp;nbsp;either.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, most of what gets played is not heavy on ostinati the way jazz
or rap music is. But there are other sorts of repetition. A song in
&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;strophic&lt;/span&gt; form repeats a theme
with each stanza. &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Fugues&lt;/span&gt;
consist of several statements of a main &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;subject&lt;/span&gt; sometimes with &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;episodes&lt;/span&gt; between each statement.
&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Rondo&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;ritornello&lt;/span&gt; form similarly repeats a
statement of a main theme between other themes. Even the grand &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;sonata-allegro&lt;/span&gt; form involves a total
of three statements of the first, second, and closing themes along with
any variations in the development and&amp;nbsp;coda.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some respects, repetition serves to lighten the burden on the
composer to write new material. But it also offers a chance for
brilliant development of ideas. For a very fundamental example, take
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N6K_IuBsRM4"&gt;Beethoven&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ijiHzheK4GQ"&gt;Symphony&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Mt7NIPFgQk"&gt;no.
5&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-mZ4_aWfH7s"&gt;C
minor&lt;/a&gt;. (All four movements
there for ya.) It opens with the most famous four notes in the world.
And that simple rhythmic motive, short-short-short-long, is used in a
thousand variations of mood, melodic &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;contour&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;texture&lt;/span&gt;, and so on throughout the
entirety of the work. Repetition that&amp;#8217;s not repetitive. Certainly there
are artists today who accomplish this as well, but they tend not to be
as popular. I have a theory about that, but that&amp;#8217;s another&amp;nbsp;post.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So maybe that&amp;#8217;s one aspect to classical music that earns it the epithet
of &amp;#8216;elevated&amp;#8217;. Quite often, you have to really be paying attention to
even notice when it&amp;#8217;s being repetitive. And isn&amp;#8217;t it a joy to be paying
attention? You can walk past the Mona Lisa and think it&amp;#8217;s just a
painting of an odd-looking woman. Or you can understand the history,
details, and genius behind and in that masterpiece and feel honored for
the&amp;nbsp;experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 03:51:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2010-12-13:austin-auto.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Form and Its Function</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/form-and-its-function.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/form-and-its-function.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/12/form-and-its-function.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#8217;s your favorite form for poetry? Haiku? Sonnet? I bet you like the
limerick. If I told you I had a limerick to share, you would expect a
five-line poem with an aabba rhyming scheme and probably a dirty
subject. If you wanted to compose a love poem, the sonnet is an obvious
choice. We tend to like poetry with a set meter and rhyming convention
because then we know what to expect. It&amp;#8217;s useful for both poet and&amp;nbsp;listener/reader.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same applies to music. There are forms with fancy names like
ritornello, sonata-allegro, or fugue. Even popular music tends to follow
a form with verses, refrains, an outro and such. As with poetry, knowing
the form of a piece you&amp;#8217;re listening to gives you an idea of what to
expect and sometimes an indication of the tone. The third movement of
symphony will tend to have a dance-like or playful quality, for example.
I find form in music to be much harder to track, though. It often
involves hearing a theme once at the beginning, and recognizing that
theme when it recurs as a variation. When you&amp;#8217;ve heard three other
themes in between, well, that&amp;#8217;s a lot to hold in your head even without
getting distracted by thoughts like, &amp;#8220;wasn&amp;#8217;t I supposed to call
someone?&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;oh yeah, this reminds of that one time on that orchestra
trip when&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221; I think I&amp;#8217;m learning some tricks, like paying attention to
key changes, but any others would be&amp;nbsp;appreciated.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with poetic forms, composers have long pushed the boundaries of
musical forms. Beethoven expanded just about every part of the symphony.
Mendelssohn placed the cadenza of his violin concerto before the coda,
rather than after. People like Schoenberg invented totally new forms.
Compare a Mahler symphony to a Mozart one, and you&amp;#8217;d scarcely recognize
any similarities. That&amp;#8217;s how art advances. As long as there is some
semblance of the original form, I think the function is still served.
It&amp;#8217;s like writing a poem with an abab rhyming scheme for 20 lines, then
throwing in a different couplet. It&amp;#8217;s not what you expect, so it gets
your&amp;nbsp;attention.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What doesn&amp;#8217;t work for me is when people claim an established form and do
something completely different. Last night, I watched Stanislav Pronin
perform Lera Auerbach&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Par.Ti.Ta&amp;#8221;. Now, a partita is traditionally a
suite of dances performed on a solo instrument. The movements in this
were titled Adagio, Moderato, Andantino Scherzando, and so on. These are
tempi, not dances. And they were anything but dancelike. Pronin said
he&amp;#8217;d asked Auerbach why it was spelled the way it was. The response was,
&amp;#8220;First of all, it looks cool.&amp;#8221; Auerbach seems to have solid credentials
and a long publication history, so maybe it&amp;#8217;s me missing something here.
But if I sold you a Com.Bo.5 and you got a sandwich with nothing else,
you&amp;#8217;d be a bit miffed. It doesn&amp;#8217;t matter how good the sandwich is; your
expectations were not met. Even if it was two sandwiches, it&amp;#8217;s not what
you think of as a combo. You want some kind of side and a drink,&amp;nbsp;right?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. There is organization and tradition in the forms
of western art music that takes time to learn, but provides a richer,
more active listening experience. You can even try listening to the form
of popular songs. See who has the creativity to break away from the
simpler forms. It&amp;#8217;s fun, as long as your mind doesn&amp;#8217;t drift off to your
shopping list, or whether you just missed your&amp;nbsp;turn&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2010 19:59:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2010-12-05:form-and-its-function.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item><item><title>Introduction, first loves</title><link>https://blog.justalfred.com/introduction-first-loves.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/11/None.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2010/11/None.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my new classical music blog. As you probably know, I&amp;#8217;m
approaching the end of my PhD work in condensed matter physics. In the
time I&amp;#8217;ve been here I&amp;#8217;ve found myself more and more enamored with the
world of classical music, by which I mean Western art music. Bravo if
you know why the former term is somewhat ambiguous. Visitors to this
site probably fall under two categories. You&amp;#8217;re probably either
scientifically-inclined with a curiosity about classical music, or
you&amp;#8217;re one of my friends who was a music major. I aim to write primarily
for the former group. I want to spread this love I have so that more
people can come to appreciate the beauty that I experience. But I ask
for assistance from the latter group. I may know more than the average
person, but I will leave out details or context or get things wrong from
time to time. I make no claim to be an expert (not even with physics,
ha!). I mean really, I&amp;#8217;ve only very recently begun to be able to discern
the form of a piece I&amp;#8217;m listening to. (I still suck at it, but it&amp;#8217;s
pretty exciting.) In my never-ending quest to learn more about classical
music, I ask that you enrich my posts with any knowledge, corrections,
opinions, or suggestions that you have. Even if you&amp;#8217;re saying that a
post is completely erroneous or naive, I will love you for it. You may
even gain something from the physical/scientific perspective I may take.
We&amp;#8217;ll see how it&amp;nbsp;goes.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve stated, my primary reason for starting this blog is to share my
passion with the uninitiated. I plan to do this by sharing stories,
articles, and videos with you. I may write about a piece that&amp;#8217;s stuck in
my head, concerts I&amp;#8217;ve attended, or some factoid that I think is
entertaining. I already have a list of topics going. Requests will be
honored if I feel capable. Should I be allowed to post on other topics
that strike my fancy such as food, literature, or science? I haven&amp;#8217;t
decided. For now I think it&amp;#8217;s best to keep this blog to one&amp;nbsp;topic.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let me start things off by sharing my background with classical
music. Through playing the violin in middle and high school, I came to
know much of the standard violin and symphonic repertoire. But I found
myself far outclassed by the time I reached college to continue playing.
So I lost my enthusiasm for, but was never too far removed from,
classical music. Then I attended a monumental (for me) concert during my
first year here in grad school. I had seen and met this particular
violinist in college when she was just starting to cause a stir in the
classical music community and was awestruck by her talents then. Seeing
the now-world-famous &lt;a href="http://www.hilaryhahn.com/"&gt;Hilary Hahn&lt;/a&gt; perform
the Glazunov &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C2mnr81jCWw"&gt;violin
concerto&lt;/a&gt; (and the Ernst
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UWNCbpwC-PQ"&gt;transcription&lt;/a&gt; of
Schubert&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2OHJ0QwmzFs"&gt;Der Erlkönig&lt;/a&gt; as
her encore) ignited in me a new passion for this music that&amp;#8217;s persisted
since. Yes, I met her again after that concert, and yes, she&amp;#8217;s still my
favorite musician ever. But that story is worth a post of its own. At
this point I started listening and listening to my old favorite
symphonies and violin concertos, then to ones I didn&amp;#8217;t know and also to
piano concertos, cello concertos, lieder, chamber pieces, opera,
sonatas, character pieces, and so on. Eventually I took a freshman level
music history class which was wonderful for consolidating and organizing
the random tidbits that I knew. That was followed by a group
introductory piano class and, most recently, private lessons in piano. I
go to concerts when I can, especially if I&amp;#8217;m traveling, and I started a
small group to watch operas on DVDs. To say I&amp;#8217;m hooked is an&amp;nbsp;understatement.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2010/09/23/130076390/classical-fans-tell-stories-of-first-loves?ft=1&amp;amp;f=129702125"&gt;recent
segment&lt;/a&gt;
on &amp;#8220;All Things Considered&amp;#8221; discussed listeners&amp;#8217; &amp;#8216;first loves&amp;#8217; in
classical music. I encourage you to follow the link. Some of the stories
are particularly moving. Specifically, though, they asked about pieces
of music. That disqualifies Hilary Hahn as my answer, so I&amp;#8217;ll give my
actual first. The earliest piece I can remember loving is Antonio
Vivaldi&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Rhvtm9LmXI"&gt;The Four
Seasons&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#8221; I guarantee
you&amp;#8217;ll recognize it. My uncle had a videotape of some ensemble (which
one I never knew) performing it. I remember the short, fat, old solo
violinist&amp;#8217;s impeccable technique bewildering my young mind. That image
with the evocative and memorable melodies gave me a reason to practice
my technique. Eventually, I was able to hack my way through the suite,
which I did. Often. Much to my classmates&amp;#8217; chagrin. I&amp;#8217;m somewhat
thankful that no recordings exist of my playing back then. It would be
painful to hear&amp;nbsp;today.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;#8217;s &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; first love in
classical music. If you have one, what&amp;#8217;s &lt;span
style="font-style: italic;"&gt;yours&lt;/span&gt;? Do share. I would love to
hear. Please comment or message/email me about this post and others you
find interesting in the future. If I don&amp;#8217;t feel that I&amp;#8217;m reaching anyone
or learning anything in the process, it will be hard for me to continue
this. I&amp;#8217;ve enabled anonymous posting. As regards the title, well, it
makes sense if you know my given name. Thanks for reading. I hope we can
keep this&amp;nbsp;up.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2010 06:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2010-11-28:introduction-first-loves.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Music</category></item></channel></rss>