<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Just Alfred</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Truth and Beauty</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/truth-and-beauty.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am one of those people who has always believed himself to be incomplete.
I&amp;#8217;m often asking, &amp;#8220;What am I doing wrong?&amp;#8221; I&amp;#8217;m never good enough. I&amp;#8217;m unloveable.
My work is never up to my standards. I&amp;#8217;m usually afraid to&amp;nbsp;try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been reading a lot on resilience and philosophy lately. It&amp;#8217;s been undoubtedly
helpful. It&amp;#8217;s clear that many of my questions and judgments are not well-formed.
As my good, respected friend framed it, you can always have worked harder or faster.
You can always have done something just a little bit better.
So those sorts of judgments have no value.
I recognize I&amp;#8217;ve been far kinder to others than to myself.
But old habits are hard to&amp;nbsp;break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, I&amp;#8217;ve granted myself a slightly extended amount of time off to find balance.
To figure out a frame of mind from which I can be a better person sustainably.
But this, too, starts from the wrong premise.
This still assumes that there is some concrete, better model of myself that I can identify and
move confidently towards.
This still involves a search for a truth that will always escape&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href="http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24113.G_del_Escher_Bach"&gt;Gödel, Escher, Bach&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#8217;s extremely elegant.
But one reminder for me is that even number theory, the study of the properties
of numbers, the study of the theorems of arithmetic—even this is incomplete.
There is no way to systematically arrive at all true statements.
There is also no way to evaluate the truth value of a given statement.
What could be more cut and dry than arithmetic?
And yet our knowledge here is bounded.
Arithmetic is &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/goedel-incompleteness/"&gt;necessarily incomplete&lt;/a&gt;.
What hope do any of us have of completeness&amp;nbsp;ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn&amp;#8217;t call for a renunciation of truth or hope, but I think I&amp;#8217;ll try something different.
I think I&amp;#8217;ll try searching for beauty instead.
Kant connected moral reasoning with our purely rational faculties via beauty and aesthetics.
Maybe engaging with the beautiful is what I&amp;#8217;ve been missing as I seek kinder truths.
Nature, art, ideas, animals, people.
I&amp;#8217;ll try connecting.
There&amp;#8217;s no real program here.
I&amp;#8217;m following it on purely on&amp;nbsp;faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#8217;s in this context that I find myself in my host family&amp;#8217;s spare home
overlooking the lake with cool weather, colors starting to decorate the sky.
Sitting down with a serving of Scotch, reading material in hand,
and a Bach 6-part fugue referenced in the aforementioned book
(the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6QA212M70hM"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ricercar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
from his &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Musical_Offering"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Musical Offering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
to be exact) on my headphones.
Exceptional audiophile headphones that were gifted from my last company.
The sound is glorious. The music is brilliant. It&amp;#8217;s stirring. It&amp;#8217;s&amp;#8230; beautiful.
And I stop, and I appreciate, and I sip my Scotch. And I remember.
This Scotch was collectively gifted to me by my coworkers when I left my job.
There&amp;#8217;s love in these drops.
Beauty has reminded me of a beautiful&amp;nbsp;truth.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-07-09:truth-and-beauty.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Present</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/present.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I entered the next room in the contemporary art room at the Corning Museum of Glass and was drawn immediately to the pure forms.
A figure represented in printed, offset &lt;a href="http://blog.justalfred.com/images/plates.jpg"&gt;glass plates&lt;/a&gt;;
a large, slightly bulging &lt;a href="http://blog.justalfred.com/images/black_cube.jpg"&gt;cube of black glass&lt;/a&gt;.
Then I found Nicole Chesney&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.cmog.org/collection/rakow-commission/nicole-chesney"&gt;Present&lt;/a&gt;.
A nacreous, abstract atmosphere painted and wiped across a glass canvas.
And I started to&amp;nbsp;think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty. Why? Do others find it pretty? Would I have found it pretty ten years ago?
Will I find it pretty in ten years? What am I supposed to see? Why does it matter?
What do other people think about when they take the time to experience this piece? Is that what matters?
Are we connected somehow? I don&amp;#8217;t see a story or an object or a scene. Just a feeling.
It feels delicate. It exhibits &lt;em&gt;wabi-sabi&lt;/em&gt;. I want to protect this.
It&amp;#8217;s not Japanese, and yet it feels Zen all the same.
I see a faint, clouded reflection of myself. I feel like I&amp;#8217;m here, but I&amp;#8217;m not.
Approaching &lt;em&gt;muga&lt;/em&gt;. I start to detach. I want others to see this and experience&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with these thoughts in mind, I made my own&amp;nbsp;art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self Portrait: Relinquishing My&amp;nbsp;Self&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.justalfred.com/images/self-portrait1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://blog.justalfred.com/images/self-portrait1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-01-10:present.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Excerpts of 2016</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/excerpts-of-2016.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I write far more personally than publicly. Here are some excerpts from entries throughout 2016.
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resolutions&amp;#8230;Plan.&amp;nbsp;Learn&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;Who am I?&amp;#8230;Thank you&amp;#8230;I don&amp;#8217;t have&amp;nbsp;answers&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;Lovely breakfast&amp;#8230;I actually do like who I am for the most part these&amp;nbsp;days&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;I&amp;#8217;ve been naïve&amp;#8230;Philosophy&amp;#8230;Let&amp;#8217;s apply&amp;nbsp;this&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leadership. New challenge&amp;#8230;What&amp;#8217;s the point of&amp;nbsp;dating/relationships?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;I will only gain this by pushing myself into discomfort&amp;#8230;I could smile again the next day&amp;#8230;I want&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I need&amp;#8230;I&amp;#8217;m not&amp;#8230;People love&amp;nbsp;me&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;I know it&amp;#8217;s not true. But the words still sting&amp;#8230;It&amp;#8217;s inspiring to observe&amp;#8230;Lovely visit&amp;#8230;The friend I want to be: reliable, trustworthy, helpful, attentive,&amp;nbsp;respectable&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&amp;#8217;m&amp;nbsp;tired&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;She&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;she&amp;#8230;She&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8230;They were all supportive&amp;#8230;Heck yeah&amp;#8230;I feel like I have a great new&amp;nbsp;friend&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commentary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I have learned, forgotten, grown, regressed, smiled, and suffered.
I&amp;#8217;m still grasping for control and searching for meaning, but with less judgment.
I&amp;#8217;m better able to help the people around me, and it turns out there&amp;#8217;s nothing more fulfilling to me.
I&amp;#8217;ve retracted into my shell somewhat, but it&amp;#8217;s richer inside than before.
This year, I want to share more of it with the people who would see.
Thank you, my&amp;nbsp;friends.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2017-01-01:excerpts-of-2016.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>You are an Antichrist</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/you-are-an-antichrist.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Correlation is not Causation. Any student of statistics has heard this repeated
time and again. But the world is complex and dynamic, and our mental capacity
has to fit in the 20-Watt, 3 pound organic mass inside our skulls. We&amp;#8217;re wired
to see patterns and when we notice B happen right after A enough times, we&amp;#8217;re
liable to think &amp;#8220;A caused B&amp;#8221;. This is good for the survival of the primitive
human. But we are not primitive. Are we? Perhaps to prove we are not, there
were those philosophers as Leibniz who went so far as to deny that
causation even really existed.
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But any reasonable person would accept that we can justifiably say that
&amp;#8220;A causes B&amp;#8221; provided a governing model and evidence to support said model.
Fire causes burns. This is useful and, moreover, reliable. It&amp;#8217;s not a far
stretch from there to allow statements of the form &amp;#8220;A prevents B&amp;#8221;. From there,
&amp;#8220;The absence of A causes B&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;The absence of A prevents&amp;nbsp;B&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, given an acceptance of causation, through action and inaction
we have effects on the world. Note that these aren&amp;#8217;t usually easy or possible
to trace (see chaos theory or the butterfly effect).
Given that every event could have generated a multitude of outcomes (even
the staunch determinist has to allow for the probabilistic nature of
quantum mechanics) there are an infinity of possible worlds that never come
to&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a subset of these possible worlds, our inactions or actions permit or
create a person who brings as much concurrent peace, harmony, and joy to
humanity as is possible. A&amp;nbsp;savior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we have acted or not acted, and thus this person does not exist. Our
actions have prevented this person, or the absence of our actions have
prevented this person. This person could have existed in an infinity of
forms, and some of these (an infinity of these) have been rendered impossible
by&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could all have effected a different chain of events, but we did not.
We could all have brought into being a savior to the world or become one
ourselves, but we did not. Our awareness of this effect is irrelevant. A
murderous machine is defective and requires termination regardless of its
awareness of its nature.
Therefore we are all guilty of causing harm to humanity. We are all&amp;nbsp;sinners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this same line of reasoning can also bring us to its opposite
conclusion. Logic is&amp;nbsp;fun!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-04-16:you-are-an-antichrist.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Renaissance Role Models</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/renaissance-role-models.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Who are your role models? Who are the people you try to emulate in some
aspect or other of life? Maybe parents? Maybe celebrities? Maybe fictional
characters? What are they like as&amp;nbsp;people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who are your celebrity crushes? Who are the people you like to look at
or watch? Maybe film stars? Maybe athletes or models? What are they like
as&amp;nbsp;people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did anyone come up in both&amp;nbsp;lists?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess that most people would answer no. I guess also that for most people,
the second list is longer. Probably a lot longer. And that&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;unfortunate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read an interesting piece recently about &lt;a href="http://www.thebookoflife.org/on-using-sex-to-sell/"&gt;advertising in the age of the
Renaissance&lt;/a&gt;.
I haven&amp;#8217;t been able to verify all the details, but the central ideas were
familiar to an art historian friend of mine. Here&amp;#8217;s the&amp;nbsp;gist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ficino/"&gt;Marcilio Ficino&lt;/a&gt;, an Italian
Renaissance Philosopher under the employ of the Medici family, wanted art to
educate. Art triggers contemplation if it engenders a desire to understand. We
desire to understand when we feel the engagement of love. And the quickest path
to love is to appeal at a sexual&amp;nbsp;level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, sexy advertising is a quick means to capturing attention which we
can then steer towards high&amp;nbsp;aims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closest direct quote of Ficino&amp;#8217;s I&amp;#8217;ve found refers to beauty rather than
sex appeal, but the idea still merits&amp;nbsp;conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas Renaissance art would depict idealized human forms,
often nude, to convey grace, harmony, and compassion, these days the idealized
human forms portrayed convey little more than material and physical notions.
That&amp;#8217;s a lost opportunity. We have sex appeal down to a science. What if we
could harness that power to improve&amp;nbsp;society?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a smaller scale, I think we might do our communities a service by
attempting to perform as sexy/beautiful role models ourselves.
We could collectively decide to be the best people
we can be, and through charisma and style inspire others to emulate us. I
definitely don&amp;#8217;t mean all others. I&amp;#8217;m certainly one who can only ever hope
to appeal to a small subslice of the general population. But for the people
who find something attractive about the way I carry myself, I want them to
discover other virtues as they learn more about me. Those who have more charm
and good looks can hope to positively influence more&amp;nbsp;people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us already try to be good people, and most of us also already try
to present well. What&amp;#8217;s novel in this mindset is in the motivation of
the latter. You might style your hair, dress of a fashion, or apply your
makeup with the aim of being respectable to colleagues, comfortable for
a setting, or simply to feel attractive. Seldom do we do so with the aim
of inspiring others. With this mindset, an otherwise
vain concern gains a measure of&amp;nbsp;nobility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like this idea so far, but I see two major pitfalls to consider. I&amp;#8217;d love
to hear of&amp;nbsp;others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, this is a wholly different proposition for men and women.
The standards of beauty/sexiness are vastly unequal. This argument can
easily be interpreted as an elaborate way of telling women to &amp;#8216;smile&amp;#8217;, a
detestably common occurrence resulting from many men&amp;#8217;s misguided belief
that women are supposed to make them feel good. I am not encouraging anyone
to diminish herself or&amp;nbsp;himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sexy in whatever way you wish to be (sexy doesn&amp;#8217;t have to be sexual) and
beautiful in the ways that you know you are.
Embody the virtues you wish for the world to celebrate. Let these two efforts
support and motivate each other. I want us to celebrate the
best of ourselves. Not to objectify or dehumanize&amp;nbsp;ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, to the last point, serving as a role model can be interpreted as only
communicating the happy, positive, strong, successful sides of ourselves.
I think this is a damaging pattern, and I think we should be allowed to share
our darker, weaker selves. Let&amp;#8217;s not pretend to be perfect. Everyone faces
some degree of adversity. Let&amp;#8217;s demonstrate ways to face it with poise,
compassion, and&amp;nbsp;humility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One&amp;#8217;s quality as a human being and one&amp;#8217;s fitness as a role model should have
nothing to do with your attractiveness, but human nature isn&amp;#8217;t so egalitarian.
Instead of lamenting this flaw in our wiring, let&amp;#8217;s exploit it to better&amp;nbsp;society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(footnote: there are psychological studies that support many of the claims
and observations here, but as an outsider to the domain, I don&amp;#8217;t know which
are well established and which have yet to be replicated. So I decided not
to reference literature whose quality I don&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;understand.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;postscript 2016-05-28: After a couple months letting this stew, I think the
call to action here shouldn&amp;#8217;t be to pretty ourselves up. Not everyone wants to
be the object of attention. We &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; try to embody the virtues we admire
anyway. I don&amp;#8217;t have a problem with that part. So the real call to action is
just to notice those who choose to combine physical appeal with other virtues
and not see it as distracting from those virtues. It&amp;#8217;s ok for a professor
to be hot in more ways than&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-03-26:renaissance-role-models.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Caseo-exploration</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/caseo_exploration.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Day after day, month after month, I would aimlessly poke through the company
kitchen looking for snacks I knew weren&amp;#8217;t there. I knew what was behind all the cupboard
doors, I knew what was in the fridge, I knew I wouldn&amp;#8217;t want anything there.
But I&amp;#8217;d look anyway, because humans make no&amp;nbsp;sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cupboards had the same nuts, chips, popcorn, and cookies. The fridge had the same yogurt,
hummus, and cheeses. Including those gross, little Babybel cheeses. The ones with the laughing
cow. My mother told me they&amp;#8217;re referred to as &amp;#8220;cow head cheese&amp;#8221; in Korea. Which means something
else here&amp;#8230;. I learned that there&amp;#8217;s a whole collection of images online of figures and sculptures
molded from the red wax coating. In my mind, that coating makes each unit of cheese a miniature cheese
wheel. Individual, miniature, hermetically sealed cheese wheels. So you ought to be able to age
Babybel cheese the way you do a cheddar or a gouda. Day after day, month after month, I looked
at those Babybel cheeses and wondered what an 18-month Babybel cheese would look and taste like.
Finally, I decided there was only one way to find&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.justalfred.com/images/cheese_experiment.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://blog.justalfred.com/images/cheese_experiment.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week marked the 18-month anniversary of the oldest in my collection. I didn&amp;#8217;t collect
the cheeses with rigorous regularity, but I was satisfied in the end having a somewhat even
spectrum of ages. It was time to examine. Opening the freshest of the four samples presented
no surprises. The 5-monther was noticeably moist. The 11-monther was wet and felt firmer
and denser. It was also noticeably more yellow than its younger brethren. The 18-month
sample expressed considerable moisture, felt even more firm,
and had a lovely (actually, a nauseous) grey, mottled patina. None was terribly aromatic,
except for maybe a scent of decay from the oldest&amp;nbsp;sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After regaining our confidence lost from seeing the drippy, grey sample, we started our vertical
tasting with the best of the bunch. Best, as in it hadn&amp;#8217;t outlived its &amp;#8216;best by&amp;#8217; date.
Most people are probably familiar with the salty, sour taste and the soft texture
that kind of sticks to your teeth. I guess a lot of people enjoy it. I&amp;#8217;m not&amp;nbsp;judging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 5-month sample tasted quite different. It tasted pungent and had a different texture. We
wondered whether the recipe had changed along with the&amp;nbsp;packaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 11-month sample was more noteworthy. The flavor was mellowed and slightly nutty.
The texture had relaxed into something like a custard or a firm panna cotta.
Smooth, dense, but yielding and not at all sticky. My friend detected formaldehyde.
I&amp;#8217;m not familiar with that particular vapor, but yes, there was a trace of something of
an origin that perhaps shouldn&amp;#8217;t be cheese. Some soft cheeses produce ammonia as they age,
so maybe it was&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was only brave enough to cut into the core of the oldest sample, which presented
small volume to evaluate. But further complexity was present. There was also a cheddar-like
sharpness that was absent from the other samples. The texture was similar to the 11-month
sample. Aside from the frightful exterior, this was the most cheese-like of&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn&amp;#8217;t get sick. I got to enjoy a nice Spanish-themed dinner
with my good friends. And I enjoyed months of happy anticipation for the unveiling.
Any regrets? That I didn&amp;#8217;t start this sooner. And I wish I took better notes of my impressions.
But in the end, I consider my hypothesis proven correct with caveats.
Yes, Babybel cheese will age and gain character. But it will gain unfriendlies that you
don&amp;#8217;t want to eat. Pros and&amp;nbsp;cons.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-02-13:caseo_exploration.html</guid></item><item><title>Der Tod und Der Atheist</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/der-tod-und-der-atheist.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Tod_und_das_M%C3%A4dchen"&gt;Schubert&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vKh4JsWvsPw"&gt;lied&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Atheist (me, hopefully not any time&amp;nbsp;soon):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not just yet! Oh, not just yet! &lt;br /&gt;
There is so much left to learn! &lt;br /&gt;
I have obligations to fulfill! &lt;br /&gt;
Let me do more good. &lt;br /&gt;
Let me do more good. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Death (also&amp;nbsp;me):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give me your hand, you fragile, defeatist soul! &lt;br /&gt;
I am a friend, and come not to judge. &lt;br /&gt;
Your debts are paid! You&amp;#8217;ve earned friends&amp;#8217; love, &lt;br /&gt;
Surrender your sensations to serenity! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2016-01-30:der-tod-und-der-atheist.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Proust in the Park</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/proust-in-the-park.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I can easily spend an entire day in front of a computer reading articles and writing emails, and by the end of the day I won&amp;#8217;t be able to recall half of what crossed my eyes.
It may feel industrious to spend so much time ingesting information and ostensibly learning, but the human brain has its limits.
With the mind zipping back and forth between the task at hand, the next task to come, the needs of your peers, the way to phrase a request, the bills that you can&amp;#8217;t forget to pay, your posture, are your zippers and buttons closed, the errand you need to run on the way home, the messages you need to pass along, the last thing you said to the person you&amp;#8217;re trying to impress whose validation you need, the emails you owe people, the wording of your next clever tweet, the next thought comes and goes before the last has had time to settle comfortably in your accessible&amp;nbsp;memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m trying to simplify my routine and cut out the extraneous.
If I only allow myself half a mind&amp;#8217;s worth of attention and a minimum of time on a task like reading, then it&amp;#8217;s worth no time at all; I won&amp;#8217;t remember the details anyway, I won&amp;#8217;t experience the gist, and it takes time away from being fully engaged in something else, something more meaningful.
It means acknowledging that I will miss out on interesting research, funny stories, insightful commentary, but half-engaged, I would be effectively missing out anyway.
So I&amp;#8217;m aiming to spend time more fully engaged in fewer activities.
It requires training, though; the mind does not easily focus on one thing for&amp;nbsp;long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And why should it?
If early humans fell frequently and naturally into states of singular focus, they would have been ill-suited to deflect the myriad dangers present in open nature.
This is the evolutionary psychological justification for the capriciousness of our consciousness.
To reject this default requires training; mindfulness meditation of the secular Buddhist variety is one form of training that particularly interests me, partly because so many of its central teachings are consistent with modern psychology.
Yet, I haven&amp;#8217;t progressed much with mindfulness practice, so I&amp;#8217;m trying alternative means to the same end as easier first&amp;nbsp;steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent some time with my host family after leaving my last job; more sympathetic and less judgmental than my real family, I have nothing but positive associations with their home and their company.
In conversation, they mentioned the &lt;em&gt;Duane Moore&lt;/em&gt; series by Larry McMurtry.
I gathered that these were sort of a Proustian telling of a life lived in Texas.
In fact, in the book &lt;em&gt;Duane&amp;#8217;s Depressed&lt;/em&gt;, the eponymous character is assigned by his therapist to read the first book of Proust&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;Remembrance of Things Past&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;more recently translated as &lt;em&gt;In Search of Lost Time&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;and is given one year to do so.
Fiction as therapy.
&lt;em&gt;In Search of Lost Time&lt;/em&gt; is a 4,000-page series of seven books that is infamous for its serpentine prose and extended phrasing.
But many point to Proust&amp;#8217;s uniquely intricate and evocative manner of capturing the thoughts, experiences, and observations of a life lived from boyhood through old age.
He reminds us of the details in the everyday that makes life so fascinating and ennobles us to find deeper meaning in our own existences.
In my unemployment and goal of further self-discovery, I decided to follow Duane&amp;#8217;s lead and read &lt;em&gt;Swann&amp;#8217;s Way&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proust&amp;#8217;s style does indeed test one&amp;#8217;s limits of concentration.
By the time you&amp;#8217;re out of the third nested appositive, you&amp;#8217;ve usually forgotten the start of the sentence.
A month later, I&amp;#8217;m 80 pages in, but I&amp;#8217;m motivated to keep at it.
After some warm-up, I can sometimes get into a flow where I can read a few pages before my mind wanders and I have to go back and re-read a bit.
With some training, I hope to get into this flow more easily&amp;#8212;an alternative to meditation.
I&amp;#8217;ve taken to heading to the park to read; it&amp;#8217;s away from the distractions of home&amp;#8212;music, endless tidying up, emails&amp;#8212;and unlike a coffee shop, I can take as much time as I like without feeling bad for taking up space.
It&amp;#8217;s a lovely park that&amp;#8217;s always full of crowds in the summer except at its quiet, shaded peripheries, and just a quick stroll from home.
I didn&amp;#8217;t discover it until several months after moving into the neighborhood; it was in the opposite direction as work.
The way we explore a new city is funny; familiar routes feel shorter, rectilinear streets are more welcoming, and the journey home is always faster.
Once my brain accepted this park, it was easy for me to immediately treat as ordinary the great central fountain and the immense, gleaming, white arch at its side.
We notice, we accept, and we move&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other day, I made it a point to take a leisurely stroll around the park to take in the environs as if for the first time before settling into a quiet, shady spot to dig into my book.
I noticed.
A conversation in Russian, a couple in the grass whose posture in dalliance must have taxed the young man&amp;#8217;s strength, a leisurely group of police officers, several tables of chess players including one with a young, clean-cut boy trying to impress an older, disheveled man, a kind-looking, attractive young woman walks my way&amp;#8212;but I shouldn&amp;#8217;t make eye contact unless I were intent on engaging, and how would you do that mid-stride in a park, anyway?&amp;#8212;and walks by followed by an older woman with a small dog who smiles at me, I forgot that there are public restrooms in this park, a squirrel takes a glance at me then decides to keep digging for whatever it thought it smelled, some flowers catch my eye; I wonder how much maintenance they require, a group of college students pass by, all smiles and banter, ice cream sandwiches for $4, I wonder if that price is strategic since many would drop a five and leave the change, a man with a mask hovers over a boy on the ground while a woman films from above, student film, probably.
And then I found my spot.
It was shady, and from my guess of where the shadows would travel, would remain shady.
A peek upwards noticed no avian nuisances to drop an interruption to my reading.
Sitting down, I took a moment to take in the cool breeze&amp;#8212;most welcome when so much of the summer has been sticky and oppressive.
When I see others wrapped in light cardigans and sweaters, I know I&amp;#8217;ll be a little more comfortable in my single layer.
And thus I&amp;nbsp;began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrator recounting his boyhood described the apparent reality of the fictional worlds contained in the books he read&amp;#8212;even more viscerally real than the landscape beyond the book in front of his eyes.
And then passed the old woman with the dog again&amp;#8212;I wonder why she smiles at me.
Back to fiction.
No, the thoughts that exist only in my mind are all fiction.
Unless I asked, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t know whether that woman was actually smiling at me or to herself.
Even then, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t know for sure, so I&amp;#8217;m free to make up whatever accounting pleases me most.
We all do this all the time; our thoughts and beliefs aren&amp;#8217;t reality&amp;#8212;only a personal fiction that, hopefully, does not depart too much from the personal fictions of others.
So, specifically, back to my reading.
After a bit, the narrator&amp;#8212;or more accurately, Proust&amp;#8212;went on to describe the advantage of&amp;nbsp;fiction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novelist&amp;#8217;s happy discovery was to think of substituting for those opaque sections [of another person], impenetrable by the human spirit, their equivalent in immaterial sections, things, that is, which the spirit can assimilate to itself.
After which it matters not that the&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I was distracted by excited shouts; not angry, more celebratory, as you would hear at a parade or around a talented street performer.
A double decker tour bus seemed to be stuck in an intersection not far ahead of me, and a second followed close&amp;nbsp;behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After which it matters not that the actions, the feelings of this new order of creatures appear to us in the guise of truth, since&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More shouts, and above the rhythms and the jazz from the local buskers, I heard the strain of a soprano singing what might have been opera.
I tried to place the direction, but soon lost the voice&amp;nbsp;entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230; the feelings of this new order of creatures appear to us in the guise of truth, since we have made them our own, since it is&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two buses decided to park just in front of me, and a picture-taking crowd gathered.
Signs informed that it&amp;#8217;s Body Painting Day, and the upper deck of both buses were filled with topless, painted people.
That explains the revelry.
But no, they weren&amp;#8217;t merely topless, they were all completely nude and painted head to toe.
The city provides some odd experiences, to be sure, and I was tempted to snap a picture as others were doing (&amp;#8220;pics or it didn&amp;#8217;t happen&amp;#8221;), but decency in my mind prevailed and I decided to afford the liberated crowd a bit of privacy.
I quickly realized how silly that was.
Obviously these people were perfectly happy, proud even, to be in public essentially nude and attracting a lot of attention, so why would they be ashamed to be in a photograph?
That reasoning was confirmed when they got off the buses for a photo op in the park.
I decided I respected the confidence many of these people&amp;#8212;whom popular fashion would tell to be ashamed of their bodies&amp;#8212;must have to expose themselves so publicly in so celebratory a fashion.
That confidence must be rooted in a firm, unyielding self-love; something I&amp;#8217;ve only recently realized I&amp;#8217;m missing and I need.
But the happy shouts and gathering crowd were interrupting my reading, so I got up and found another&amp;nbsp;spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novelist&amp;#8217;s happy discovery was to think of substituting for those opaque sections [of another person], impenetrable by the human spirit, their equivalent in immaterial sections, things, that is, which the spirit can assimilate to itself.
After which it matters not that the actions, the feelings of this new order of creatures appear to us in the guise of truth, since we have made them our own, since it is in ourselves that they are happening, that they are holding in thrall, while we turn over, feverishly, the pages of the book, our quickened breath and staring eyes.
And once the novelist has brought us to that state, in which, as in all purely mental states, every emotion is multiplied ten-fold, into which his book comes to disturb us as might a dream, but a dream more lucid, and of a more lasting impression than those which come to us in sleep; why, then, for the space of an hour he sets free within us all the joys and sorrows in the world, a few of which, only, we should have to spend years of our actual life in getting to know, and the keenest, the most intense of which would never have been revealed to us because the slow course of their development stops our perception of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This passage struck me as one of those keen expositions of a fact most of us take for granted for which we continue, a hundred years on, to read, admire, and gain wisdom from Proust.
From fiction, we may receive a distillation of the human condition that expands the range of emotional experiences to include ones we may never otherwise know.
It may be this fact that explains the societal impact of &lt;em&gt;Uncle Tom&amp;#8217;s Cabin&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Jungle&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;One Flew Over the Cuckoo&amp;#8217;s Nest&lt;/em&gt;.
The disturbance or joy we feel from novels like &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Pride and Prejudice&lt;/em&gt; owes itself to the same.
Have you ever fallen in love with a fictional character&amp;#8212;not a real, attached sort of love, but from the descriptions of another character&amp;#8217;s love, a parallel, vicarious one?
I know a few people who only read non-fiction claiming the rest is a frivolous waste of time; they either lack Proust&amp;#8217;s insight, or they don&amp;#8217;t value emotional enrichment.
Life as a human consists of competing emotional currents, and the better we understand them, the better we understand ourselves and others.
Emotional enrichment is not only beneficial, but essential to a mature and responsible world-view.
And as Proust eloquently explains, the novel is a particularly powerful vehicle of that&amp;nbsp;enrichment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The passage also provides a motivational seed&amp;#8212;two percent of the way through this magnus opus&amp;#8212;a metaphorical carrot on a stick, tempting the reader to make the effort to continue through the rest.
This is, after all, a novel.
It is a demanding one, but it has already provided such vivid tableaux with the sympathetic expression of an intense emotion which, indeed, I have never known&amp;#8212;or perhaps that I forgot ever having.
A friend who has read &lt;em&gt;Swann&amp;#8217;s Way&lt;/em&gt; remarked that it had some really beautiful moments.
Maybe I do want to be more ambitious and read the entire work.
Maybe my life really will be richer for&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only got a couple pages further before I decided to walk home.
I had enough to think about, and before getting lost in Proust&amp;#8217;s world, before receiving another flood of ideas, before losing my train of thought completely, I wanted to&amp;nbsp;share.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2015-07-20:proust-in-the-park.html</guid><category>humans</category></item><item><title>Stories</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/stories.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of my goals with this blog is to motivate others to share their experiences.
I think there is value to this, especially if you think no one would care about your story.
The fact is, there are people out there who will care.
And it can mean the world to know that they are not alone in their experiences.
So I&amp;#8217;d better set an example and share my&amp;nbsp;own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently left my job at Paperless Post as a Data Scientist/Data Engineer.
Paperless Post boasts a gender-diverse workforce and a refreshingly cooperative culture.
Smart people work there who encourage your ambitions and generously share their knowledge.
The company tries hard to make its employees feel like first-class citizens without implicitly enforcing a particular culture.
I had friends across the company with whom I could chat about anything from tea to opera to history.
I absolutely loved the team we hired.
My teammates were very intelligent, kind, curious people with diverse backgrounds, skills, and interests.
(Also, only one of the four was a man. I was proud of this. I didn&amp;#8217;t make the final hiring decisions, but my input carried some weight.)
I was working on important projects and made our team visible throughout the&amp;nbsp;company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did I&amp;nbsp;leave?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t know the true answer to&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the two months since I gave my notice, my answer to why I left has continually changed, though it was always&amp;nbsp;honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I felt that I had accumulated too much exhaustion and with it negativity, and I was blocking progress more than I was helping.
So I had to remove myself to allow the team to move forward without me as a moody&amp;nbsp;bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I felt that actually, I was doing more than anyone to help my team, but I wasn&amp;#8217;t being allowed the authority I needed to be as effective as I could be.
So I had to remove myself to find a situation where I could realize my full&amp;nbsp;potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I felt that management was honestly trying to fill the gaps and inefficiencies I pointed out, but I was too impatient to see their efforts through.
I was too insecure and weak-willed to express what I and the team needed with sufficient assertiveness.
So I had to remove myself to save myself from frustrations of my own&amp;nbsp;creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I felt that even if I could choose the projects I would spend my time on, the needs of the company were out of step with my interests.
So I had to remove myself so as not to waste the company&amp;#8217;s resources with my&amp;nbsp;disinterest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I felt that everything could have been fine, but I was such an emotional wreck (as evidenced by my rapid weight loss) that I needed more than a vacation to regain my sensibilities.
So I had to remove myself to save my team from absorbing my pessimism and to save myself from falling into deeper&amp;nbsp;depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I feel now?
I think when I gave my notice, all I knew was that I wasn&amp;#8217;t happy and I wasn&amp;#8217;t going to get much happier.
And I wasn&amp;#8217;t even sure of that much.
I think all of the reasons I gave people had truth, and yet none was really true.
There is some research that indicates intuition can actually outperform thoughtful analysis for sufficiently complex problems, particularly when there isn&amp;#8217;t much experience to rely on.
I think my situation was a case of this.
My gut had been telling me to quit for a long time.
It took me a while to&amp;nbsp;listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, that&amp;#8217;s how I remember things.
Memories are funny that way.
They keep &lt;a href="http://discovermagazine.com/2009/jul-aug/03-how-much-of-your-memory-is-true"&gt;rewriting themselves&lt;/a&gt;.
My retelling is honest, but is it true?
Like Nabokov&amp;#8217;s humming Humbert recounting a fictional fiction, how much can I trust my loose, wet&amp;nbsp;memory?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all I can give is a story.
And that story will change again in due time as I imagine myself gaining some hitherto unrealized&amp;nbsp;clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I have no regrets.
A month ago, I was physically weak, anhedonic, and two steps from tears at any moment.
Now I am healthier, visibly happier, and I have a clearer sense of what I need out of life and a career than I have ever had.
I can see where I am, where I want to be, and how I&amp;#8217;ll get there.
I&amp;#8217;m past much, though not all, of the fear that I held before.
I knew before that I would be ok.
Now I believe that I will be&amp;nbsp;ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not bad for a month&amp;#8217;s worth of&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.justalfred.com,2015-07-09:stories.html</guid><category>humans</category></item></channel></rss>