<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Just Alfred</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://blog.justalfred.com/feeds/science.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2013 03:39:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Hypotheses Part 3</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/hypotheses-part-3.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/12/hypotheses-part-3.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/12/hypotheses-part-3.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The professional desk jockeys among my readers have probably all
considered the toll that lifestyle takes on their bodies. Standing desks
are growing as a solution to the slouching and inactivity. This often
works great, but does introduce fatiguing stress to one&amp;#8217;s joints. Others
take to sitting on exercise balls.
&lt;a href="http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/04/12/ask-well-ball-chairs/"&gt;Studies&lt;/a&gt; indicate
that these ball chairs don&amp;#8217;t actually improve posture or provide extra
exercise. My personal experience corroborates this. I think I&amp;#8217;ve hit on
a good compromise, and it&amp;#8217;s a pretty old idea.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just balance something on your head! Find a comfortable position (don&amp;#8217;t
forget to arch your lower back slightly) then stick something on your
head. Now you&amp;#8217;re locked in. Turn your head at your own&amp;nbsp;risk.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can start with something easy like a stuffed animal or a banana.
Then maybe a book. Try balancing a bottle of Scotch while wearing a bike
helmet. Pretty soon, you&amp;#8217;ll be spinning plates on sticks and be straight
as a stick,&amp;nbsp;too.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re worried about looking silly, well, you can go back to sitting
on a&amp;nbsp;ball.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hypothesis is that this idea actually works. I welcome&amp;nbsp;data.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you tend to work on a laptop, consider where your hands
function comfortably and where your natural line of sight is. You&amp;#8217;ll
find the two are rather&amp;nbsp;distant.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2013 03:39:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-12-16:hypotheses-part-3.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category></item><item><title>Nobels</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/nobels.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/09/nobels.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/09/nobels.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what&amp;#8217;s cooler than winning a Nobel Prize? Winning two Nobel
Prizes. How many people have done this since the first award in 1901?
Four. Would you believe that the first was a&amp;nbsp;woman?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Madame Marie Skłodowska-Curie. Born in Poland, died in France. A
pioneering woman in science, her list of achievements is humbling to
even the greatest of geniuses. Her first Nobel was the Physics Prize,
awarded in 1903 alongside Henri Becquerel and her husband, Pierre Curie,
for the discovery of spontaneous radioactivity. (Quick, what&amp;#8217;s the
difference between radiation and radioactivity?) Her second was the
Chemistry Prize in 1911 for the discovery of radium and polonium and the
isolation of the&amp;nbsp;former.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To date, she is the only individual to have won the Nobel Prize in two
different sciences. She was also one of the most generous with the award
money. Her discoveries (and her gender) forced the reconsideration of
well-established beliefs. Her legacy continues in the Curie Institutes
in Paris and Warsaw. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marie_Curie"&gt;And on and on and
on&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8230;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logic, innovation, and temerity are not exclusive to men. As much as we
marvel at modern science and technology, we&amp;#8217;d be much further along if
our culture were not tainted with a latent sexism (and racism, for that
matter). I mention this for two reasons. First, we have wonderful role
models in science to inspire young women. They are shamefully largely
forgotten. Second, if men do not as a whole learn to respect women as
their intellectual equals, then everyone pays a&amp;nbsp;cost.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is not fair, but we can choose to treat others&amp;nbsp;fairly.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2013 14:06:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-09-08:nobels.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category><category>Humans</category></item><item><title>Hypotheses Part 2</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/hypotheses-part-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/08/hypotheses-part-2.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/08/hypotheses-part-2.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fancy bars these days like to serve their cocktails with a single big
chunk of ice. Less surface area means slower cooling means less dilution
of your expensive elixir over time. I don&amp;#8217;t buy&amp;nbsp;it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s my reasoning. Ice serves two purposes in
cocktails. First is to chill liquids, second is to keep those liquids
cold. Let&amp;#8217;s consider these in&amp;nbsp;turn.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At what temperature is ice? Zero degrees Celsius, right? Sometimes. Your
freezer is actually quite a bit colder, so fresh ice from the freezer is
just as cold. Pick up an ice cube with a damp hand, and it will freeze
the water on your fingers and stick. It&amp;#8217;s not very pleasant. But do it
anyway. For science. Ice sitting in a bucket for a while will be pretty
close to zero. You&amp;#8217;ll know it if the ice is&amp;nbsp;wet.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s ignore melting for a moment. We can talk about whiskey stones if
you prefer. Once you drop a cold stone in a room-temperature liquid, the
two will equilibrate in temperature. The liquid chills, and the stone
warms. But the stone doesn&amp;#8217;t warm uniformly. The outside warms up first
and passes this heat inwards. This means the inside of a whiskey stone
or block of ice can be substantially colder than the outside. Every bit
of cooling of the liquid has to come from the stone/ice, so with a
single large chunk, it takes longer to get to the cooling power of the
center, meaning it takes longer to cool the&amp;nbsp;liquid.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s talk about wet ice, so that the whole chunk is at zero or so. Now
all cooling of the liquid results in melting of the ice. Heat from the
liquid causes the ice to transition into a liquid state until the two
reach thermal equilibrium. But for a given volume and initial
temperature of liquid that you&amp;#8217;re chilling, the exact same amount of ice
will melt regardless of its shape. So again, less surface area means the
liquid takes longer to&amp;nbsp;chill.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put these two effects together, and using one large chunk of ice will
leave more cooling power locked in the center of the ice, and more of
the chilling will have to come from melting rather than simple heat
exchange. Result: bigger ice cube = slightly more&amp;nbsp;dilution.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about keeping a drink cold? Now the liquid is presumably at the same
temperature as your ice already. Also presumably, you&amp;#8217;re a distinguished
imbiber and sip your drink slowly. We can ignore simple heat exchange
between ice and liquid here since that will occur quickly compared to
the lifetime of your drink. Now, let&amp;#8217;s compare a glass filled with
crushed ice vs. one big chunk. As the heat enters your glass, it
eventually makes its way to your ice and melts it. Equal amounts of heat
means equal amounts of melting. However, with one big chunk, your drink
can get a little warmer in regions further from the ice. Since the
volume of liquid that needs cooling becomes effectively smaller, less
ice has to melt.&amp;nbsp;Score.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if most of your ice is sitting above the surface of
your drink it&amp;#8217;s chilling not only the liquid, but also the air. Most of
your scotch&amp;#8217;s lifetime will be in this state. Yes, even if the ice were
not sticking shamelessly out, the liquid would be chilling the air, and
end up melting the ice anyway. But it would also have less surface area
and sit lower in the glass resulting in more insulation from warmer&amp;nbsp;air.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are two small, competing effects, and it&amp;#8217;s not clear without
experiment which wins. My guess is that a big, but not huge ice cube is
better here. In part because most people won&amp;#8217;t care much about the
difference between a drink at 0C and&amp;nbsp;3C.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My recommendation: always chill drinks with small ice cubes fresh from
the freezer if possible. For serving, ice cubes from a standard ice cube
tray are probably big enough. Bigger than that, and you&amp;#8217;re just showing
off. If you really hate dilution, get whiskey stones and/or
double-walled glasses. If your glass has a stem, use it so you&amp;#8217;re not
pumping heat from your hands into your drink. If I&amp;#8217;ve left something out
of my analysis, please let me&amp;nbsp;know!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 14:08:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-08-21:hypotheses-part-2.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category></item><item><title>Hypotheses Part 1</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/hypotheses-part-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/07/hypotheses-part-1.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/07/hypotheses-part-1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m going to try again to focus on short-form publishing here. I&amp;#8217;m
starting yet another series of posts called &amp;#8220;Hypotheses&amp;#8221;. I am well
known as having random ideas float through my head. Some of these are
ideas about how some part of existence works. I&amp;#8217;ll share some with you
in this series.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Have you ever marveled at dogs&amp;#8217; olfactory acumen?
Give a bloodhound a sock, and he&amp;#8217;ll find a lost person. Or so the movies
say. Have you also ever marveled at how smelly we can get by the end of
a&amp;nbsp;day?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall that daily showering is a very late phenomenon in the course of
human evolution. We don&amp;#8217;t read perpetual complaints of people stinking
in historical accounts, which means the stench we acquire used to be
easily tolerable. But now we diligently wash away our natural odors
daily, and frequently apply more redolent replacements. Still, how many
of you have learned your partner&amp;#8217;s smell? Not the fragrance worn, but
the natural musk? I am willing to bet most of you. Here&amp;#8217;s my&amp;nbsp;hypothesis:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you grew up in a dark cave your entire life. Having evolved
these exquisitely sensitive light sensors we call eyes, and having never
strained them, stepping into sunlight for the first time would be
overwhelming or excruciating. Maybe it&amp;#8217;s the same with the smell of&amp;nbsp;people.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noses are appreciated as keen chemical sensors, but I posit that we are
evolved to be particularly sensitive to the range of human smells. Our
deprivation of that stimulus leads what used to be a normal and varied
experience to be singularly and intolerably&amp;nbsp;malodorous.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can&amp;#8217;t be too hard to validate or falsify. Try getting stinky with
your most loved one, and tell me how it goes. Trying this with a house
full of roommates would be even better. Some desensitization is
necessary to overcome the initial shock, but maybe by the third or
fourth day, you&amp;#8217;ll start to like it. I bet you&amp;#8217;ll be able to tell
different people apart. You may even be able to tell their moods. But
please do shower if you decide to report to me in&amp;nbsp;person.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2013 18:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-07-27:hypotheses-part-1.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category></item><item><title>Amazing Engineering - Episode 1</title><link>http://blog.justalfred.com/amazing-engineering-episode-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published at: &lt;a href="http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/03/amazing-engineering-episode-1.html"&gt;http://kwontum.blogspot.com/2013/03/amazing-engineering-episode-1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an experimental physicist, I spent more time engineering than doing
science. As a result, I&amp;#8217;ve come to greatly appreciate sophisticated or
clever works of engineering. Sometimes you read about accomplishments
that don&amp;#8217;t seem possible. I&amp;#8217;m starting a series on these sorts of
feats.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name="more"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For the first episode, I&amp;#8217;d like to start with something I first learned
about as an undergrad. See if you can guess what this&amp;nbsp;is:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://d1jqu7g1y74ds1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/sunspot.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://d1jqu7g1y74ds1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/sunspot.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you guessed &amp;#8220;sea creature&amp;#8217;s eye&amp;#8221;, you would be wrong. If you guessed
anything biological, you would be wrong. It&amp;#8217;s actually an extremely
high-resolution image of a sunspot. (By the way, the image was taken
from
&lt;a href="http://www.universetoday.com/71971/amazing-sunspot-image-from-new-solar-telescope/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
article) Here&amp;#8217;s what&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;unique:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astronomical observations almost always involve focusing light of some
sort onto a sensor. But after traveling all the way here in a
more-or-less straight line through mostly nothing, light from the stars
has to pass through our atmosphere. X-rays get scattered like light in a
dusty room, while visible and infrared light get jumbled up from
atmospheric turbulence. Look above a hot car in the summer to see a
strong example of&amp;nbsp;this.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to make up for that is to stick your telescope in space, à la&amp;nbsp;Hubble.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other, more radical way is to correct for the jumbling. That&amp;#8217;s
right. Make a shape-shifting mirror that changes fast and accurately
enough to compensate for the atmosphere&amp;#8217;s messiness, and do it with
enough resolution to matter. It&amp;#8217;s the optical equivalent of
noise-canceling headphones. And it&amp;#8217;s significantly harder. Also, much
more precise. It&amp;#8217;s called Adaptive Optics. And, remarkably, it&amp;#8217;s been in
use since the late&amp;nbsp;90s.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technique involves using a point source in the sky, like a star, as
a reference. The active mirror element continuously changes so as to get
as tight an image of this reference as possible. This improves the
angular resolution of a telescope by a factor of about twenty or so.
Which means what used to be one blob can be resolved into a few hundred
smaller blobs, if they were ever arranged like&amp;nbsp;that.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is no star that&amp;#8217;s bright enough to use, then you can make one.
Lasers are used to illuminate a spot higher up in the atmosphere to use
for reference. Artificial&amp;nbsp;stars!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to look at the sun, though, things are harder for three
reasons. First, heating of the air at ground level worsens the jumbling.
Second, visible light is more susceptible to atmospheric turbulence than
the infrared light that&amp;#8217;s often more interesting for night-time
observations. Third, there&amp;#8217;s no point-like reference star to use, and
it&amp;#8217;s too bright out to make&amp;nbsp;one.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that image above captures quite a lot of engineering magic. It seems
like a given that we&amp;#8217;d have clear images of our closest star, but it
takes something as crazy as adaptive optics to actually achieve it. Oh,
and by the way, this technology has led directly to medical applications
(like improved laser eye surgery), so it&amp;#8217;s another case of pure science
leading to unexpected benefits elsewhere in&amp;nbsp;society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Just Alfred</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 20:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:blog.justalfred.com,2013-03-31:amazing-engineering-episode-1.html</guid><category>The Classical-Kwontum Interface</category><category>Science</category></item></channel></rss>